<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Swarodaya - the way of the breath</title>
    <link>http://swarodaya.com/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Swarodaya - the way of the breath</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 08:57:52 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://swarodaya.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 9</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170917-dhyan-chapter9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170917-dhyan-chapter9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra 1.48 to 1.51&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seedless, higher-state samadhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these last sutras of the first pad, Patanjali takes us to the deeper realms of the subconscious through the practice of intuition. These states are of the higher, seedless-samadhi; the regular practice of which is very important for us to know and realize the purpose of our life. Just like success, samadhi is not a destination. It is journey - the difference is that instead of travelling on rugged and rough, directionless and maze-like roads, the journey is pre-decided, aware and meaningful, in the right direction, on the correct speed, and on the karma-marga (the path of action), taking life to higher levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In continuation of the past sutras, Patanjali says that &amp;lsquo;adhyatma prasad&amp;rsquo; - (our desires and wishes based on the awareness of our capabilities, and strengths) - imparts us with total wisdom. As we understood - &amp;lsquo;wisdom&amp;rsquo; in the past sutras - it is the knowledge arising from deep within, which was not present previously, but has risen for the attainment of our intentions. Patanjali talks about one more aspect of this wisdom - one that is complete with the truth, which can be tested in the practical world, as the knowledge that has meaningful practical applications. The knowledge that cannot be tested, that is not useful towards the attainment of the purpose, the existence or non-existence of that knowledge does not matter. One that is the truth, has an use, and based on the utility of which, all the meaningful discoveries have been made; new discoveries, new inventions, which are practical and useful and the one that gives meaning to life. For success in life, your discoveries, our truth, will build higher pathways for us. Every individual is different. Everyone has their own style of working, after having awareness about ourselves - our approach, our way of working, our method - start to develop and and the awareness of which is the truth filled wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be very different from the knowledge that has been acquired in the past - through seen and heard mediums, and in itself holds a distinct meaning. For whatever you have understood and known earlier, this would be different from it. Since childhood, the religious views and environment of our home, observation of the social norms, education, exposure - all together form our identity. These form impressions and in day-to-day life, form our conditioning. We are made up of these impressions, and live by this identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever in life, when we want to explore new heights or new successes, at that time, we need new impressions and reference points. From where do we get them? The world is limited. At that time, the wisdom obtained through spiritual offeractory, for the attainment of our goals, opens up new dimensions and new pathways. Then new ways, new thinking, new discoveries, drives us to new heights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This state, helps us to create a new world and new impressions, bringing the previous ones to a halt. Then we no longer operate on the old impressions and references. Just like a snake sheds its skin to move ahead, we too, leave the old unwanted thinking and move ahead, completing one’s purpose, and attaining the desired results. When the new impressions gained from the new thinking are removed, and the old impressions are removed too, it creates a new state of seedless samadhi. A state filled with intense deep satisfaction - meaningful with our being, blissful and a state of self-absorption - the state of seedless samadhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of Chapter Nine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this chapter, the translation of the book - &amp;lsquo;Dhyan&amp;rsquo;, comes to an end. For many, this would be the end of the yoga sutra journey, but for me, it marks a new beginning - new and a better understanding of the self and life. Thank you once again, GuruSakha. And a thank you to the reader for being co-travellers of this journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 9 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 8</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170909-dhyan-chapter8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170909-dhyan-chapter8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.42 to 1.47&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spiritual offertory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous sutras, Patanjali discusses about the stability of the mind, peace and clarity. In these sutras, Patanjali takes us one step ahead where, for attaining immense prosperity, success and growth, new models of thought can be generated through the wisdom of mind. The mind is your mate and your minister and it guides you to build and flourish your empire. A mind state, where every decision and every choice can turn profitable and it feels as if the energies of the entire universe is conspiring to help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali terms this mind state as &amp;lsquo;samadhi&amp;rsquo; - where one is absorbed and contained. In the forth coming sutras, Patanjali talks about the four forms of &amp;lsquo;beej-yukt samadhi&amp;rsquo;, their dimensions, and the benefits that can be gained from them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In day-to-day situations, you would have observed that at-times, when you would decide to do a task, and you start to think about it, you get motivated to do something related to it and this leads you into a sequence of tasks.. Lot of options open up without much contemplation and everything gets easy. The clarity to do a task completes 90 percent of the task. You experience ease, peace, and happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In situations opposed to it, you get a feeling of being stuck. Useless thinking, analysis without any meaning blocks your mind. You are unable to think ahead. After spending a while in this situation, you get stressed and you tend to quit the task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sutra, Patanjali discusses a state that is free from such challenges, is meaningful, and that goes beyond logical reasoning. In state beyond this, where, just through practice, talking about the intuitive state, Patanjali says by the clearing the old memories, washing them, you come to feel a state that is present in it’s pure awareness and is free of form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, Patanjali, is talking about intuition and gives clarity on it. By erasing the dust from the old memories, you come to state that is free of logic and is purely intuitive. Many people consider the realizations gained from previous experiences as intuition. Patanjali says that intuition is, when this layer of knowledge clears and washes away. Lets us understand this in detail, as it shall help us in the journey ahead. When we have clarity about this, it is easy of us to work on siddhis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To succeed in any given task, your subconscious guides you every moment. However, logical thinking drives it away and confuses you. The world of the conscious mind constantly interacts, through the five senses and stores these experiences in the subconscious. It gathers all information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when you got hurt and suffer pain, at the time of your getting hurt, the entire scene, as-it-is, in front of your eyes for a moment - it’s color, form, shape, the sounds that were present - even if it is the tune of a song, the screaming of children, the coughing of elders or the laughter of ladies, the smells that were present, the temperature in the environment, the taste in the mouth - all this, gets captured in a moment, gathers and gets compiled in the memory bank (memory). Then in the forth coming moments, with the help of five senses creates a picture based on the gathered information, connects it to the event, and stores it in the memory bank. Like this, all the happy and sad moments that you experience in life, get stored in the memory bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this memory, the thoughts of your life too, start getting shaped and formed. When, anytime in the future, similar sounds or color, taste, environment or temperature, or any of the two experiences occur together, then the mind starts feeling that it is hurt and would be in pain. This response would not be based on thoughts, but feelings. And in such case, would your reaction, be based on the current situation - No!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali talks about clearing the dust of these experiences. By clearing of this dust, one can experience the feel of consciousness. It’s called intuition. Intuition is not what we experience through the controlled functioning of the memory bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the very next sutra, the very same consciousness is experienced in a logic-free way. Patanjali says that in this way we can understand the states of thoughts and thoughtlessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In thought-filled states, in an attempt to bring about solutions, the consciousness entangles one thought to another. You would have observed that some invisible force automatically guides you. One after another, the thoughts lead you to positive and meaningful acts. However in states of thoughtlessness, you are in peace and bliss. The mind is in a joyful state as if involved in play. Or else you can it feels the restlessness that you experience while sitting idle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These experiences are contained within the limitations of natural states of tri-gunas. The natural state indicates the invisible world. The manifested world comprises of the tri-gunas of Rajas, Tamas and Sattwa - and within the balanced state of these three lies the invisible world. One that is not visible. One that has occurred or the one who is yet to occur. Talking about awareness, he states that the subtlety of awareness, it’s realm is not visible, is invisible. If you use the sutra practicality, only then you will get the essence of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever you are making a decision, during the moments of those decision making - the mind or the awareness, passes through three points - &amp;lsquo;bindus&amp;rsquo;. Foremost is about the decisions previously made in these situations in the past ; second would be about the effects of this decision - direct and indirect and third would be about the result of this decision?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In discussions, we may choose to spend a lot of time talking about it, but while making decisions, this happens in a moment. The depth in decision making comes from either the intuition or from experience or from the awareness of the visible and the invisible effects. Through consciousness, the awareness gained of unexpressed state of the gunas, or the thoughts of the same, are always meaningful. beneficial, and useful. The decisions made in absence of intuition are harmful, and failure-causing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laden with awareness, meaning and positivity, the actions and decisions leading to the attainment of goals, can be achieved only through samadhi. Patanjali says that all these four states - nirvitark, savitark, nirvichar and savichar are forms of seeded samadhi (sabeej). When there is a proficiency and efficiency attained of the state of nirvichara, we gain spirituality offertory (prasad).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Beej-yukta (seeded) samadhi ? The meaning of Beej is the presence of subtle thought or intention behind any action or purpose undertaken. The entire universe or manifestation is for one or the other purpose. Desire or intention is the driving force of the world. Without intention, yog or siddhis are just not possible, meaningless, without purpose. Without the intention to experience, the purpose of manifestation is useless and unsuccessful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, every karma has a seed of desire in it. It is this that drives you. It is this secret that Patanjali aims to share in this sutra when he states that all these four samadhis forms are seeded and can be experienced with the seed is intended. By leaving all desires, and without any intention, these cannot be experienced. In the very next sutra, Patanjali takes you to one step forward, with the thought that when proficiency is gained in the state of nirvichara, one gains spiritual offertory(prasad).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through practice, when you experience, that whenever you wish, you can pick up a thought and contemplate about the balance state of Gunas in it, to the manifested state, then you will not hold the thought. You will let it go. Many people hold on to thoughts for the fear of losing them. Then the thought takes the form of a thought-whirl and holds the person. With effort, you learn to grasp and leave the thoughts. And by gaining proficiency in this, one attains spiritual offertory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simple meaning of offertory (prasad) is which is pleasurable, desired, and experiential. The word Adhyatma comes from two words - Adhya - meaning knowledge and Atma meaning information about the self, knowledge about one’s self, about one’s potential and capabilities. You come to know about all that you are capable of. There is no higher knowledge than the knowledge about one’s self. There is no higher happiness than creating the our world with our potential and capabilities. You may make a note of this that it is this what you keep on doing all the time. And you shall be able to gain both, in this state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the foundation, of behind attaining huge successes in life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of Chapter Eight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 8 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 7 Part 2</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170724-dhyan-chapter7-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170724-dhyan-chapter7-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.34 to 1.41&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Effective Methods for Dhyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next method, Patanjali says, to illuminate your thinking you need to focus on the non-depressive thoughts. Such thoughts that are uplifting, blissful, and are illuminating; which do not give you pain, remorse or guilt; are non-negative, and are positive. In these sutras, Patanjali states in Sanskrit - Vishoka va Jyotishmati. As I had received the knowledge of the yog sutras through my Guru orally, I never had any doubt in my mind about them. But many a times in discussions, that these word have been misinterpreted as non-depressive light - meaning &amp;ldquo;tratak&amp;rdquo; to be done on the light of the ghee lamp. This interpretation is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guruji always insisted that Patanjali yog sutras have to be experienced with closed eyes - not with open eyes. And Patanjali Yog Sutra complete the dimension of the inner mind and the states beyond it - it is not about the physical body. Patanjali wants us to transcend beyond the body and to the further states, and not to be limited to the physical body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the word is studied, it is actually - &amp;lsquo;jyotishmati&amp;rsquo; - jyotish va mati. Mati is opinion and Jyotish meaning illuminating &amp;ndash; the one that illuminates. One that illuminates thoughts, gives light, imparts non-depressive thinking and positive thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times, we read some statements that seem to sort out things within; as if some worries are sorted, or as if the mind is lost and suddenly, it starts seeing solutions in a new light. Even by contemplating on such thoughts, one receives the offerings of the chitt - like peace, stability, and clarity. Many such sayings and proverbs can give you such an experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such statement that inspired me for many years is - God grant me the serenity to accept the things, I cannot change; courage to change the things that I can; and wisdom to know the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another such sentence is - Life is as Such. Recall and select such fundamental statements, that are uplifting and help you illuminate your thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the forthcoming sutras, Patanjali shares all the more easy methods with you. By focussing your energy on those who are above attachment of the senses. For the best result of this method, you can choose to focus your attention on those individuals in your circle who are above the attachments of visual and auditory faculties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus your attention on successful and stable personalities. Such as those of whom you can interact and connect on personal basis. If you do not find such people around you, you may choose to focus your attention on concept of Ishwar. However in this sutra, Patanjali, talks about internalizing those personalities who are above ardor and cravings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many a times, we do so unknowingly. For example, in some situations, we tend to remember an elder while doing some work. This is exactly what Patanjali is asking us to do and internalize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In political circles, I tested this method on joint-secretaries and secretaries (who were associated directly with the cabinet ministers), by asking them to internalize the positive emotions of the Minister while making decisions. The secretaries have to make decisions based on the thought that, if the Minister would be the decision maker, what would be the decision of the Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was astonishing. Not only that these secretaries gave beautiful performances, but they also played the best of roles in making meaningful decisions for the country. They received such wonderful appreciative response from their seniors and they got promoted to influential posts. In other fields too, this method gave very astonishing results. Select a few individuals in your vicinity and experience its practical working and internalize it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next method is for advance level sadhaks. However Patanjali shares it at this point. The test of which should be done after three months of experience of the above mentioned methods. If you do it earlier than that, it will take a long time to succeed in it. However you can be clear in your mind that you can jump directly to this technique. Rest all the methods start showing the result in a few days or in a couple of weeks. In this method, you gain clarity within a month and half. For me, with about three years of meditation experience, I gained clarity of this method in a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The method is based on paying attention on knowledge in sleep and dreaming control. It means that the body is asleep and you are aware that you are dreaming. And you would receive the offerings of the consciousness - solutions, peace, clarity and stability - by consciously paying attention on the knowledge accumulated in the dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it is quite surprising that Patanjali mentions this method at this point. For this, Dhyan, Dharana, Samadhi through Sanyam is required, which Patanjali addresses in the third pad. When I shared my thoughts with Guruji, he smilingly admonished me saying the method of extracting knowledge through dreams, has helped many scientists discover many things in dreams. When you do not find solutions through any other method, you shall find them through this method. However, I stuck to my question, and after three years of working on Patanjali, I had put up my view. When I repeated my question again, I was smilingly told - Ask Patanjali!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question, even after 15 years, suprises me. For me, usage of this method should be included in the third pad. That shall make it easy to act upon. By doing it at this stage, is not a challenge, just that it may take longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By stabilizing the mind on any one of the above mentioned methods, practice stopping the thought whirls for at least 15 days. After that, during the 15 minutes of meditation before bedtime, mentally make a ‘dharana’ that you shall make a note of your dreams in your diary when you wake up. Keep a pen and diary handy. You can experience the benefits of making dharana. For example before sleeping, you can decide to wake up at 6 am and be ready by 7 am to leave. In your routine days, even though you may be waking up at 7:30am, but when when you would have made a dharana - you would naturally wake up at 6:00 without any effort. When you are able to practice this method with ease, you shall be able to wake up at the time of your choice without effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In three to four days, by making a ‘dharana’ that you shall realize that you are vaguely able to remember all four of your dreams (yes, we generally have four dreams in a night). Then by putting a date to it, you shall note down your dreams in detail. Stress your mind to try and recall the details. Within 15 days, you will realise that your are able to recall them with ease. When you shall be able to recall your dreams completely with clarity, then, you will make the dharana such that &amp;ndash; in my dreams, I shall remember that I am dreaming! Keep noting your dreams in your diary. And eventually, add a sentence that - In my dreams, I shall be taking a hanky out of my pocket (or any such object for that matter which is not present in the pocket). Taking the red hanky out is the indicator of the fact that this is a dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall the statement several times before sleep. In a week’s time, you shall be able to have the awareness that this is indeed a dream. Put you hand in your pocket, to remove the red hanky and then smilingly put it back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you will be contemplating in your dreams. Recall place, events and subjects. Remember them. If you are not happy with your dream, then in your dreams, closing your eyes, make a dharana saying that I do not wish to see this dream. I wish to see this (the subject of your choice) in the dream. When you shall be able to dream the subject of your choice. Those that address your problems, or those fulfilling your desires; and it can be any! All dreams are in the domain of your subconscious, And then you go back to sleep in your dreams and wake up as per the set alarm and then describe your dream in your diary. Then you may get busy in your daily life. Keep your diary along with you. And whenever you get a chance, read the description in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The knowledge that you receive as an offering imparts peace for the inner mind, clarity and stability. And you receive solutions for those issues, which you fail to receive in daily life. You gain new perspectives in terms of money, success, investment, prosperity, and growth. The limits of knowledge procured from your sleep is limitless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next sutra, Patanjali says, that wherever you focus, wherever your attention is attracted, if you sustain it with awareness, you receive the above mentioned peace, clarity and stability. For practicing of this method, whatever suits you, you may choose to make it the center of your attention. How? For this, you need to understand two things, Patanjali says that it is important, that you choose only one subject as the focus your attention and not, change it. Second is about time. It is not appropriate that as the subject is of your choice, you get in the flow, and not be aware about the time. For then, it is not meditation, it is a habit. It may not hurt you now, but later you may feel guilty about spending much more time than you should have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, choose a subject of your choice, and delve in it. And when the alarm rings after half an hour or an hour, stop it. Music, sports, beautiful faces, golf, reading-writing, chat, it can be anything. But it has to be done for a specific time period only. After a few days of practice, you shall find yourself more focussed, with better concentration and at peace. Throughout the day, for an hour or half, set the alarm and delve into the subject of your choice. You can make your subject of your choice as the medium of your attention. Do this for minimum three months. If you want to change it, you may change the subject after three months. If you change it every weekly or monthly, the experience of meditation shall be delayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schedule and time-bind these methods of meditation. And if possible, even the place. This will help you expedite the process as well as deepen it. To decide the timeframe means that daily at 7am and at 10am &amp;ndash; this is just an example. You may decide as per your convenience. Through these methods, the inner mind, calms, clears and stabilizes. This will provide you the ability to delve deep into important subjects and also shall widen your perspective in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali discusses the ability to think big - on the macro level, as well as think in detail - at the micro level at the same time. Any individual gains prosperity and success as per his ability to think. When the thought is limited or narrow, the person does not progress much. You would have seen many people around you who have a very limited or narrow thinking. Their way of life and their achievements in life are a direct result of their thinking. Sometimes, we are not able to control and we end up reprimanding them to think broader. But just by saying - it does not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says that it is very much possible do so through these methods. Knowingly or unknowingly, when an individual passes through these methods, then their vision starts getting broader. This is such an aspect of the mind, that starts to develop or can be developed. All those who have attained great heights in their lives - such heights that astonishes you - it is based on this aspect of the mind. Let us understand this with an example and then move ahead. Try observing a product with detail, for example a car, or a phone. Let us take an example of the car that is sold the most in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some set of engineers would have designed it, some set of workers would have made it in the factory, while the marketing would have been done by another team. But who made it possible for it to reach the entire world? The one who would be heading the project! For it is his vision that would have been spread to the entire world. The marketing team’s vision would be limited to one or two countries or maximum to a continent. The thinking of the workers would be limited to the factory, while the thinking of the car designer would be limited to the environment in which it has to be driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the vision of the one who heads the project would include the engineer, the manufacturer, the marketing, government rules and regulations, banking, and the world market: it would include all. He is able to think on all the aspects more skillfully than all the other people involved as he is able to include all of them for an important and a huge task. The thought process of the person who is heading &amp;ndash; is macro as well as micro. Patanjali states that the head has a grasp over his mind, that helps him to take the product from small to big heights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali, in this sutra, refers to the ability to see the details as well as the aerial view, or the ability to see things in totality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the thought whirls get emancipated - the weakening of modifications - the inner mind attains the clarity of a diamond. Being receptive, he receives, all that which is worth receiving. A complete balanced is achieved of these three states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By practicing the methods as explained in the previous sutras, the mind attains clarity of a diamond. It is left without conflict or doubt. Hence it is never in dilemma, fear, confusion or a blocked state. It is free from these and is very receptive. The receptivity of the mind is increased. It just absorbs the relevant and leaves a lot of irrelevant behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali say that the balance of the three gives rise to the state of communion. With the clarity of the mind, it gets possible to know that what is it that you want in life. Close the book, and think for a while, about what is it that you want. What is your purpose or aim? What is your target in the next three to five years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make an effort. Close the book and start writing on paper. Then open the book and start to read ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will realize that you have a lot of clarity about the goals of the next 3-5 years. It is about this clarity and these achievements that Patanjali talks about in this Sutra. The clarity to see with, meditate with, and it will start internalizing in you, and you become receptive to whatever you feel suitable, to what gives you happiness and you start to achieve it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of chapter seven, part two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 7 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 7 Part 1</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170717-dhyan-chapter7-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170717-dhyan-chapter7-part1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.34 to 1.41&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Effective Methods for Dhyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these sutras, Patanjali imparts the best and the most effective methods to meditate. These methods are extremely simple, and yet, highly effective when practiced. You will find a huge difference with a few days of practice. Along with meditations, we shall also discuss these methods in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first method involves the practice of observing the pause after the exhalation of breath. This method can be comfortably practiced sitting on the chair, sofa, bed or floor. A few things to be kept in mind while observing your breath -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep your phones switched off for a time of 20 minutes. Request the people around you to not disturb you for 20 minutes. Set an alarm for 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sit crossed legged on the floor or on the bed. Ensure that your spine is well-rested on the backrest of the bed or the wall. The lower back and buttocks should be in contact with the backrest or the wall. This shall ensure that your spine is straight or erect. For comfort, you may use a stiff pillow to sit on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting on the sofa, you have to ensure that it’s back should be such that your back and buttocks are chocked on it. Your legs should not dangle and should be rested on the floor. If needed, you may keep a rest under your feet. Close your eyes and relax your body. Rest your hands on your knees. Focus on your breath as it enters and leaves your nostrils. Feel it as it enters and leaves&amp;hellip; It enters, it leaves&amp;hellip;. Keep observing it for a while. Your mouth should be closed and the breathing should be from the nose. If needed, clean your nose to ensure the uninterrupted flow of breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the method of meditation. Gently exhale and observe the pause after exhalation. Let the breath flow in with ease. Then gently exhale. Observe the pause. Let the breath flow in naturally. After doing this for a few times, focus your entire attention on exhalation and the pause after the exhalation. After 10-12 times, stop making the conscious gentle effort. All your attention should be on the pause that occurs after the exhalation of breath. Observe the pause. As your breath shall become subtle and long, the pause shall gradually extend. Now observe this pause one inch below your navel. Keep observing it. Experience the gradual increase of the pause. Whatever thoughts cross your mind, let them come, however, as soon as you realize, bring your attention back to your navel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the alarm rings, rub your hands. Feeling the warmth, keep them on your eyes, and gently open your eyes. Observe your mental state for a while. Recall this feeling several times of the day so that you can remember it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as you wake up, if you don’t have to run to the washroom, do this exercise sitting on the bed. Or else, complete the needed activities, and then sit for meditation. The relaxed state of the body should be made use of, at such times, hence brush and bath too, can be delayed. This can be also done at night if the consumption of alcohol is not done. Within a period of less than a week, you shall observe the stability within you. Meditate naturally, with ease and relaxation. The body has to be let loose. Should not be thinking about anything else. This is the way this method has to be followed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second method is of contemplation meditation. You can do it anytime and anywhere. Even as you read this. Only thing is to be conscious about your thoughts. Do it now and evaluate your thoughts. This contemplative meditation too binds and stabilizes the mind. In this method, Patanjali says that - Vishay Vatti Pravruttirupana - meaning that by observing the tendencies arising by seeing and hearing, the mind gets stable. The tendencies arising by hearing can also be termed as habit. When these habits, start creating a disconnect within you, it terms of yog, it need addressal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which thought whirls got activated through hearing? Just think about it. What do like listening the most? Let&amp;rsquo;s not think about song and music for a while. Kindly close and and address this question for a while. The book and the eyes closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did you see? A very few people will be able to experience that what they and their ears want to hear, is appreciation. Let us understand the essence of this sutra as Patanjali wants us to. It will help us to contemplate on how to settle the mind in this very moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, when someone, appreciated you whether about your memory or beautiful writing, or your beauty, or your facial features or voice, or your ability to comprehend things, or say anything, you would have remembered it until this day. Some people are such that their actions are based solely on the appreciation that they will receive for themselves. What all you do for the pleasure of the hearing faculty! Sometimes, you will give donations, or at times, you will give special emotion to individuals. And at times, you tend to appear and behave special in front of others. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s us think about this for a while. Try to recall and understand. When you do not receive appreciation for all your dramas, you are in pain. Repeatedly, for the longing of appreciation, the dramas that you do, the thought, an activity - and you&amp;rsquo;re addressing of it, and you&amp;rsquo;re doing of it - itself is a thought whirl. Observation of these shall provide you with a lot of solutions for your problems and the mind shall begin to stabilise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are enacting such, you hardly realise that you are doing so. It just happens. However the anticipation of hearing appreciation makes your restless. And when you do not receive the same, you are upset. Then your words gain the tone, “there is no appreciation ; there is no point doing anything for others ; there is no respect etc”. Be slightly thoughtful and try to get away from this mental suffocation. If possible, for forever. Keep your dramatics for the movies, and if you get better at it, you may try your hand in the movies too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural and calm state of your mind, is your eternal beauty. You shall always be able to feel the emotions that arise in the mind of another for it. Words are not needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same way, the visual pleasures give rise to thought whirls - to see and to show. Do you realise this? Try to observe these thought whirls. To look good, you go to a large extent ; you give a lot of pain to your body ; what not do you care in your diet. And then, seeing your photograph, you comment that this photograph is not a good one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this it because the beauty that you are trying to seek in the photograph, is not present in the photograph, as you are always trying to pose as someone else - as some actor, actress or a politician. The beauty of the photograph lies hidden behind these masks. When you start accepting the self, the way you actually are - fat, thin, whatever your facial features are, the way they are - they are naturally beautiful. And do not be hell bent on changing them. Do not be artificial. Accepting the beauty of the self with your inner mind, and you will have the entire world be gazing at you. When you try and be like someone else, the peace of mind, gets disturbed. The effort to look like someone else, takes you away from your own self. Even if you are able to observe this aspect of yourself, you shall be able to establish in your self. Your stability is your beauty - eternal, loving and mesmerising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The activity of all the five senses combine to give rise to thought whirls. Most of these are such that they cause disturbances within you. Due to this, you shall face conflict and challenges as explained in the previous sutras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other senses like touch, feel and smell, too give rise to similar thought whirls. The addiction of taste to a particular brand also generates thought whirls as when you do not get it, you are in pain. Just think about all those industries that are dependent on the sense of smell. Observe it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can free himself from the pain that enates from the activities of the senses, by just being observant about them and you can save your mental energies and can channelize your senses towards making the life better and can enjoy the experiences of senses to the fullest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sense of touch, is connected with the skin, and is the cause of sensuality. The feel of another to gratify the sense of the self, gives rise to the feelings of sensuality. This can become the cause of pain and melancholy for others. By being aware of your emotions and attitude about the sensations of touch, you shall calm down. The awareness set-in, about it’s enjoyment at the right place, in the right context, and at the right time, which shall prevent you from being disturbed within .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contemplative meditation too brings stability in you, and establishes you and frees you from pain and misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of chapter seven, part one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 7 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 6 Part 2</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170521-dhyan-chapter6-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170521-dhyan-chapter6-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.30 to 1.33&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to retain the experience of God: the meditative state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali shares the secret of being able to remain in states of awareness in day-to-day life. The way is to maintain friendliness with the ones who are happy, compassion towards the ones who are in pain, joy and enthusiasm with the ones who are doing good deeds and equanimity towards the wrong doers. This shall ensure that the mind shall remain at peace, the thoughts shall remain clear, and a state of stability with awareness shall set in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guruji explained these sutras in detail. However at that time, I understood them in an over-view. But today, after 18 years, after testing these sutras, have understood them minutely. Guruji had explained me that there are five types of minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kshipt - insane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moodh - stupid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vikshipt - scattered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ekagra - focussed and skilled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Nirodah - stable and at peace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are known as the five states of the subconscious. The mind behaves based on either one of these states. These can be known as the mind states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kshipt mind is disturbed and insane. If this state worsened, a person is termed as mentally ill and needs medical attention. He does not realize the damage that is caused by his actions. In very intense moments, such people may cause physical harm to themselves. Such conditions are brought under control through medication. Such mind states do not help to achieve something concrete, rather gives rise to survival issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second condition - moodh - the dull stupid - or an underdeveloped mind. Such a mind is incapable to analyse subjects or practical situations of day-to-day life. Such a mind refrains from making social contacts. It has a limited understanding and takes offence on little things in life. On the personal front, such minds are filled with fear. They tend to be overly emotional and end up doing stupid things in life. The graph of success and prosperity of such people face downwards in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vikshipt state scatters the mind in fragments. It gets involved in multi-tasks simultaneously. You would have observed that at times, when you have to attend an important meeting, where there is an allocated limited time to it. In such cases, sometimes, the opposite person unnecessary dabbles with the mobile, or engages in petty conversations (instead of saying that I am in a meeting and shall catch up with you later), or when you are in-midst of an important conversation, he is busy sharing jokes over the sms. Or he leaves for some small task and takes pretty long to return. Although the meeting has been planned for mutual benefit, he is involved at ten different places. In terms of Yog, this is termed as the Vikshipt or the scattered mind. Such people may gain success with a lot of hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets us understand these 5 mind states and then we shall understand how to deal with each of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ekagra mind is the mind that is focussed on the target. Such people are organised, focussed and sorted out in their thoughts. These people gain a lot of success in their lives. Highly successful, above the petty show-off, and are precise in their conversations. They hold deep understanding of their subjects and are skilled at social interactions. People of ekagra minds are good listeners, and are able to express their views with clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individuals with nirodah mind are those whose minds are completely still and stable. The way they talk make you feel stable. Their entire personality feels stable and at peace. In life such people are at the highest position. Even by talking to these people, the mind feel satisfied, clear and inspired. By taking everyone along in their journey, they help everyone around them succeed too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all go through these five states and experience these five states frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kshipt - insane,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moodh - stupid, vikshipt - fragmented, ekagra - focussed and skilled, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nirodah - stable and at peace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you observe the people around you, you shall be very easily recognise these five categories of people around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states that by determining our interactions with these, the offering emanating from our sub-conscious such as - peace, clarity, wisdom and stability - can be maintained always. Now how do we deal with them? There shall be a detail discussion on it in which helps you maintain a state of balance, peace and joy, as well as the experience of God stays with you throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of yog and dhyan, one needs to maintain an emotion of friendliness and compassion with the vikshipt, equanimity and compassion with the moodh and the kshipt, friendliness with ekagra and total dedication with the nirodah. By maintaining this practice, the mind shall be at peace, stable and joyful. Or else the mind is disturbed, sad and restless. Why does this happen so? By clarifying this with day to day examples, we shall move ahead. These sutras are given so much to weightage as the forthcoming sutras, which refer to the method of meditation and samadhi are related to these. To understand them better, it is important to for us to understand these five states of mind. By familiarizing with them, it gets easy to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to maintain friendliness and compassion with the vikshipt, for it will not take long for the vikshipt to be ekagra. If you ignore the fragmented mind, and get annoyed, then this behaviour would be stupid on your part ( for it would be taking offence without a complete understanding the situation)! By getting annoyed, you are entering the phase of the moodh - and fragmenting it further. This is not the method of integration in YOG. Your yogic behaviour should be such that it helps you remain connected with yourself, be within yourself, and which ever situation that you are addressing, you aid in bringing a positive end to it, and not a disruptive one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vikshipt mind state is the one that remains at the maximun situations. Meditation can help bring the vikshipt state to the state of ekagra. Maintaining of friendliness using one’s ekagra or nirodh state of mind, one should try and bring those with vikshipt states to ekagra states. This is the natural law of humanity. Mostly people around you are in this state of mind. One should not keep anger or criticism towards them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moodh and kshipt should be treated with equanimity. Even with animals, we maintain a distance with a fear of being injured with their horn or kicks. In the same way, we can never judge beforehand which action of theirs may cause us harm. A waste of wealth, energy, peace and time happens while dealing with such people. When you become friendly towards the moodh or kshipt - they do not gain anything, however you do end up becoming like them. They do not appreciate or understand your efforts, help or time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maintain your sanity and peace of mind, it is best that for one to maintain an indifference or equanimity. Or else you shall start feeling vikshipt yourself, start taking offence and shall remain disturbed too. If it is not possible to maintain a total indifference, it is important that you spend limited time and bail yourself out of the situation as soon as possible. Although there is very less chance, but if at all, a moodh shows interest and requests for clarifications, then, you can be compassionate and help them reach a state of ekagra. And in the attempt in doing so, chances of them getting angry on you or taking offence cannot not be negated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with an ekagra mind is alert towards his responsibilities, and is dedicated to complete his tasks with enthusiasm. By deciding his targets, he is aware about what he should be doing and what not. Their skill makes them focussed and confident, and at the same time, makes them committed to give their best and this gives them success in life. Best, professional, and giving maximum delivery in a limited time period. One should not worry about maintaining an attitude of friendliness with such people. By maintaining an indifference towards these, it shall be stupidity on your part, and by maintaining compassion for them, you shall be treated indifferent by them, which shall fragment your mind further. Hence the attitude of friendliness shall help you take the best from such people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attitude of joyful dedication should be maintained towards a nirodah mind. Not compassion, nor friendliness nor indifference. By indifference or compassion, you will bring yourself the moodh state and with friendliness, you shall be scattered. But through dedication, you shall never know which treasures you will explore and if not so, the mind shall be ekagra. That is the reason, that there is a tradition to maintain an attitude of dedication and joy towards, Gurus, Saints, Elders and Yogis. After this discussion, understand that you will not find a bigger saint or a yogi in caves than a person, who is involved in the worldly life and is doing his karmas and is in ekagra or nirodah state. The one who has evaded from his worldly responsibilities does not possess even that much of power that he can remain in the world and carry on with his duties. By addressing responsibilities, through the way of a yogi, is the highest form of austerity. Patanjali describes this in detail in the forthcoming sutras. Now the next sutra is on the method of meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 6 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 6 Part 1</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170430-dhyan-chapter6-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170430-dhyan-chapter6-part1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.30 to 1.33&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to retain the experience of God: the meditative state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous sutras, Patanjali discussed the various challenges as - guilt, sadness, doubt, carelessness, laziness, indulgences, illusion, loss of clarity and mental disturbances. These states, disturb and disrupt the subconscious. With faith and dedication towards God, these states can be dissolved. These disturbed states cause mental stress, depression, breathlessness and tremors in the body. Actions conducted in these states do not yield to meaningful results and these results become the cause to depression, breathlessness and disturbances in body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feelings of extreme guilt give rise to disease in the body and mental guilt gives rise to illnesses. The disturbances in the relationships imparts a sense of worthlessness in life, which leads to drinking, and giving rise to liver problems. Lot of self-doubt leads to skin-allergies and lot regret on the actions of the past, leads to itching. Most diseases are caused due to negative emotions in life, different kind of negative emotions give rise to different kinds of problems in different parts of the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadness can be understood as the absence of happiness and fun. The reason behind this is the negative emotion and thought that comes to our minds and settles on it’s surface like a layer of dust. Due to this layer of negativity, the mind is unable to feel the happiness. However, through the experiences of meditations, this layer can be removed and the mind can be restored to its natural state of happiness. An intense state of sadness causes problems of depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fear of losses keeps the mind in doubt and the absence of faith and confidence makes the subconscious doubtful. The ability to make correct decisions and achievements in life is hampered. By keeping trust and faith, it may happen, that you may get cheated once-in-a-while, however it does not happen always. Faith and trust guides your subconscious in those situations, where you are prone to get cheated and in this way, you are saved from losing the prosperity which otherwise you would have lost if you would have heeded to your fears and doubts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carelessness and absence of awareness leads to overconfidence. This too, arises from a disturbed subconscious. Jap (repetition) and Smaran (recall) can help dissolve these challenges. The main cause of laziness is being attached to unorganised thought processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexual indulgence is a natural attribute in a certain age. However for some over-sensitive people, it forms a long lasting inner impression. For such people start living their sexual fantasies anywhere and anytime, which leads to distraction of the mind, and the ability to complete the tasks effectively takes a back seat. The mental energy starts to dissipate and work-effectiveness reduces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation sets in the awareness that the desires of sensual pleasure of touch, based on fantasy, drains away a lot of your mental energies, which could have been utilised to complete a lot of important and pending tasks. With this awareness, an individual can channelize the sexual energy and use it at the right time and at the right place and not at the wrong time and place which leads to mental disturbances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cause for illusion is also the absence of the mature grasping ability of the senses, while the other reason being the mental instability. By being aware of the senses and the activation of the subconscious, these situations are be overcome soon. By only two weeks of meditation, these situations can be overcome and your proficiency in the tasks improves in a way that it is noticeable by others too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali describes the absence of vision as - darshanalabdh. Darshan means vision and Alabdh means the unavailability. Here, vision does not mean the literally seeing through eyes, nor does the unavailability means the incapacity to purchase. Let us understand these two words through example, which shall help us understand the further sutras with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me and my family were visiting universal studios with a few family friends. A discussion started about the benefits of designing or living in a vastu compliant home. Among us, was a business friend who used to follow the rules of vastu and had faith in the system. While among us, was another friend had least interest or exposure of vastu and was not bothered. Both of them lead a successful and prosperous life. Both of them presented their viewpoints. A heated discussion took place with fresh hot snacks as I watched in complete silence. When it got over, I was asked my take on vastu. I opinined that let us have a look at the vastu of the universal studios and then shall continue the discussion in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached the studios and were feeling very good. While have a ride on the train to look at the movie sets, conversations with the studio guide followed. Looking at the capacity of the train and the amount of people on board, a friend commented on the amount in dollars that would be collected by evening, while the other commented on the expenses that would have taken place in making of the place. The third friend was commenting on the beauty of the pictures around, as I wondered on the vastu perspective of the place which made it so successful. One of the friends, who was an engineer was observing the technical aspects of the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same place at the same time was being evaluated by different people from different perspectives, as the kids enjoyed in their own ways. With all this, we ended our day by visiting the Beverly hills and then returned to the hotel in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vastu discussion continued during dinner time with an intention to know my views. I asked my business friend, that today, at the same place, at the same time, why is it that different people talk about different things? He replied that different people belong to different fields and hence they have different thoughts. They have their own perspectives to which I completely agreed. I told him that you run an industry. You also have a driver, and a personal assistant who are mostly with you all the time. Then there is a supplier who supplies you the raw material with which you make your products. However, there is difference between you and them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your awareness - forms your opinions, which forms your perspective. For you, it would be very easy to start another factory business, while for others or rather, even the foreman of your factory, this cannot be thought off - as they lack this perspective. Even if the foreman realizes how to run two machines parallelly, he shall be capable to become a production manager. This can happen with awareness - by having an eye for it. By the practicing vastu, the awareness and perspective, both sharpen, as in it, the five elements of nature are to be synchronized in the space of the building. And hence, such a place has to be decided to reside where the inner wisdom makes decision on your behalf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In absence of this awareness, the individual shall lack perspective - it is this understanding, which Patanjali tries to hint in these sutras. In the past sutras, he explained us how through the medium of meditation, awareness and perspective, can be attained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conscious mind is prone to instability, not the subconscious or the unconscious. The instability gives it the ability to constantly evaluate and analyse. However contrasting thoughts that emanate from the subconscious mind - throw it off balance beyond an extent. This leads to wrong decisions and this lead to direct or indirect losses. Meditations provide depth that imparts stability to the mind. Decisions are not based on logical analysis, but rather on wisdom, and this always leads to beneficial and desired results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conflict and disturbances in the sub-conscious mind gives rise to mental agony and depression. This further causes disturbances in the rhythmic flow of breath, causing breathlessness. This weakens our will power, and at the slightest of stress, the body undergoes tremble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali provides very deep insights in these sutras about the mind-breath connection. The connection between the rhythm of breath and the mental and physical strength. In very stressful situations, the breath becomes heavy and irregular. If you are able to maintain the rhythm of breath, through practice, then you shall be able to overcome very stressful situations and turn them in your favour. The body shall be able to maintain its natural state and you come across as a very influential personality to the opposite person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says that to stop these challenges, one element, one truth, should be meditated upon and practiced regularly. This can be done by understanding the essence of the tatwa, the truth, through the method of meditation, as explained in the forth coming sutras. That one element, or the truth is that which does not hold any doubt or conflict in it. Just like the sound of God, Om or your own breath ; or the light that emanates from fire. That element which has not place of doubt, and only through proper practice it shall be purified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali explains this in depth in the forth coming sutras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be continued&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 6 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 5</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170414-dhyan-chapter5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20170414-dhyan-chapter5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.23 to 1.29&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Experience of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various assumptions about God. However, Patanjali gives us the practical method to experience God in very clear, simple, and few terms. Through this method, the experience of God can occur in a very short time period. What should be the emotion embraced about God and why should one recite &amp;lsquo;OM&amp;rsquo; - these are the few things that Patanjali talks about in these sutras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a state of awareness, the merger with nature and a state of transcending the body is achieved by faith and dedication towards God. God - the Special Purusha - is the one that is beyond and untouched by conflict, karma, and sanskars, and their results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past sutras, Patanjali discussed Purusha-Khayat (Purush Bodh - self realization) and the means by which one can merge with Prakruti through an awareness. The Pure Eternal Purusha is a part of God. However, God is the Special Purusha. In the journey of 5000 years, the word - Param Atma - too become a synonym of it. Dedication and faith towards the specialities of this Purusha also leads to unification with Nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Special Purusha is untouched and unaffected by conflict, karma, and sanskar. Conflict is the condition created by patterns, memories, and impressions in our mind. In addressing this conflict, our actions take the form of Karma. The results gained in addressing them gives rise to new experiences which gives rise to new impressions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speciality of this Purusha - God - is that he is untouched and unaffected by these patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seed of all-knowing is - niratshay - in him. He is the Sanatan Guru of all the Adi Gurus. It is important to understand what it means when we say that the seed of all-knowing is contained within him as this understanding leads to depth in meditation. Niratshay means: beyond which there lies nothing - it is the one that contains everything, within itself - in totality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, there is a building. Then there is the locality whose area includes the building. Then the city, which includes the locality. Then the state and the country which includes the city, and then there is finally the earth and the universal space which includes the country. However there is nothing beyond the universal space that exceeds it. It is in this sense that there is the seed of all-knowing in the Purusha, but in terms of God. It is Niratshay - nothing is beyond it and it is above all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pure consciousness in you contains the seed of all-knowledge and is capable of doing everything. However it has limitations, when compared to God. It is the same as the space inside a home is the part of the space in the universe, and yet has limitations as it is confined to the home. When the home is demolished, this space of the home, shall merge with the infinite space of the universe. In the same way, when the boundary of the body is transcended, one merges with nature and experiences the unlimited joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is the GURU of all the adi-gurus. Kalen Anavechedat means the one which cannot be destroyed with time and cannot perish as it is eternal. He is Adi-Guru of all Gurus. The meaning of Guru can be understood as the one who, with the depth of one’s wisdom, uplifts the wisdom, potential and self-realization in you. As it is the Gravity that holds you to the ground, in the same way, it is the same power that connects you with your own nature. The blessing of the Guru is the one that helps you realize your own pure eternal nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one who, after realizing the self, paves the way for your realization is termed as Guru by Patanjali. The one who is always established in his true nature - pure and eternal. The one who himself is the Vishesh Purusha. The one who is beyond conflict, karma, and impressions. The one who is the Adi Guru to all the other Adi gurus. That is God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Om is the sound of God, by the recitation of which, one can experience God, and it is by this experience of the consciousness, all the obstacles disappear. Patanjali says that Om is his sound reflection. To recite, does not mean verbal recitation. It means mental recitation. Even in the mental recitation, it means mental hearing. Even if you keep on reciting mentally, you may err. Only by hearing the mental recitation of OM, one can experience the eternal God that lies behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try and remember your experience about how much you get receptive while remembering a tune of song. Only after a silent pause, you get the tune clearly. Then its wording, emotion, rhythm, tune and if it is song of a movie, even it’s picture surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In such a deep state, the hearing of the mental recitation of AUM starts to give us the glimpses of the experiences of GOD. At such times, in the pauses of Silence, one needs to turn one’s attention towards the inflow and outflow of breath. Also realise the sound of “A” in the intake, the sound of “U” in the pause and the sound of “M” in the outflow of breath. Very soon, one shall start to experience it very soon. The breath starts becoming deep, long and light. Eventually the awareness of the body and breath is lost and a feeling of oneness with the universe sets in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one mergers with Nature, one experiences the inner consciousness. Then all the obstacles and challenges disappear. These challenges lie in the states of the conscious and the sub-conscious levels. They also exist on the physical and life levels. The inner consciousness starts to fill those empty states due to which all the obstacles and challenges have risen. The inner mind gains peace, clarity, and stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the forthcoming sutras, Patanjali talks about the methods to maintain these states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 4 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 4</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161217-dhyan-chapter4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2016 18:43:37 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161217-dhyan-chapter4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.17 to 1.22&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wisdom through Self-Realization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with self realisation comes a new thought &amp;ndash; new insight &amp;ndash; imparting a &amp;ldquo;wow&amp;rdquo; feel. It feels as if some knot in the mind has been untangled and the mind is lighter, clearer, and is filled with new thoughts. Patanjali defines this state of mind with a new term &amp;ldquo;Sampragyata&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; insight or inner wisdom. Many a times, people consider this to be a state of Samadhi. Although, it is not so. Patanjali understands this state based on his experiences of the initial states of Meditation. Even the one who does not meditate, would have experienced this state many a times. This state can be recreated by choice through regular meditation. Whenever one wishes, one can create it. And it is in this state of mind, that new avenues of success begin to open up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, while talking to someone about our ambitions or goals at a special place &amp;ndash; like a seashore or a golf ground, or while taking off in a flight, or while overlooking the sky from a tall building or a mountain, or while watching little children talking to each other &amp;ndash; a new thought &amp;ndash;  or a new insight opens up a new path for you, and fills you with a new awareness. And, this experience is beyond logic - full of depth, blissful, and insight - that takes you beyond the experiences of the limitations of the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us understand the word &amp;ldquo;Pragya&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; enlightened consciousness, for Patanjali uses it regularly. This word is a combination of two roots. The prefix &amp;ldquo;pra&amp;rdquo; means the external or the one coming from outside, and &amp;ldquo;gya&amp;rdquo;, means the knowing or knowledge. As the word &amp;ldquo;Prabhav&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ndash; influence, can be understood as a &amp;ldquo;Bhav&amp;rdquo;, emanating from &amp;ldquo;Par&amp;rdquo; or something or someone else. So, when we say that in the &amp;ldquo;Prabhav&amp;rdquo; of &amp;ndash; under the influence of &amp;ndash; it is an indication of an external emotion. When we say &amp;ndash; he is a &amp;ldquo;Pravasi&amp;rdquo;, a tourist, we imply that he comes from another place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Pragya &amp;ndash; enlightened consciousness &amp;ndash; can be understood as awareness stemming from an &amp;ldquo;external&amp;rdquo; source &amp;ndash; which was absent previously. If it was present earlier, it would fall in the category of logic. But this is beyond Logic. If it arises from the depths, then it must be deep. If it touches the core, it is blissful. If it has risen from beyond the limitations of the conscious mind, then it would be making you aware of limitlessness of your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per the method explained above, by maintaining this state of awareness, one more state rises where only &amp;ldquo;Sanskar&amp;rdquo; (impressions) are left with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a very beautiful manner, Patanjali makes you aware of the different states of mind, and takes you to the deep states of awareness. In the sutra 1.16, maintenance of this state is indicated, and it does not indicate a pause. The maintenance of this state gives rise to a new state, in which not only sanskar (past impressions) are retained, but an awareness of the self is gained along with the feeling of being merged with Nature. It is a state of being absorbed into Nature; where the awareness of the physical body is lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By following the two methods given by Patanjali in the forthcoming sutras for twice a day, within the span of one week or ten days, different people experience this merging: an experience of being one with the great universe is felt. An experience that is felt in the depths of oceans or close to the waters. An awareness of water is present and a feel of weightlessness is experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the merging with Nature, and after losing the awareness of the physical body, one gets the experiences of the vastness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further on, Patanjali adds that through faith, enthusiasm, memory, absorption (samadhi), and wisdom, this state can be experienced. The method is explained in the forthcoming sutras. With intensity, reaching this state can be expedited. The pace of progress depends on the intensity of the effort made &amp;ndash; whether low, medium, or strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 4 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 3</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161127-dhyan-chapter3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2016 09:55:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161127-dhyan-chapter3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.12 to 1.16&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self realisation through Yog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurring thoughts that surface on the subconscious mind can be controlled with Abhyasa (Practice) and Vairagya (Dispassion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.12 Patanjali Yog Sutra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When, for the first time, I heard this from Guruji, an inner voice echoed saying that this is “impossible”; this cannot happen as I always believed that the flow of thoughts is natural! And also at the same time, got a feeling that &amp;ndash; hope my Guruji is not getting senile! This conversation took place in the year 1993, where along with the study Samkhya Karika, Guruji discussed Patanjali Yog Sutras too. With a smile, he replied, “This is important as well as necessary for you, for this is the first step towards the experience of “Siddhis”. This is also important for you to understand Vastu in depth”. I felt as if he had read my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the forthcoming sutras he commented, “For an understanding of Patanjali Yog sutras, experience of life is needed, which shall come with time. But as of now, you just memorise them and understand. As your subconscious shall pass through various diversities of life, these sutras shall guide you. You are eager, enthusiastic, and have a tendency of taking risks. (I thought that he hinted towards my decision of leaving the profession of software and deciding to learn Vastu in a small village.) But with experience, you shall be able to internalise them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word of the Guru is above all. He answered all my silly questions with patience and ease. The essence of these sutras started to surface. Clarity towards life started to increase with every passing day. Today I realize that his every word was eternal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is 100 percent, a true fact, that by Abhyasa (constant practice) and Vairagya (dispassion), the recurring thoughts can be completely stilled. You shall realize this through the practice of a few days. Patanjali step-by-step helps you establish in beautiful states of the subconscious. Defining every word, internalizing it with clarity, practicing the mind, in the most beautiful and most simple manner explaining Abhyasa and Vairagya and leading it towards self realisation. In this journey of yog sutras, Patanjali does not refer to any external or physical practices. He only refers to subject of the subconscious and the conscious mind. He refers to the body as not a physical form, but a form of the soul. Mere attention of these have to be kept in mind in the complete journey of subconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deliberate effort to establish stability is Abhyasa (practice). Abhyasa does not mean to operate mechanically. But it rather means to insert deliberate effort in it so much so that it comes naturally. Just as with practice in music, the tune and rhythm in music naturally sets in. Or with practice, any act can be performed effortlessly. Then to do it effortlessly becomes the regular practice. And then, practicing this state (of regular practice) with devotion, establishes the process firmly. The method mentioned in the forthcoming sutras help in establishing the practice firmly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali holds a non-dualist opinion about dispassion. He states that by not succumbing to the cravings of matters that are heard or seen, develops a regulated wisdom or understanding. This is dispassion. Dispassion does not mean to give up desires, to stay away from worldly matters, or to give up everything. Usually “dispassion” is wrongly associated with these emotions. Patanjali was the creator of Yog. He states that by maintaining a desire-free approach towards the cravings that arise from matters seen or heard and developing a state of non-indulgence is dispassion. Passion is indulgence. Yog sutras refer to dispassion in this reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In day-to-day life, you do practice this. By paying attention, you shall be able to get the jist of it. By understanding the true meaning, you shall be able to internalize this as well as practice it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, you see a new car (or any other object) or hear about it and there-on stems a craving to own it. Until you don&amp;rsquo;t get it, you tend to remain restless. And once you get it, you treat it with utmost care. If it gets damaged even a bit, you are agitated and disturbed. Till the car remains In perfect condition, the mind is happy. If not, the mind is agitated. This state is the state of indulgence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your emotion should be, “Yes, done. We shall get it”.  Even if you are planning to get it the very next day, you should be continuing with your daily chores without getting diverted, or indulging into emotions related to it. And when you procure the car, even while you are accepting good wishes about the car, your attitude should be composed without flowing into emotions of indulgence or excitement. If there is a scratch on the car, your blood should not boil nor should you be disheartened. You must remain calm. And if someone starts to react, your response should be &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s ok, does not matter. It is not about external responses, but the thought process within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is dispassion; non indulgence. This does not mean giving up of worldly life, desires, or the ambition to move ahead or giving up success and prosperity. As per Patanjali, these are the states of a disturbed mind; not of a focussed one. And in the next sutras, Patanjali talks about attaining beautiful life where all desires are met and wishes are fulfilled. But without submitting to your cravings or remaining away from your indulgences &amp;ndash; as this is required for achieving bigger targets of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a higher state of being, free of indulgence towards all the three gunas (Rajas, Tamas, and Satva) leads to a state of self-realisation. Patanjali uses the word “Purushkhyate”, for self realisation. The meaning of Purush is all-pervasive, eternal, the one that never changes just as the sky or soul. Khyate means to know, to realize. This is the true form of the self &amp;ndash; pure Chaitanya, the Purush Tatwa (element). Prakriti is the Feminine Tatwa (Element). Together, they combine to form the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Patanjali talks about attaining depth in self realisation through various methods. Here onwards, in the journey of Yog, we shall understand the outlook of Patanjali by this definition.. Patanjali states about being free of desires over the three gunas. Let us experience these before we move ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prakriti is tri-gunatmak, and the mind too, is attached to one of these states in permutation or combination. These three Gunas are: Satwa, Rajas, and Tamas. Fundamentally, these are the three states of the subconscious. When established in Satwa, the subconscious is pure, aware and filled with clarity. A mind established in Rajas is in constant flux, looking or asking for some action. A mind established in Tamas is inactive &amp;ndash; unaware and disturbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subconscious is never steady in either of the three states. When in a state filled with awareness and clarity, it is eager to create. And then it goes to an unaware, disturbed, and an inactive state. And as life proceeds, it gets used to being in one of these three states. And continues to remain so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By being an observer, you can experience these states of the subconscious. Or by recalling the experiences of the past, you can understand the three Gunas. Patanjali says, ”In higher state of Vairagya (dispassion), by maintaining a state of non-indulgence towards these situations, you shall be able to know the eternal that stands behind these. And that is your true form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 3 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 2</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161112-dhyan-chapter2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 08:33:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161112-dhyan-chapter2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.5 to 1.11&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are five reasons that take one beyond the control of the self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurring thoughts can be painful as well as non-painful. An example of painful thought can be, when the behaviour of a friend does not meet one’s expectation, or when one gets recurring thoughts of another’s painful behaviour. Or, when you do not get due recognition for your efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These recurring thoughts become the cause of pain in the mind. It can be caused when something bothersome is being done by a co-worker or a subordinate, which, although may not be directly connected to you, it keeps on playing on your mind. And due to it’s continuous play on your mind, you get into a conversation with yourself &amp;ndash; “it should have been like this, not like that”. These kind of thoughts are neither painful nor related to you, but their continuous resurfacing on your mind  prevents you from putting your energy to meaningful tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali categorises these recurring thoughts which take you beyond the realm of the self, into the following five types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perception&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Misperception&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imagination / Conceptualization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sleep / Unawareness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memories (of the past)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Perception:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states that correct perception is based on three factors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sensory Inputs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inferences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Traditional Textual Knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many a times we tend to evaluate people, objects, thoughts, and perspectives. We judge them to be right or wrong. We tend to opinions such as: the prime minister should have done this and not that. Sachin Tendulkar should be playing like this. Lata Ji sang very properly. Children should be behaving like this. Ladies should behave like this as Mata Sita did so. One should not be dressing up like this. He gave a lot of honour and respect. Gave the appropriate. Did the appropriate. Did the inappropriate. Should be done as such. Should not be done as such &amp;ndash; etc. In many aspects of life, life can go on without being judgemental. The same mental energy can be channelized towards meaningful and positive tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thoughts arising in these forms tend to clutter the mind. You end up passing judgment without having a case! There are three reasons behind one holding a correct perception. Either you have seen something as such, or you hold such beliefs, or you have read about it somewhere. Based of these three factors, you judge the right and the wrong, and you go beyond the realm of the self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, even by mere observation of this fact, you tend to start establishing in the self. And when this happens, then onwards, all the decisions made by you are correct. And all your actions yield positive results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Misperception:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason for recurring thoughts is misperceptions. Baseless and false knowledge leads to misperceptions. Due to this reason, life tends to get unnecessarily tense. You are trying to get in touch with a friend. You called him up but he does not answer. You send him a message but do not get a reply. You send him an email, but you know that he has not read it as you have not received a “read” report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You tend to get disturbed and feel neglected by your friend. Why does he do so? You start thinking whether or not you have committed a mistake. However, it does not feel so. You start evaluating all your past associations with him. Then you start to wonder about his well-being. And you message, “All well?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these are nothing but your misperceptions! Baseless and imagined. Just that your friend may be engaged in some important task or thought, so much so without him realising that many days would have passed without having a proper conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such misperceptions, you tend to make your life stressful. So now, when your friend is happy and approaches you to share his happiness with you, then your behaviour gets modified as per the your repeated and recurring thoughts of him in the past. You ignore him and he too realises that he has been ignoring you. However he fails to understand it as he is unaware of his behaviour in that frame of time, and he ends up misinterpreting your behaviour. And this results into painful relationships. Only by developing awareness of misperceptions, your behaviour can remain natural and this awareness opens the eternal doors to your inner understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Imagination / Conceptualization:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third reason is conceptualization. Patanjali states that conceptualised or imagined situations are based on verbal knowledge. In reality, there is no existence of these situations. However we unnecessarily tend to react to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words give forms to those situations which do not exist in reality. Patanjali Yog sutras are older than 5000 years. Until about 100 years ago, it was only through the medium of words, that knowledge was exchanged. Even in today’s day and age, the usage of words is prominent, although in today’s situations, there are other mediums like images that have been associated with the exchange of knowledge. Along with words, images, movies and television also have become a medium of knowledge exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The knowledge arising from these mediums, can be, at times, far-fetched from the reality, and can be the cause of the recurring illusionary thoughts in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poetry, songs, ghazals, movies, TV serials, and many a times, even news, gives rise to imaginary and  illusory knowledge within us. They give rise to a chain of thoughts in the subconscious, that recurringly arises on the surface of the mind. Far fetched from the reality, and without having any existence, such imaginations also take you beyond the control of the self. You will often find people around you who immerse themselves in the characters of songs, movies, so much so even in “Saas-Bahu” TV series &amp;ndash; ultimately creating pain. They lead an existence where they are beyond the control of the self, and reflect the pain ….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By establishing in the self, you can rejoice in the thoughts arising from the verbal knowledge without getting in their flow or without losing control of the self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Sleep / Unawareness:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth reason is unawareness, a state of sleep. An absence of awareness, a state where you are not conscious. A state that is not beneficial as well that becomes a hurdle to making gains in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali terms this cause as sleep. In sleep, there is an absence of awareness. Here he does not refer to the daily action of physical sleep. He refers to a state which is based on the absence of aware and wakefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example you getting mad at someone and commenting &amp;ndash; hope you were not sleeping. Did you not realize it. What is that you are trying to address here by saying that &amp;ndash; where was your attention. You were so unaware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reason is also one of the reasons behind continuously recurring thoughts &amp;ndash; I am unable to understand. I do not understand what to do. Sometimes even without raising these questions, you undergo these emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states that by subduing of these recurring thoughts and by establishing within the self, you are able to overcome these states of unawareness. Then you are able to remain and retain an alert and aware state. Otherwise, in the states of unawareness, you are not even aware of the decisions that you make, which in future creates challenges for you and you regret having made these decisions unconsciously. By subduing of continuous recurring thoughts and by establishing with the self, you are able to create beautiful situations in life. You are able to make great achievements in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Memories (of the past):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Painful or benign; memories are the major cause for recurring thoughts. Our experiences of the past are the reason behind these memories. And sometimes, these leads to painful, aggressive situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The painful, sweet, spicy memories of the experiences recurringly surface on the mind. Especially when words, people, situations, and images related to those memories appear before your eyes. If you are not in the practice of negating them, you get drawn in their flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memories igniting from songs, ghazals, movies, images, faces, and dialogues tend to evoke a feeling and emotion. People tend to be filled with happiness, sadness, or hatred based on these memories. To erase them or to flow in them, people end up drinking. By drinking, these memories get alive. The memories of the past makes people get out of control and undertake different actions. It&amp;rsquo;s acceptable to an extent, but of these memories start to negatively influence your present, and life becomes miserable &amp;ndash; for ourselves and for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To come out of those past memories and the being able to establish in the self, becomes the focal point to move ahead and better in life. It becomes the “feedback” to inspire and rise high in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 2 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 1</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161030-dhyan-chapter1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161030-dhyan-chapter1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.1 to 1.4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yog means &amp;ndash; to stay within yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some thought patterns recur continuously in one&amp;rsquo;s subconscious. For example, if you had an argument with someone during the day, then just before bedtime the entire sequence of events replays on your mind just like a movie. Even though you do not wish to think about it, these thoughts continuously surface in your mind. For example, thoughts like  “he should not have said this”, or “I should have said that”, or “I too tried to explain saying this”, or “why is he saying this?”, or “he should understand”, or “why is he unable to see” etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These recurring thoughts can start to play on your mind at anytime. They may play on your mind like a movie when you are brushing your teeth, or when you bathe, or when you are looking out of the window while driving, and at times when you are engrossed in work. If this flow of thoughts overwhelm you, you may not be able to continue to work. Most people tend to leave their work aside and get lost in these thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says that only by subduing these thoughts, one is able to unite with the self, and that is the definition of Yog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only then is one able to stay within himself. He is united with the self. Until then, he tends to be like his recurring thoughts, where he is always lost in the flow of thoughts and loses his individuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one who is able to see this &amp;ndash; you, the self &amp;ndash; is termed as the “observer” by Patanjali. Just like an observer watching a movie. While listening to melodious songs, an observer tends to substitute himself in the scenes, and starts to dance with the on-screen character. He does this in the cinema hall as well as outside the cinema hall! While watching a movie, a certain impression is formed in the mind of the observer. And when that tends to recur, the observer tends to identify with the movie characters and in doing so, loses his individuality. He becomes like his recurring thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find many a people around you who live the lives of the characters they see in movies. They live the movie character not only while dancing, but also in behaviour, speech, thoughts, and in action too. This makes them lose their identity, and they expect others to treat them as the character that they are living in their minds. When people around them are unaware of the movie impressions, and have not seen the movie, and their behaviour is not as per the expectation, it gives rise to a new set of problems and pains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times when a person has lost his individuality, the methods of Yog can help one observe oneself, which in absence of a Yogic perspective would be difficult to observe. All achievements in life are possible only when one has identified with the self. When one fails to achieve the desired expectations in life, it indicates an absence of identifying with the self &amp;ndash; even if at a subtle level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further on, Patanjali discusses these subtle aspects. When you read about it, you realise that you live with these aspects several times a day. And to overcome them, Patanjali addresses the reason behind the continuous recurrence of thoughts, and then guides us with the techniques to stay within one’s self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 1 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Introduction</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161027-dhyan-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 08:56:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161027-dhyan-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some events change the course of your life in a subtle, yet profound way. For me, one such event of life was being introduced to Patanjali Yog Sutras. During the preparation of the Advance Mahavastu course, KB sir entrusted me with the English translation of Patanjali Yog Sutras. Although it was a mammoth task and took a couple of months to translate, I enjoyed the journey. It helped me understand better the human mind and its workings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali Yog Sutras are aphorisms by Sage Patanjali written circa 400 CE. They rank among the basic philosophical writings of yoga which talk about the methods of self realization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yog Sutras are divided into four chapters, containing in all 196 aphorisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 1: Samadhi pada. In this chapter, Patanjali describes Yog and the ways to attain it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 2: Sadhana Pada. In this chapter, Patanjali shares the instructions for the practice of Yog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3: Vibhuti Pada. Vibhuti is the Sanskrit word for &amp;ldquo;power&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;manifestation&amp;rdquo;. This chapter is about the powers that can be acquired by the practice of yoga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4: Kaivalya Pada. Kaivalya translates to &amp;ldquo;being in Rhythm&amp;rdquo;, which is the ultimate goal of yoga. This chapter describes the process of Kaivalya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a series of nine writings, I attempt to translate the book Dhyaan &amp;ndash; by sir &amp;ndash; which describes the first chapter, &amp;ldquo;Samadhi Pada&amp;rdquo; in depth. Through easy to understand examples and lucid flow of words, this book is recommended reading to all those who wish to understand the essence of Yog sutras. This book is available in Hindi. I share the English translation of the same. In my translations, I have attempted to maintain the essence as I have felt it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to follow along, you can get a copy of the book here at Amazon: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader.🙏&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Videos</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/videos/dummy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 08:56:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/videos/dummy/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 16</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra16/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states, that we shall be able to gain vision of the self, our true nature, of what we actually are, the (purusha), when we are able to curb the desires arising from the three gunas, the satwa, the rajas and the tamas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of tri-gunas has originated from Samkhya philosophy, The closest English translation of this word is “quality”. Sankhaya philosophy states that there are three guṇas, in every aspect of life, in every thought, in every action, These three gunas are sattva (good and constructive), rajas (passionate and active), and tamas (dark and destructive,). All of these three gunas are present in everyone of us and everything we do. The interplay of these gunas defines our character, It translates into our personality, innate nature, our behavior, our actions and our reactions. Our mind is always present in any one of the three gunas. We are living our lives in one of these three states all the time. And no personality or event is exclusisvly belongs to just one of the three gunas. However, when the ssattva guna is prominant, there is love and harmony, when the rajas guna is prominant, there is passion and activity, and when the tamas guna is prominant, there is intertia and lethargy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a mother, when I am teaching my children so that they are able to understand a subject well, learn it well and get a grasp over it, I am living in a sattvic state of mind. As the same mother, when I am encouraging them for activities and competion, when I am teaching them how to write the exam papers in the smartest possible way, when I am teaching them the little tricks and tips to get good grades, I am living in a rajasic state of mind. And as the same mother, when I am scolding them as they did not stand first in their class or they did not score as per my expectations, and I am disturbed and depressed, I am living in a tamasic state of mind!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will influence the personality of my kids accordingly to the guna that is the most dominant in me through out the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is more of sattva guna in my nature, my children will grow up secure, balanced, stable, fearless and natural. As a mother, if I live more in the rajasic mode , my children will grow up to become competative, risk takers, adventurous and aggressive. And, as a mother, if I have a lot of tamas guna dominant in me, I will raise me children to be dependent, attention and approval seeking, distressed and having low levels of energy. I am the same mother, who lives in different states of gunas at different times of the day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says only when we are able transcend the desires that arise from the three gunas, we shall be able to know our true self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tantra: An Introduction</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20160717-tantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2016 09:34:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20160717-tantra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tantra is an ancient method practiced in India by Yogis since ages where through the involvement of the mind, breath, body and senses, expansion of abilities and self awareness takes place. It opens many new dimensions which one would not be aware, otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s fundamental belief stems from the fact that there is one universal consciousness and we and everything that we see, are a part of it. Everything that we see, is interlinked and interconnected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tantra has Sanskrit roots which means to expand and liberate. Through the expansion of our awareness, it liberates us from our limitations and helps us reach our destination with ease!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three schools of Tantra. They have two approaches. The dark approach which scares us to death, and we read things that we fail to understand. And the beautiful aspect that is sublime. Swaryog, my passion, belongs to the second one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beauty of this science is that we need to practically experience it. We need someone to guide us. Books merely do not help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One who has not touched water cannot experience the joy of swimming. But merely by splashing our hands and feet in water, we do not learn swimming. We need someone, who knows how to swim, to take us in the waters, and teach us the strokes, that help us to learn how to swim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you receive the experiences, it gets ingrained in your thoughts and nature, and it becomes a part of you. It becomes you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>