<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog-rsses on Swarodaya - the way of the breath</title>
    <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog-rsses on Swarodaya - the way of the breath</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2016 09:55:52 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://swarodaya.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 3</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161127-dhyan-chapter3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2016 09:55:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161127-dhyan-chapter3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.12 to 1.16&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self realisation through Yog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurring thoughts that surface on the subconscious mind can be controlled with Abhyasa (Practice) and Vairagya (Dispassion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.12 Patanjali Yog Sutra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When, for the first time, I heard this from Guruji, an inner voice echoed saying that this is “impossible”; this cannot happen as I always believed that the flow of thoughts is natural! And also at the same time, got a feeling that &amp;ndash; hope my Guruji is not getting senile! This conversation took place in the year 1993, where along with the study Samkhya Karika, Guruji discussed Patanjali Yog Sutras too. With a smile, he replied, “This is important as well as necessary for you, for this is the first step towards the experience of “Siddhis”. This is also important for you to understand Vastu in depth”. I felt as if he had read my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the forthcoming sutras he commented, “For an understanding of Patanjali Yog sutras, experience of life is needed, which shall come with time. But as of now, you just memorise them and understand. As your subconscious shall pass through various diversities of life, these sutras shall guide you. You are eager, enthusiastic, and have a tendency of taking risks. (I thought that he hinted towards my decision of leaving the profession of software and deciding to learn Vastu in a small village.) But with experience, you shall be able to internalise them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word of the Guru is above all. He answered all my silly questions with patience and ease. The essence of these sutras started to surface. Clarity towards life started to increase with every passing day. Today I realize that his every word was eternal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is 100 percent, a true fact, that by Abhyasa (constant practice) and Vairagya (dispassion), the recurring thoughts can be completely stilled. You shall realize this through the practice of a few days. Patanjali step-by-step helps you establish in beautiful states of the subconscious. Defining every word, internalizing it with clarity, practicing the mind, in the most beautiful and most simple manner explaining Abhyasa and Vairagya and leading it towards self realisation. In this journey of yog sutras, Patanjali does not refer to any external or physical practices. He only refers to subject of the subconscious and the conscious mind. He refers to the body as not a physical form, but a form of the soul. Mere attention of these have to be kept in mind in the complete journey of subconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deliberate effort to establish stability is Abhyasa (practice). Abhyasa does not mean to operate mechanically. But it rather means to insert deliberate effort in it so much so that it comes naturally. Just as with practice in music, the tune and rhythm in music naturally sets in. Or with practice, any act can be performed effortlessly. Then to do it effortlessly becomes the regular practice. And then, practicing this state (of regular practice) with devotion, establishes the process firmly. The method mentioned in the forthcoming sutras help in establishing the practice firmly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali holds a non-dualist opinion about dispassion. He states that by not succumbing to the cravings of matters that are heard or seen, develops a regulated wisdom or understanding. This is dispassion. Dispassion does not mean to give up desires, to stay away from worldly matters, or to give up everything. Usually “dispassion” is wrongly associated with these emotions. Patanjali was the creator of Yog. He states that by maintaining a desire-free approach towards the cravings that arise from matters seen or heard and developing a state of non-indulgence is dispassion. Passion is indulgence. Yog sutras refer to dispassion in this reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In day-to-day life, you do practice this. By paying attention, you shall be able to get the jist of it. By understanding the true meaning, you shall be able to internalize this as well as practice it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, you see a new car (or any other object) or hear about it and there-on stems a craving to own it. Until you don&amp;rsquo;t get it, you tend to remain restless. And once you get it, you treat it with utmost care. If it gets damaged even a bit, you are agitated and disturbed. Till the car remains In perfect condition, the mind is happy. If not, the mind is agitated. This state is the state of indulgence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your emotion should be, “Yes, done. We shall get it”.  Even if you are planning to get it the very next day, you should be continuing with your daily chores without getting diverted, or indulging into emotions related to it. And when you procure the car, even while you are accepting good wishes about the car, your attitude should be composed without flowing into emotions of indulgence or excitement. If there is a scratch on the car, your blood should not boil nor should you be disheartened. You must remain calm. And if someone starts to react, your response should be &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s ok, does not matter. It is not about external responses, but the thought process within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is dispassion; non indulgence. This does not mean giving up of worldly life, desires, or the ambition to move ahead or giving up success and prosperity. As per Patanjali, these are the states of a disturbed mind; not of a focussed one. And in the next sutras, Patanjali talks about attaining beautiful life where all desires are met and wishes are fulfilled. But without submitting to your cravings or remaining away from your indulgences &amp;ndash; as this is required for achieving bigger targets of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a higher state of being, free of indulgence towards all the three gunas (Rajas, Tamas, and Satva) leads to a state of self-realisation. Patanjali uses the word “Purushkhyate”, for self realisation. The meaning of Purush is all-pervasive, eternal, the one that never changes just as the sky or soul. Khyate means to know, to realize. This is the true form of the self &amp;ndash; pure Chaitanya, the Purush Tatwa (element). Prakriti is the Feminine Tatwa (Element). Together, they combine to form the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Patanjali talks about attaining depth in self realisation through various methods. Here onwards, in the journey of Yog, we shall understand the outlook of Patanjali by this definition.. Patanjali states about being free of desires over the three gunas. Let us experience these before we move ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prakriti is tri-gunatmak, and the mind too, is attached to one of these states in permutation or combination. These three Gunas are: Satwa, Rajas, and Tamas. Fundamentally, these are the three states of the subconscious. When established in Satwa, the subconscious is pure, aware and filled with clarity. A mind established in Rajas is in constant flux, looking or asking for some action. A mind established in Tamas is inactive &amp;ndash; unaware and disturbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subconscious is never steady in either of the three states. When in a state filled with awareness and clarity, it is eager to create. And then it goes to an unaware, disturbed, and an inactive state. And as life proceeds, it gets used to being in one of these three states. And continues to remain so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By being an observer, you can experience these states of the subconscious. Or by recalling the experiences of the past, you can understand the three Gunas. Patanjali says, ”In higher state of Vairagya (dispassion), by maintaining a state of non-indulgence towards these situations, you shall be able to know the eternal that stands behind these. And that is your true form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader.🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 3 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 2</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161112-dhyan-chapter2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 08:33:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161112-dhyan-chapter2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.5 to 1.11&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are five reasons that take one beyond the control of the self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recurring thoughts can be painful as well as non-painful. An example of painful thought can be, when the behaviour of a friend does not meet one’s expectation, or when one gets recurring thoughts of another’s painful behaviour. Or, when you do not get due recognition for your efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These recurring thoughts become the cause of pain in the mind. It can be caused when something bothersome is being done by a co-worker or a subordinate, which, although may not be directly connected to you, it keeps on playing on your mind. And due to it’s continuous play on your mind, you get into a conversation with yourself &amp;ndash; “it should have been like this, not like that”. These kind of thoughts are neither painful nor related to you, but their continuous resurfacing on your mind  prevents you from putting your energy to meaningful tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali categorises these recurring thoughts which take you beyond the realm of the self, into the following five types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perception&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Misperception&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imagination / Conceptualization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sleep / Unawareness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memories (of the past)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Perception:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states that correct perception is based on three factors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sensory Inputs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inferences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Traditional Textual Knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many a times we tend to evaluate people, objects, thoughts, and perspectives. We judge them to be right or wrong. We tend to opinions such as: the prime minister should have done this and not that. Sachin Tendulkar should be playing like this. Lata Ji sang very properly. Children should be behaving like this. Ladies should behave like this as Mata Sita did so. One should not be dressing up like this. He gave a lot of honour and respect. Gave the appropriate. Did the appropriate. Did the inappropriate. Should be done as such. Should not be done as such &amp;ndash; etc. In many aspects of life, life can go on without being judgemental. The same mental energy can be channelized towards meaningful and positive tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thoughts arising in these forms tend to clutter the mind. You end up passing judgment without having a case! There are three reasons behind one holding a correct perception. Either you have seen something as such, or you hold such beliefs, or you have read about it somewhere. Based of these three factors, you judge the right and the wrong, and you go beyond the realm of the self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, even by mere observation of this fact, you tend to start establishing in the self. And when this happens, then onwards, all the decisions made by you are correct. And all your actions yield positive results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Misperception:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason for recurring thoughts is misperceptions. Baseless and false knowledge leads to misperceptions. Due to this reason, life tends to get unnecessarily tense. You are trying to get in touch with a friend. You called him up but he does not answer. You send him a message but do not get a reply. You send him an email, but you know that he has not read it as you have not received a “read” report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You tend to get disturbed and feel neglected by your friend. Why does he do so? You start thinking whether or not you have committed a mistake. However, it does not feel so. You start evaluating all your past associations with him. Then you start to wonder about his well-being. And you message, “All well?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these are nothing but your misperceptions! Baseless and imagined. Just that your friend may be engaged in some important task or thought, so much so without him realising that many days would have passed without having a proper conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such misperceptions, you tend to make your life stressful. So now, when your friend is happy and approaches you to share his happiness with you, then your behaviour gets modified as per the your repeated and recurring thoughts of him in the past. You ignore him and he too realises that he has been ignoring you. However he fails to understand it as he is unaware of his behaviour in that frame of time, and he ends up misinterpreting your behaviour. And this results into painful relationships. Only by developing awareness of misperceptions, your behaviour can remain natural and this awareness opens the eternal doors to your inner understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Imagination / Conceptualization:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third reason is conceptualization. Patanjali states that conceptualised or imagined situations are based on verbal knowledge. In reality, there is no existence of these situations. However we unnecessarily tend to react to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words give forms to those situations which do not exist in reality. Patanjali Yog sutras are older than 5000 years. Until about 100 years ago, it was only through the medium of words, that knowledge was exchanged. Even in today’s day and age, the usage of words is prominent, although in today’s situations, there are other mediums like images that have been associated with the exchange of knowledge. Along with words, images, movies and television also have become a medium of knowledge exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The knowledge arising from these mediums, can be, at times, far-fetched from the reality, and can be the cause of the recurring illusionary thoughts in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poetry, songs, ghazals, movies, TV serials, and many a times, even news, gives rise to imaginary and  illusory knowledge within us. They give rise to a chain of thoughts in the subconscious, that recurringly arises on the surface of the mind. Far fetched from the reality, and without having any existence, such imaginations also take you beyond the control of the self. You will often find people around you who immerse themselves in the characters of songs, movies, so much so even in “Saas-Bahu” TV series &amp;ndash; ultimately creating pain. They lead an existence where they are beyond the control of the self, and reflect the pain ….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By establishing in the self, you can rejoice in the thoughts arising from the verbal knowledge without getting in their flow or without losing control of the self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Sleep / Unawareness:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth reason is unawareness, a state of sleep. An absence of awareness, a state where you are not conscious. A state that is not beneficial as well that becomes a hurdle to making gains in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali terms this cause as sleep. In sleep, there is an absence of awareness. Here he does not refer to the daily action of physical sleep. He refers to a state which is based on the absence of aware and wakefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example you getting mad at someone and commenting &amp;ndash; hope you were not sleeping. Did you not realize it. What is that you are trying to address here by saying that &amp;ndash; where was your attention. You were so unaware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reason is also one of the reasons behind continuously recurring thoughts &amp;ndash; I am unable to understand. I do not understand what to do. Sometimes even without raising these questions, you undergo these emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states that by subduing of these recurring thoughts and by establishing within the self, you are able to overcome these states of unawareness. Then you are able to remain and retain an alert and aware state. Otherwise, in the states of unawareness, you are not even aware of the decisions that you make, which in future creates challenges for you and you regret having made these decisions unconsciously. By subduing of continuous recurring thoughts and by establishing with the self, you are able to create beautiful situations in life. You are able to make great achievements in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Memories (of the past):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Painful or benign; memories are the major cause for recurring thoughts. Our experiences of the past are the reason behind these memories. And sometimes, these leads to painful, aggressive situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The painful, sweet, spicy memories of the experiences recurringly surface on the mind. Especially when words, people, situations, and images related to those memories appear before your eyes. If you are not in the practice of negating them, you get drawn in their flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memories igniting from songs, ghazals, movies, images, faces, and dialogues tend to evoke a feeling and emotion. People tend to be filled with happiness, sadness, or hatred based on these memories. To erase them or to flow in them, people end up drinking. By drinking, these memories get alive. The memories of the past makes people get out of control and undertake different actions. It&amp;rsquo;s acceptable to an extent, but of these memories start to negatively influence your present, and life becomes miserable &amp;ndash; for ourselves and for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To come out of those past memories and the being able to establish in the self, becomes the focal point to move ahead and better in life. It becomes the “feedback” to inspire and rise high in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader.🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 2 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 1</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161030-dhyan-chapter1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161030-dhyan-chapter1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.1 to 1.4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yog means &amp;ndash; to stay within yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some thought patterns recur continuously in one&amp;rsquo;s subconscious. For example, if you had an argument with someone during the day, then just before bedtime the entire sequence of events replays on your mind just like a movie. Even though you do not wish to think about it, these thoughts continuously surface in your mind. For example, thoughts like  “he should not have said this”, or “I should have said that”, or “I too tried to explain saying this”, or “why is he saying this?”, or “he should understand”, or “why is he unable to see” etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These recurring thoughts can start to play on your mind at anytime. They may play on your mind like a movie when you are brushing your teeth, or when you bathe, or when you are looking out of the window while driving, and at times when you are engrossed in work. If this flow of thoughts overwhelm you, you may not be able to continue to work. Most people tend to leave their work aside and get lost in these thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says that only by subduing these thoughts, one is able to unite with the self, and that is the definition of Yog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only then is one able to stay within himself. He is united with the self. Until then, he tends to be like his recurring thoughts, where he is always lost in the flow of thoughts and loses his individuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one who is able to see this &amp;ndash; you, the self &amp;ndash; is termed as the “observer” by Patanjali. Just like an observer watching a movie. While listening to melodious songs, an observer tends to substitute himself in the scenes, and starts to dance with the on-screen character. He does this in the cinema hall as well as outside the cinema hall! While watching a movie, a certain impression is formed in the mind of the observer. And when that tends to recur, the observer tends to identify with the movie characters and in doing so, loses his individuality. He becomes like his recurring thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find many a people around you who live the lives of the characters they see in movies. They live the movie character not only while dancing, but also in behaviour, speech, thoughts, and in action too. This makes them lose their identity, and they expect others to treat them as the character that they are living in their minds. When people around them are unaware of the movie impressions, and have not seen the movie, and their behaviour is not as per the expectation, it gives rise to a new set of problems and pains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times when a person has lost his individuality, the methods of Yog can help one observe oneself, which in absence of a Yogic perspective would be difficult to observe. All achievements in life are possible only when one has identified with the self. When one fails to achieve the desired expectations in life, it indicates an absence of identifying with the self &amp;ndash; even if at a subtle level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further on, Patanjali discusses these subtle aspects. When you read about it, you realise that you live with these aspects several times a day. And to overcome them, Patanjali addresses the reason behind the continuous recurrence of thoughts, and then guides us with the techniques to stay within one’s self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader.🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 1 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Introduction</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161027-dhyan-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 08:56:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/20161027-dhyan-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some events change the course of your life in a subtle, yet profound way. For me, one such event of life was being introduced to Patanjali Yog Sutras. During the preparation of the Advance Mahavastu course, KB sir entrusted me with the English translation of Patanjali Yog Sutras. Although it was a mammoth task and took a couple of months to translate, I enjoyed the journey. It helped me understand better the human mind and its workings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali Yog Sutras are aphorisms by Sage Patanjali written circa 400 CE. They rank among the basic philosophical writings of yoga which talk about the methods of self realization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yog Sutras are divided into four chapters, containing in all 196 aphorisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 1: Samadhi pada. In this chapter, Patanjali describes Yog and the ways to attain it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 2: Sadhana Pada. In this chapter, Patanjali shares the instructions for the practice of Yog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3: Vibhuti Pada. Vibhuti is the Sanskrit word for &amp;ldquo;power&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;manifestation&amp;rdquo;. This chapter is about the powers that can be acquired by the practice of yoga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4: Kaivalya Pada. Kaivalya translates to &amp;ldquo;being in Rhythm&amp;rdquo;, which is the ultimate goal of yoga. This chapter describes the process of Kaivalya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a series of nine writings, I attempt to translate the book Dhyaan &amp;ndash; by sir &amp;ndash; which describes the first chapter, &amp;ldquo;Samadhi Pada&amp;rdquo; in depth. Through easy to understand examples and lucid flow of words, this book is recommended reading to all those who wish to understand the essence of Yog sutras. This book is available in Hindi. I share the English translation of the same. In my translations, I have attempted to maintain the essence as I have felt it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to follow along, you can get a copy of the book here at Amazon: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader.🙏&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 16</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra16/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states, that we shall be able to gain vision of the self, our true nature, of what we actually are, the (purusha), when we are able to curb the desires arising from the three gunas, the satwa, the rajas and the tamas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of tri-gunas has originated from Samkhya philosophy, The closest English translation of this word is “quality”. Sankhaya philosophy states that there are three guṇas, in every aspect of life, in every thought, in every action, These three gunas are sattva (good and constructive), rajas (passionate and active), and tamas (dark and destructive,). All of these three gunas are present in everyone of us and everything we do. The interplay of these gunas defines our character, It translates into our personality, innate nature, our behavior, our actions and our reactions. Our mind is always present in any one of the three gunas. We are living our lives in one of these three states all the time. And no personality or event is exclusisvly belongs to just one of the three gunas. However, when the ssattva guna is prominant, there is love and harmony, when the rajas guna is prominant, there is passion and activity, and when the tamas guna is prominant, there is intertia and lethargy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a mother, when I am teaching my children so that they are able to understand a subject well, learn it well and get a grasp over it, I am living in a sattvic state of mind. As the same mother, when I am encouraging them for activities and competion, when I am teaching them how to write the exam papers in the smartest possible way, when I am teaching them the little tricks and tips to get good grades, I am living in a rajasic state of mind. And as the same mother, when I am scolding them as they did not stand first in their class or they did not score as per my expectations, and I am disturbed and depressed, I am living in a tamasic state of mind!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will influence the personality of my kids accordingly to the guna that is the most dominant in me through out the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is more of sattva guna in my nature, my children will grow up secure, balanced, stable, fearless and natural. As a mother, if I live more in the rajasic mode , my children will grow up to become competative, risk takers, adventurous and aggressive. And, as a mother, if I have a lot of tamas guna dominant in me, I will raise me children to be dependent, attention and approval seeking, distressed and having low levels of energy. I am the same mother, who lives in different states of gunas at different times of the day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says only when we are able transcend the desires that arise from the three gunas, we shall be able to know our true self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 15</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states, that we shall be able to gain vision of the self, our true nature, of what we actually are, the (purusha), when we are able to curb the desires arising from the three gunas, the satwa, the rajas and the tamas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of tri-gunas has originated from Samkhya philosophy, The closest English translation of this word is “quality”. Sankhaya philosophy states that there are three guṇas, in every aspect of life, in every thought, in every action, These three gunas are sattva (good and constructive), rajas (passionate and active), and tamas (dark and destructive,). All of these three gunas are present in everyone of us and everything we do. The interplay of these gunas defines our character, It translates into our personality, innate nature, our behavior, our actions and our reactions. Our mind is always present in any one of the three gunas. We are living our lives in one of these three states all the time. And no personality or event is exclusisvly belongs to just one of the three gunas. However, when the ssattva guna is prominant, there is love and harmony, when the rajas guna is prominant, there is passion and activity, and when the tamas guna is prominant, there is intertia and lethargy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a mother, when I am teaching my children so that they are able to understand a subject well, learn it well and get a grasp over it, I am living in a sattvic state of mind. As the same mother, when I am encouraging them for activities and competion, when I am teaching them how to write the exam papers in the smartest possible way, when I am teaching them the little tricks and tips to get good grades, I am living in a rajasic state of mind. And as the same mother, when I am scolding them as they did not stand first in their class or they did not score as per my expectations, and I am disturbed and depressed, I am living in a tamasic state of mind!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will influence the personality of my kids accordingly to the guna that is the most dominant in me through out the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is more of sattva guna in my nature, my children will grow up secure, balanced, stable, fearless and natural. As a mother, if I live more in the rajasic mode , my children will grow up to become competative, risk takers, adventurous and aggressive. And, as a mother, if I have a lot of tamas guna dominant in me, I will raise me children to be dependent, attention and approval seeking, distressed and having low levels of energy. I am the same mother, who lives in different states of gunas at different times of the day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says only when we are able transcend the desires that arise from the three gunas, we shall be able to know our true self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 14</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra14/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sah tu dirgha kala nairantaira satkara asevitah dridha bhumih&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persistent and continues practice, with devotion, establishes a firm foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After explaining the importance of unbiased practice, for controlling the fluctuations of the mind, Patanjali states that continuous practice with effort and devotion, is the way to establishes a firm rooted foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his book Outliers, author Malcolm Gladwell, says that it takes roughly ten thousand hours of practice to achieve mastery in a field. After studying the lives of extremely successful people to find out how they achieved succes, the psychologists found a direct relationship between hours of practice and achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that Microsoft was founded by Bill Gates and Paul Allen. But many of us dont know that Gates and Allen had done thousands of hours of programming practice prior to the founding of Microsoft. The Beatles, for years, played eight hours per night, seven nights per week. The Beatles had played over 1,200 concerts together!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In plain words, Patanjali is asking us to fall in love with our interests and living it 24x7! People who are sucessful in any fied, are not always born gifted. But they are in love with what ever they are doing and live their subject all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we start living a subject, we see start seeing patterns in it. We start seeing clues everywhere and it seems that the entire universe comes to help us achieve our goal. We start seeing twists and turns in it that were hiding in plain sight. Those revaltions of the subject come to us, which were otherwise impossible to grasp. All this and much more. Everything else stops to matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so the next time, when we see someone doing something, that we think is amazing, and get a feel that we are not able to it, stop for a moment, and ask, whether is that person doing something that we are not? And if we, too, want to do the same. are we putting enough of hard work? Are we in love with the subject? Are we living it 24x7? Has it become our passion, our obsession?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;apne aap se puchiye, kya apme woh junnon hai?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,
&lt;em&gt;sah tu dirgha kala nairantaira satkara asevitah dridha bhumih&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persistent and continous practice, with devotion, establishes a firm foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 13</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra13/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tatra sthitau yatnah abhyasa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A practice, which is a deliberate effort to bring stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After stating in the previous sutras that continuous unbiased practice, is the way to control the thought whirls, in this sutra, Patanjali explains that deliberate practice of doing so, shall result into a stable mind. Here, Abhyasa refers, not just to mechanical efforts. It is an effort with your complete head and heart are involved. And it is done to such an extent, where it comes to a state where it gets effortless. And when we are able to do it effortlessly, it results into that state of mind, where the mind is at peace and is free from fluctuations and disturbances. It results into a stable mind. And only a stable mind will be able to find solutions from the sub-conscious! Only a stable mind is capable of those observations which we fail to perceive in normal day to day situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Steve Jobs once commented to his biographer,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you just sit and observe, you will see how restless your mind is if you try to calm it, it only makes things worse, but over time it does calm, and when it does, there’s room to hear more subtle things - that’s when your intuition starts to blossom and you start to see things more clearly and be in the present more. Your mind just slows down, and you see a tremendous expanse in the moment. You see so much more than you could see before. It’s a discipline; you have to practice it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing a popular story of General Motors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, the Pontiac Division of General Motors received a complaint:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our family, we have a tradition of having ice cream for desert after dinner each night. Every night, after we’ve eaten, whenever I drive down to our local store to buy icecream and choose to buy Vanilla flavor, my car does not start! But if I buy some other flavor, it works fine!.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However insane it sounded, the engineer arranged to meet the man just after dinner time – and the two drove to the ice cream store ever night. On the days, they decided to order vanilla, the car would not restart, or else, everything would be just fine..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engineer now realised that there was a problem that needed identification and fixing. He started to log what happened from the moment they arrived at the store – arrival time, time taken to make the purchase, and several other factors. Soon he had a clue – purchases of vanilla ice cream took less time than the other flavours. The reason was that the freezer containing vanilla ice cream was at the front of the store near a quick purchase till, while other flavours were at the back and required lining up to get checked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quickly the engineer realised that this was the answer to the problem – not the ice cream flavour, but the time required. When purchasing vanilla ice cream there was a vapour lock which prevented the car restarting. With the other flavours, there was sufficient time for the engine to cool down, allowing vapour to dissipate and the car to restart….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so Patanjali says, only and only, if you are capable of observation, you would be able to see situations from a different angle, and only and only, if you are able to see things differently, you will be capable of bring better solutions to them and create a better life for your self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tatra sthitau yatnah abhyasa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A practice, which is a deliberate effort to bring stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 12</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra12/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;abhyasa vairagyabhyam tat nirodhah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These can be stopped by unbiased practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After explaining the five reasons for thought whirls, Patanjali shares the method to stop them. He suggests unbiased practice. He uses the term abhyasa and vairagya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abhyasa is when something is done with persistent effort for a long time. After long term practise, the activity gets effortless and with passing time, the individual is able to perform it with excellence and ease. With repetition, the performance of a task comes naturally to a person and one is able to reproduce it with excellence from time to time. It becomes his second nature. This is Abhyasa. When practicing, or while doing Abhyasa, he asks the practitioner observe Vajragya, remain non-biased or non-attached. Non-attachment or non-biasedness to external factors, to the various aspects where Abhyasa is involved. Becoming non-attached to all those factors that may cause of the Abhyasa, practice to break, or be disturbed, that may result in imperfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between Abhyasa and Vajragya is that the Abhyasa, is an inward journey, while Vajragya, is cutting out the external distractions to make that inward journey smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets understand this with an example of a sport person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a child enrols in a sports academy, he is asked to continues practice for hours. Starting from how to hold a bat, or a ball, or how to lay the stumps in the ground. The student is asked to follow a set of fixed instructions while practicing. And in this process, after practicing for months and years, the student transforms into an ace cricketer and and starts playing the game very well, in a very unique way. This is, what we call Abhyasa, practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the same student, who is now a famous cricketer, while playing a match, focusses less on the game, and more on the photographers clicking his picture, or on the amount of media coverage he is getting, or on the prize money, then he is no longer unbiased. His attention is not longer just focused on the game. It has digressed to various external factors of the game and he has lost his internal focus. He has formed an attachment and his abhyasa is no longer vairagya ….no longer unbiased. And from here, stems all kind of hurtful or non-hurtful thought whirls. Although he shall continue to play for years to come, his performance shall sway as per his thought whirls, for whenever he would need to pay his peak attention on the game, he may or may not be able to do so, as his mind would be focused on various external issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, Patanjali, requests unbiased practice, if we want to bring an end to continuous thought whirls, and bring in the stability to the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;abhyasa vairagyabhyam tat nirodhah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These can be stopped by unbiased practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 11</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;anubhuta vishaya asampramoshah smritih&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Past remembrances are based on our inability to let go experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states, that our past remembrances or memories, whether painful or not, whether hurtful or not, become the last reason to our non-stop, unending thought whirls. Memories, whether good or bad, become the foundation to our feelings and this foundation, forms our mind-set. Whatever we experiance gets permanently recorded in our minds, and as per the context, this recording starts playing. And all reactions, our responses are based on this recording. When this recording is repeated several times, it gets embedded in our behaviour, and we come to know it as our Sanskars&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming to our example of a boy meeting a girl at the wedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She is wearing a pink dress. She looks at him and smiles. In the past, the boy has fond memories of a meeting a girl, in a wedding, who was wearing a pink dress. In the past, that girl had falling in love with him and he had an pleasent affair. So, this time, again, when he sees a girl, at the wedding, in a pink dress, he thinks, he has found his beloved. But then, over a period of time, he realises, this is not the fact, and hence, he is lost in thoughts, he is in pain. In this case, his inability to let-go the memory of the past, becomes the cause for his pain and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time, we take a decision, we base the decision on our past. If our experiences in the past, in a particular context, have been pleasant, then we would want to continue that pleasent experiances, we would want to continue that feeling to be with us, and hence, we would choose accordingly. And if our experiences are negative, to avoid the pain, we would choose accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With time, the details of our memories are erased and what remains with us, is the feel. And it is this feel gives birth to a series of hurtful or non-hurtful thought chains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is about letting go the past, and moving on. It does not mean forgetting or forgiving everyone and every deed. Nor it means to clinging to every event or experience that has caused us happiness or pain. It is just means protecting ourselves from being stuck. We all have limited energy and time with us. It just means we need to move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;anubhuta vishaya asampramoshah smritih&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Past remembrances are based on our inability to let go experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 10</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;abhava pratyaya alambana vritti nidra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repetitive unawareness is based upon lack of exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sutra, Patanjali states nindra as the fourth reason for hurtful or not hurtful thought whirls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nindra, our unawareness. Patanjali does not refer to it to sleep with closed eyes. He refers to that state of mind, that we live in 24x7, with our open eyes. It refers to a state, where, with open eyes, we are unable to see, observe or perceive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming to our example of a boy meeting a girl:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She looks at him, smiles. She starts a conversation with him and gives subtle suggestions about her interest in him. This boy however, is so full of himself, that he is totally unaware of the feelings, the girl is trying to communicate through her gestures. After the wedding is over, he realizes situation.. He realises what he had missed, as he he was unaware at that moment. But now, the moment has passed and it’s too late. Although, now, he is cannot stop thinking about what had happened. His unawareness becomes the foundation to his non-stop thought whirls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story can have two endings. In future, if he gets a chance to meet the girl, and convey his thoughts, he shall be happy. But if he does not get this opportunity, he shall be depressed. In whichever case, he is unable to stop thinking of the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awareness is the ability to perceive, to feel, or to be conscious of events, objects, thoughts, emotions, or sensory patterns. And the level of awareness is directly linked to our success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Expanded awareness brings success. Awareness isn&amp;rsquo;t a rubber band, but it needs to be stretched&amp;rdquo;, says Deepak Chopra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how do we stretch this band? How do we develop self awareness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says, only when we are able to stop our thought whirls, we are able to establish in our selves, and when we are able to establish in our selves, we are able to develop self awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;abhava pratyaya alambana vritti nidra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repetitive unawareness is based upon lack of exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 09</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra09/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sabda jnana anupati vastu sunyo vikalpah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illusioned or Imagined situations are based on worded knowledge, devoid of substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sutra, Patanjali states, Vikalpa, as the third reason for hurtful or not hurtful thought whirls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vikalpa can be understood as the one based on imagination. Vikalpa is the one, which is Kalpaniic, illusionary. The environment that we live in, becomes the breeding ground to our imagination. What we perceive through our senses is the truth and nothing beyond that, is the truth - this kind of thinking is vikalpa. And this illusion, becomes the cause to an endless stream of thoughts, hurtful or not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming to our example of a boy meeting a girl at a wedding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A boy meets a girl at the wedding. The girl looks at the boy and smiles. Nothing beyond that! However, the boy starts imagining about how the girl may be in love with him and how the girl may want to get married to him. In this case, all that the girl did, was to smile. And the rest was imagined by the boy. And when, this did not happen in reality, the boy was hurt. He could not stop thinking of the girl. He felt rejected. He felt depressed. And the reason for his pain, his depression, his rejection, was not the girl, but the imaginary castles that boy build in the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vikalpa can be understood as a day dream, fancy, a mirage, a hallucination – a kalpana – where things do not exist in reality. But then, how can we tell, whether our own mental images are accurate or vivid, when we have no direct comparison? How do we judge the contents of our own minds? Researchers in Sweden have found that our imagination can change our perception of reality. Our mind can play tricks on us by changing illusions of what we think, hear and see, into what seems like reality!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to save the mind from such thought whirls, from such situations, Patanjali says that we need observe our thoughts. Only and only, when we observe our thoughts, we get a clear idea of what is truth and what is imaginary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sabda jnana anupati vastu sunyo vikalpah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illusional or Imagined situations are based on worded knowledge, devoid of substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 08</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra08/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;viparyayo mithya jnanam atadrupa pratistham&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misinterpretations are based upon false perceptions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viparya, comes from the word Paryaya, and the meaning of Paryaya is interpretation. Vi means contrary to. So one that is contrary to interpretation, can be understood as misinterpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says incorrect knowledge, lack of information, wrong or distorted perception, form the base to misinterpretations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to our example of the boy meets a girl at the wedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She smiles and at one of her cousins and the boy misinterprets that the girl is smiling at him and he feels that she is interested in him. It is his distorted sense of perception, that leads him to think in this manner. He goes and asks her, whether she loves him. She denies. He is heart broken. He is disturbed. He picks up a fight with her. He uses foul language and makes a scene. And even after doing all this, he cannot stop thinking about her. He is in pain. And the cause of his pain comes from the fact that he misinterpreted her gestures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example of how we often perceive a person or a situation or to be one way, and only to later discover that there was some missing element in our understanding, and this discovery changes our perception completely. And the problem with these misinterpretations are that they become the root cause of stress, ego, negativity and fear in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if we are in a financially difficult position, and we are invited to a social event, we are hesitant to join. Our inner complexes make us feel, that because we are not financially doing well, our relatives may have us invited to show off their affluence. On the other hand, if we are doing financially well, and we are invited for a social event, our perceptions tell us, that because we are doing socially well, we are invited, or else no one would have bothered too call us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why, the Talmud says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not see things the way they are, We see things the way we are!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is our reflection that we seek in the society. And only if we are aware of our misperceptions, we shall be able to correct them, which in turn shall save us from negative, stressful situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;viparyayo mithya jnanam atadrupa pratistham&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misinterpretations are based upon considering false perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 07</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra07/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pratyaksa anumana agamah pramanani&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasons for being right are based upon seen experiences, interpretations and ancient scriptures. In the previous sutras, Patanjali lists the 5 reasons for the thought whirls. Pramana or right knowledge, being the foremost in the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sutra, Patanjali, states, that Pramana, the knowledge, can be attained from three sources: seen or direct experiences, interpretation and ancient scriptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, base our decisions or opinions on our judgements. And our judgements are based on our experiences, on our understanding and on our reading of ancient books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pramana can be well understood with the example of a boy meets a girl. A boy meets a girl at the wedding. The girl looks at the boy and she tells him that she is in love with him and wants to get married. This event creates a series of thoughts whirls in the mind of the boy. This is case of Pramana, where the boy has a direct experience of meeting the girl and hearing her say that she loves him. She wants to get married to him. In this case, the event or the emotion is directly seen and perceived by the boy. And depending on the boy’s situation, it can be hurtful or not. This thought can be non-hurting, if the boy likes the girl. It would rather make him happy. But, just in case, he does not like her, or is in love with someone else, and he is in a situation that he cannot say no to her, it can be hurtful – however the event has created a situation where he is constantly thinking of what has happened. What he has directly saw and experienced, become the starting point to a continuous chain of thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when one just understands a subject or a thought, has knowledge about it, but has no experiences, or validation? In such cases these individuals who are authorities on a subject, but have no practical experience of the same. It leads to memorization or mere intellectualization. Their understanding is not complete or mature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember my experience with a famous gynecologist in my home town. When she started practicing, she was unmarried, young and did not have kids of her own. Her approach towards her patients was very indifferent and cold. However, later, when she got married and had kids of her own, her attitude changed dramatically. She became warm and compassionate. Our understanding of a subject, our perspective, undergoes a lot of change, when we ourselves live these experiences. When we walk the talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pratyaksa anumana agamah pramanani&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasons for being right are based upon seen experiences, interpretations and ancient scriptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 06</title>
      <link>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra06/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pramana viparyaya vikalpa nidra smritayah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being right, misinterpretation, illusion, unawareness, and past remembrances. After categorizing the thoughts patterns as hurting or not, Patanjali states the 5 sources from where these thought whirls emanate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pramana / right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Viparyaya / misinterpreted or incorrect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vikalpa / illusion imagined&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nidra / unaware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smriti / based on past memories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says that although we encounter countless types of thoughts, the reasons for these thoughts whirls can be divided into 5 categories. This simplification itself is very relaxing for us, for only if we are able to observe our thoughts well, if we are able to witness them, by knowing the root cause of their emergence, we are able cease the whirls created by them, and we are able to break the unending pattern. And when we are able to cease these thought whirls, we are able to establish in our true nature. And when we do so, our discretionary powers improve, and when our discretionary powers improve, the choices that we make, are correct, and these correct choices, pave the road to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s understand the 5 types of reasons behind our thought whirls, using a simple example of a boy meeting a girl at a wedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;First is Pramana&lt;/em&gt;: Based on direct perception and experience. A boy meets a girl at the wedding. The girl looks at the boy and tells him that she loves him and wants to get married to him. A case of Pramana, where the boy has a direct experience of meeting the girl and hearing her say that she loves him and wants to get married. He is continuously thinking about her words. Why, because he has heard, by himself. And he is sure of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Second is Viparya&lt;/em&gt;: Comes from the word Paryaya, the meaning of Paryaya is Matlab or interpretation.Vi means the contrary to. The one that is opposite of the true meaning, or interpretation, is misinterpretation. A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She smiles and at one of her cousins and he misinterprets that the girl is smiling at him and is interested in him. He goes and asks her whether she loves him. She denies. He is heart broken. And cannot stop thinking about her. In this case, the pain comes from the fact that he misinterpreted her gestures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Third is Vikalpa&lt;/em&gt;: Based on imagination, based on kalpana or bhram and bhram can arise from any of the 5 senses. It is Misperception. A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She just looks at the boy and smiles. Nothing more. However, the boy starts imagining about how the girl loves him and how the girl will get married to him and how they will live happily ever after. All that the girl did is smile. The rest was imagined by the boy’s mind. And when, this does not happen, the boy is hurt. And the reason of this hurt is the imaginary castles that he had build in his head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourth is Nindra&lt;/em&gt;: Based on unawareness. A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She looks at him, smiles. She has a small conversation with him and gives subtle suggestions about her interest in him. This boy however, has never interacted with girls before, and hence, he is totally unaware of the feelings the girl is trying to communicate through her gestures. After the event is over, he realises the situation. And now, he is continuously thinking if what had happened. In future, if he gets a chance to meet the girl and convey his thoughts, he shall be happy. But if he does not get this opportunity he is sad, as he feels that he has lost a golden opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifth is Smriti&lt;/em&gt;: Based on memory. A boy meets a girl. She is wearing a pink dress. She looks at him and smiles. In the past, the boy has fond memories of meeting a girl, in the wedding, wearing a pink dress. In the past, the girl had fallen in love with him and there has an affair. So, this time, again, when he sees a girl, at the wedding, smiling at him, he thinks, he has found his beloved. But then, over a period of time, he realises, that this is not the fact, and he is in pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pramana viparyaya vikalpa nidra smritayah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowledge of the truth becomes the foundation to thoughts whirls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>