<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Swarodaya - Maximize Your Potential</title>
    <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Swarodaya - Maximize Your Potential</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 11:41:31 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://swarodaya.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Bhrisha: The Creator of Goodwill Zone</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171103-bhrisha/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171103-bhrisha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The seventh energy field from the eastern direction is Bhrisha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zone&lt;/strong&gt;: ESE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Significance of Bhrisha&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Samudra manthan (समुद्रमन्थन) &amp;ndash; churning of the ocean &amp;ndash; is one of the most famous events in the hindu mythology, and is the attribute of this energy field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the Devtas were defeated by the Demons, to figure a way out, the Devtas sought help from the Lord Vishnu who advised them to handle the matter tactfully. To come to a truce, the Devtas and Demons jointly decided to churn the ocean for the nectar of immortality and share it equally among themselves. The end game plan of the Devtas was to have all the Nectar by themselves and become invincible. Thus began the process of the churning of the ocean with the Devtas on one side and the Demons on the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The churning of the ocean first gave rise to the Halahala - the deadly poison, representing the impurities of the ocean. Lord Shiva consumed this poison, due to which his neck turned blue, and he came to be known as the Neelakantha … what happens later, is well-known to all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The energy field of Bhrisha represents our ability to churn, analyse and come up with meaningful solutions to problems in life. Too much churning is futile as we can never reach a solution, while too little of churning is also of no use as we tend to jump to conclusions without deep thinking. Whenever we find that the analyzing ability of an individual is not effective enough, because of which the individual ends up making wrong decisions in life or remains indecisive, we need to examine this energy field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting case observations related to Bhrisha:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Pleasent case of Mr P&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr P was a happy-go-lucky software engineer living with his wife and child. All were happy until the sudden death of his father. His father died in an accident and he was forced to quit his software job in order to takeover his family business of bus-travels in his hometown. His father owned a transport company which ran a fleet of buses to the nearby cities and towns. As soon as Mr P took over the family business, he realized that his father had borrowed a huge amount of about one crore from the local money lenders to buy a fleet of busses and this money was entrusted to his uncle to do the needful purchase. However as soon as his father died, his uncle back stabbed and refused to acknowledge the presence of this huge amount of cash in his custody and thus began a series of challenges in the life of Mr P. After two years of struggle and never ending arguments with the money lenders and fights with his uncle, Mr P started to lose hope and sought help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On examining his home, along with a few other imbalances, primarily, I found that the zone of Bhrisha was cut and the walls of the zone were colored blue. The cut in this energy field was reducing his ability to analyse a way out of the situation and figure out a solution. The presence of the blue color in the zone was making things worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presence of Blue&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ESE is a transitional zone from the element of Air to Fire. Here Air (wood), is being converted into Fire. The presence of blue color in this zone hinders the drying of the wood, thus hindering the conversion of Air to Fire. It is this reason, that on page 49 of the course book, to enhance the zone of ESE, the color green is recommended (and not blue).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now going by this theory, one may argue that in the pictures of Samudra-Manthan (which are used in this zone as a remedy), there is always lot of water shown, is permissible, then why is the presence of blue a hinderance? Here we need to be mindful of the fact that the waters shown in the Samudra manthan are the ocean waters - which are not static, and have a lot of movement and turbulence in them. This movement and turbulence, creates friction, which eventually leads to the generation of heat. Thus, it is in this zone, that it is recommended to place mixer-grinders and washing machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to our case study of Mr P, the cut in the Zone was decreasing his ability to analyse and the blue color was adding to his problems. It impacted his analytical ability to an extent that he could not come-up with solutions that could help him resolve the problem. His every decision was going wrong and making life difficult for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Situation changed only when, eventually, along with remedies in the other zones, the blue wall-color was replaced with green. Eventually, over a period of three months, his decision making power improved and he could help himself overcome the challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other observations&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as blue color decreases the analytical ability of the resident to conclude decisions, in the same way, the presence of red also causes challenges. Red in this zone, creates excess heat, expediting the process and hence preventing the smooth transition of Air to Fire. This leads to the resident taking hasty decisions which in-turn gives losses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In certain cases, the presence of sewing machine is seen to give health challenges such as high fluctuations in BP. If you come across such cases, kindly relocate the sewing machine to any of the fire-based zones (SE, SSE, or S).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In few of the cases, it was observed that the presence of flickering lights, put up during the festivals, in this zone, caused minor fluctuations in the BP. When the lights were removed, there was immediate relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many cases, health suffers very badly due to presence of kitchen burner in this zone. This can be treated with a yellow stone or the burner can be relocated. However it is best to relocate the kitchen burner out of this zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presence of metal may also act as anti-element in this zone, reducing the analytical ability of the resident. I had an interesting case observation where the person had to finalize a property from the multiple options available, and even after contemplation of weeks, he could not finalize. In this case, there was a presence of heavy metal in this zone, which was the cause of indecision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the imbalance of colors and metal, the presence of sewers  too hamper the analytical ability of the person. This thought raises the question: if a toilet is allowed in this zone, then why not sewers? It is important that we understand the difference between the two. When a toilet is present in the zone, the mess is flushed and cleared immediately, while in case of the sewerage, the mess is present 24x7 in the zone. This constant presence of mess negatively impacts our ability to think and analyse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remedy&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image of Samudra-Manthan is very widely used as remedy in this zone. Once a Senior shared a very beautiful observation with me. He suggested me to use the image of Lord Shiva (Neelkanth) in the NE (Ishan), whenever the image of Samudra Manthan is being used in Bhrisha. He explained me that the process of manthan, along with the good things, also gives rise to poison and presence of the Neelkanth image of Lord Shiva in the NE, helps this poison to be consumed and not spread to the other areas of our life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the Kamadhenu cow, the Kalpavruksha and Parijat tree also brings beneficial effects in this zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this day and age when everyone seems to be making smart moves to get ahead in the rat race, we need the energy of Bhrisha to impart us the power to think correctly and make meaningful choices and thus make our day-to-day life successful. Bhrisha symbolizes the churning that happens within &amp;ndash; too much of which results into poison, destroying all that is beneficial; and too little of it not helping us reach any meaningful conclusions. There are and shall always be all kind of people that make this world, and in our dealings it is this energy field of Bhrisha that gives us the ability to churn and bring out what is the best suited for us in every situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, even the Devtas needed the Demons to churn out the Amrit!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(These observations are solely based on my case-studies and case-studies of many Acharyas. It may or may not apply to your case observations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Satya: The Energy field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171022-satya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171022-satya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the sixth energy field from the eastern direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sanskrit meaning&lt;/strong&gt;: the unchangeable truth or reality; the undistorted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Significance of Satya&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the attributes of this energy field, it is very important to understand the essence of - What is Satya? Satya is the objective truth. Subjective truth is the one that is open to individual interpretation and can be colored in a particular context, while Objective truth is the one that does not change in reference to context. Satya is that objective truth that is true and consistent with reality in one’s thought, speech, and action. Hinduism recognizes this as - Dharma. The Truth that does not change with time and situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attributes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This energy field is responsible for developing good-will and status, and is responsible for establishing our credibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also imparts the power of thinking and analysis to an individual. When balanced, this energy field encourages the individual to stick to his - Dharma, and uphold his thoughts and words in different situations of life and contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the credibility of an individual comes into question, along with other zones, this energy field needs examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entrance Effects: E6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever, there is an entrance door placed in this energy field, the power of occupants of the home to keep up their commitments weakens and their behavior gets unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This energy field has lots of interesting case studies, one of which is worth sharing on this forum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Case of Brigadier S&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was approached by Mrs S who came to me through a referral. She shared something very personal about her husband - Brigadier Mr. S. Brigadier S was forced to take voluntary retirement from the Army for his flirtatious nature. This incident came in with many challenges. Along with the tarnished image of her husband, the monthly income coming to halt and the future employment prospects for the Brigadier looking very bleak. She asked me whether something could be done in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On examination of their home, along with other minor challenges, I saw something very interesting in this zone, that caught my attention. It was a huge mural made of mirror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observations of the Mirror have many. Mirror behaves&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At times, as an extension to the zone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At times, it behaves like Metal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At times, it works like an anti element for Air zones. (The element of Air - green plants - are cut by metal).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And at times, it acts as Water.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effects of the Mirror can be many and there are no standard fixed set of rules that can be applied on its usage. Only with experience and multiple observations, one can determine the behaviour of the mirror in the zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this particular case, Mirror worked as an anti-element and was adding to challenges of the couple. Marriage is one the biggest commitment that the individual has in life and in this case, the huge mirror mural acted as metal and cut the element of Air, and increasing the chances of commitment failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While doing this case, I was not sure whether my analysis was correct. So I was hesitant to ask them to remove that huge piece of Decor, as it was a very beautifully done piece of Art. However, I requested that it be relocated. But the Mural was done in a way that it was a permanent fixture to the wall and its relocation was not possible. But, Mrs S said that she can get it painted to any other color if it would help to bring some solution. I requested to get the piece painted green, to which she agreed and in a span of a week, it was painted green. No longer, there was any mirror effect left on the mural, and now it was opaque and looked like a huge green piece of decor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another change that was done in this case was of the bed position of the Brigadier. His bed was relocated in the Northern zone of the home. This was done with an intention to bring a change in his mindset and make him work oriented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these 2 major changes, things started to show positive effects in about three months time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a huge change in the behavior of the Brigadier for the better. This lead to better relations between the couple. He found employment in an MNC at a very high senior position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few other cases, it has been observed that a door in this zone also invites commitment failure from others towards their family members. In one of the cases, the resident complained that every year the boss would promise a particular percentage of raise in the annual salary, but when the time to give a raise comes, the boss has an excuse and fails to maintain the commitment. On treating of the door, this problem was positively resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roles can be defined. Responsibilities have to be understood. A balanced zone of Satya helps to imbibe a sense of understanding of responsibilities to the residents of the home. It is this sense of responsibility that a makes every marriage rock solid and converts every house into a home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(These observations are solely based on my case-studies and case-studies of many Acharyas. It may or may not apply to your case observations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surya: The Energy field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171012-surya/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171012-surya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The fifth energy field on the eastern direction is Surya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zone&lt;/strong&gt;: East&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sanskrit meaning&lt;/strong&gt;: The sun, the controller, the core, one of the 12 Adityas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mythological Significance of Surya&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surya - the Sun God - is considered to be one of the main devtas of Rig-veda. It is the guardian power, the soul, the controller of any system. It is one of the Nine planets (modern science considers Sun a star, not a planet, but astrologically, it is one of the planets) of the solar system, and the most important one. Surya-namaskar is a traditional form of worship to the sun; and the very auspicious Gayatri mantra, is associated with the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often shown as riding a chariot of the seven horses, Sun is the guardian power that runs the world. It is said to have 1000 eyes (1000 rays) symbolically meaning that it has a strong power of observation and it can penetrate everywhere. The power of the Sun imparts us with far-sightedness and a capacity to observe, for it is only when we learn to observe, we are able to gain control and mastery of our world. Thus, when the energy field of E5 is well-balanced in a home, (free of negatives like toilets, garbage, and other imbalances) it provides the residents with strong sense of control over their surroundings, an air of authority, and power. Residents are full of confidence, enjoy high self-esteem and a strong willpower. However, when there are imbalances in this energy field, it is seen that the residents tend be unsure of themselves and their decisions keep on changing generally. Their mindset is flickering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mythologically, Surya is the father of Yam as well as the planet Saturn (Shani - the Deity of the West direction). Surya and Shani do not go well together and even in the zones of Vastu, are placed diametrically opposite to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vedas state that the Sun is responsible for manifestation of life on earth. For if the rays of the Sun are absent, life would not exist. When seen in the context of Vastu, this energy field has maximum impact on the males of the family. When there are imbalances here, or the area is cut in the floor plan, the men of the such homes are found to be not very responsible. They do not take their family responsibility very seriously and do not fulfill their roles towards the immediate and extended family. Also, there is a very strong urge in them to shy away from day-to-day practical tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This energy field is also responsible for good fame and name in the society. When we are looking for an established name and fame in the society, we need to attend to this energy field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in those cases, where this energy field is extended in the bar-chart, it is seen that the residents are dominant and authoritative in their outlook and want to exert control on others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the recommended remedies of MV, those who have an astrologically well placed Sun, can keep Vishnu poster in this energy field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the markets there are a lot of Sun faces being sold nowadays. Most of them are made of brass, while some of them are made of copper. Placing a brass sun to a space helps enhance the stability of that space, for brass signifies the earth element; while the placement of the copper sun helps to enhance fire element in the space, for copper signifies the fire element. If you have a choice, it should be made looking at the bar-chart. It will help you bring effective results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entrance Effects: E5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun represents heat, energy, and light. When this zone of energy is
balanced, the residents enjoy the flow of the Sun energy in its
complete strength. When energy of this zone is disturbed by the placement of a door, the residents remain disturbed and suffer from a short-temperament and aggressive behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every energy field is unique. Surya, the energy field, belongs to the direction of East, of social associations and connections. When balanced, the residents enjoy a strong and a healthy rapport with people and the society, especially if working in public domain or are head of institutions. They are not shy and do not evade public interaction. When there is imbalance in this energy field, the residents develop an escapist mentality, leading to loneliness and in some cases, depression too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Aditya-Hridayam Stotra states, the power of the Sun is very auspicious and highly beneficial, helps to be victorious in every battle and destroys enemies and brings permanent happiness. In the same way, a balanced energy field of Surya, helps the residents to emerge confident and strong willed in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;आदित्यहृदयम् पुण्यम सर्वशत्रु-विनाशनम ।&lt;br /&gt;
जयावहम् जपेन्नित्य-मक्षय्यम परमम् शिवम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(These observations are solely based on my case-studies and case-studies of many Acharyas. It may or may not apply to your case observations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 9</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170917-dhyan-chapter9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170917-dhyan-chapter9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra 1.48 to 1.51&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seedless, higher-state samadhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these last sutras of the first pad, Patanjali takes us to the deeper realms of the subconscious through the practice of intuition. These states are of the higher, seedless-samadhi; the regular practice of which is very important for us to know and realize the purpose of our life. Just like success, samadhi is not a destination. It is journey - the difference is that instead of travelling on rugged and rough, directionless and maze-like roads, the journey is pre-decided, aware and meaningful, in the right direction, on the correct speed, and on the karma-marga (the path of action), taking life to higher levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In continuation of the past sutras, Patanjali says that &amp;lsquo;adhyatma prasad&amp;rsquo; - (our desires and wishes based on the awareness of our capabilities, and strengths) - imparts us with total wisdom. As we understood - &amp;lsquo;wisdom&amp;rsquo; in the past sutras - it is the knowledge arising from deep within, which was not present previously, but has risen for the attainment of our intentions. Patanjali talks about one more aspect of this wisdom - one that is complete with the truth, which can be tested in the practical world, as the knowledge that has meaningful practical applications. The knowledge that cannot be tested, that is not useful towards the attainment of the purpose, the existence or non-existence of that knowledge does not matter. One that is the truth, has an use, and based on the utility of which, all the meaningful discoveries have been made; new discoveries, new inventions, which are practical and useful and the one that gives meaning to life. For success in life, your discoveries, our truth, will build higher pathways for us. Every individual is different. Everyone has their own style of working, after having awareness about ourselves - our approach, our way of working, our method - start to develop and and the awareness of which is the truth filled wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be very different from the knowledge that has been acquired in the past - through seen and heard mediums, and in itself holds a distinct meaning. For whatever you have understood and known earlier, this would be different from it. Since childhood, the religious views and environment of our home, observation of the social norms, education, exposure - all together form our identity. These form impressions and in day-to-day life, form our conditioning. We are made up of these impressions, and live by this identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever in life, when we want to explore new heights or new successes, at that time, we need new impressions and reference points. From where do we get them? The world is limited. At that time, the wisdom obtained through spiritual offeractory, for the attainment of our goals, opens up new dimensions and new pathways. Then new ways, new thinking, new discoveries, drives us to new heights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This state, helps us to create a new world and new impressions, bringing the previous ones to a halt. Then we no longer operate on the old impressions and references. Just like a snake sheds its skin to move ahead, we too, leave the old unwanted thinking and move ahead, completing one’s purpose, and attaining the desired results. When the new impressions gained from the new thinking are removed, and the old impressions are removed too, it creates a new state of seedless samadhi. A state filled with intense deep satisfaction - meaningful with our being, blissful and a state of self-absorption - the state of seedless samadhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of Chapter Nine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this chapter, the translation of the book - &amp;lsquo;Dhyan&amp;rsquo;, comes to an end. For many, this would be the end of the yoga sutra journey, but for me, it marks a new beginning - new and a better understanding of the self and life. Thank you once again, GuruSakha. And a thank you to the reader for being co-travellers of this journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 9 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 8</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170909-dhyan-chapter8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170909-dhyan-chapter8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.42 to 1.47&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spiritual offertory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous sutras, Patanjali discusses about the stability of the mind, peace and clarity. In these sutras, Patanjali takes us one step ahead where, for attaining immense prosperity, success and growth, new models of thought can be generated through the wisdom of mind. The mind is your mate and your minister and it guides you to build and flourish your empire. A mind state, where every decision and every choice can turn profitable and it feels as if the energies of the entire universe is conspiring to help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali terms this mind state as &amp;lsquo;samadhi&amp;rsquo; - where one is absorbed and contained. In the forth coming sutras, Patanjali talks about the four forms of &amp;lsquo;beej-yukt samadhi&amp;rsquo;, their dimensions, and the benefits that can be gained from them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In day-to-day situations, you would have observed that at-times, when you would decide to do a task, and you start to think about it, you get motivated to do something related to it and this leads you into a sequence of tasks.. Lot of options open up without much contemplation and everything gets easy. The clarity to do a task completes 90 percent of the task. You experience ease, peace, and happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In situations opposed to it, you get a feeling of being stuck. Useless thinking, analysis without any meaning blocks your mind. You are unable to think ahead. After spending a while in this situation, you get stressed and you tend to quit the task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sutra, Patanjali discusses a state that is free from such challenges, is meaningful, and that goes beyond logical reasoning. In state beyond this, where, just through practice, talking about the intuitive state, Patanjali says by the clearing the old memories, washing them, you come to feel a state that is present in it’s pure awareness and is free of form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, Patanjali, is talking about intuition and gives clarity on it. By erasing the dust from the old memories, you come to state that is free of logic and is purely intuitive. Many people consider the realizations gained from previous experiences as intuition. Patanjali says that intuition is, when this layer of knowledge clears and washes away. Lets us understand this in detail, as it shall help us in the journey ahead. When we have clarity about this, it is easy of us to work on siddhis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To succeed in any given task, your subconscious guides you every moment. However, logical thinking drives it away and confuses you. The world of the conscious mind constantly interacts, through the five senses and stores these experiences in the subconscious. It gathers all information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when you got hurt and suffer pain, at the time of your getting hurt, the entire scene, as-it-is, in front of your eyes for a moment - it’s color, form, shape, the sounds that were present - even if it is the tune of a song, the screaming of children, the coughing of elders or the laughter of ladies, the smells that were present, the temperature in the environment, the taste in the mouth - all this, gets captured in a moment, gathers and gets compiled in the memory bank (memory). Then in the forth coming moments, with the help of five senses creates a picture based on the gathered information, connects it to the event, and stores it in the memory bank. Like this, all the happy and sad moments that you experience in life, get stored in the memory bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this memory, the thoughts of your life too, start getting shaped and formed. When, anytime in the future, similar sounds or color, taste, environment or temperature, or any of the two experiences occur together, then the mind starts feeling that it is hurt and would be in pain. This response would not be based on thoughts, but feelings. And in such case, would your reaction, be based on the current situation - No!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali talks about clearing the dust of these experiences. By clearing of this dust, one can experience the feel of consciousness. It’s called intuition. Intuition is not what we experience through the controlled functioning of the memory bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the very next sutra, the very same consciousness is experienced in a logic-free way. Patanjali says that in this way we can understand the states of thoughts and thoughtlessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In thought-filled states, in an attempt to bring about solutions, the consciousness entangles one thought to another. You would have observed that some invisible force automatically guides you. One after another, the thoughts lead you to positive and meaningful acts. However in states of thoughtlessness, you are in peace and bliss. The mind is in a joyful state as if involved in play. Or else you can it feels the restlessness that you experience while sitting idle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These experiences are contained within the limitations of natural states of tri-gunas. The natural state indicates the invisible world. The manifested world comprises of the tri-gunas of Rajas, Tamas and Sattwa - and within the balanced state of these three lies the invisible world. One that is not visible. One that has occurred or the one who is yet to occur. Talking about awareness, he states that the subtlety of awareness, it’s realm is not visible, is invisible. If you use the sutra practicality, only then you will get the essence of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever you are making a decision, during the moments of those decision making - the mind or the awareness, passes through three points - &amp;lsquo;bindus&amp;rsquo;. Foremost is about the decisions previously made in these situations in the past ; second would be about the effects of this decision - direct and indirect and third would be about the result of this decision?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In discussions, we may choose to spend a lot of time talking about it, but while making decisions, this happens in a moment. The depth in decision making comes from either the intuition or from experience or from the awareness of the visible and the invisible effects. Through consciousness, the awareness gained of unexpressed state of the gunas, or the thoughts of the same, are always meaningful. beneficial, and useful. The decisions made in absence of intuition are harmful, and failure-causing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laden with awareness, meaning and positivity, the actions and decisions leading to the attainment of goals, can be achieved only through samadhi. Patanjali says that all these four states - nirvitark, savitark, nirvichar and savichar are forms of seeded samadhi (sabeej). When there is a proficiency and efficiency attained of the state of nirvichara, we gain spirituality offertory (prasad).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Beej-yukta (seeded) samadhi ? The meaning of Beej is the presence of subtle thought or intention behind any action or purpose undertaken. The entire universe or manifestation is for one or the other purpose. Desire or intention is the driving force of the world. Without intention, yog or siddhis are just not possible, meaningless, without purpose. Without the intention to experience, the purpose of manifestation is useless and unsuccessful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, every karma has a seed of desire in it. It is this that drives you. It is this secret that Patanjali aims to share in this sutra when he states that all these four samadhis forms are seeded and can be experienced with the seed is intended. By leaving all desires, and without any intention, these cannot be experienced. In the very next sutra, Patanjali takes you to one step forward, with the thought that when proficiency is gained in the state of nirvichara, one gains spiritual offertory(prasad).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through practice, when you experience, that whenever you wish, you can pick up a thought and contemplate about the balance state of Gunas in it, to the manifested state, then you will not hold the thought. You will let it go. Many people hold on to thoughts for the fear of losing them. Then the thought takes the form of a thought-whirl and holds the person. With effort, you learn to grasp and leave the thoughts. And by gaining proficiency in this, one attains spiritual offertory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simple meaning of offertory (prasad) is which is pleasurable, desired, and experiential. The word Adhyatma comes from two words - Adhya - meaning knowledge and Atma meaning information about the self, knowledge about one’s self, about one’s potential and capabilities. You come to know about all that you are capable of. There is no higher knowledge than the knowledge about one’s self. There is no higher happiness than creating the our world with our potential and capabilities. You may make a note of this that it is this what you keep on doing all the time. And you shall be able to gain both, in this state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the foundation, of behind attaining huge successes in life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of Chapter Eight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 8 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 7 Part 2</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170724-dhyan-chapter7-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170724-dhyan-chapter7-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.34 to 1.41&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Effective Methods for Dhyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next method, Patanjali says, to illuminate your thinking you need to focus on the non-depressive thoughts. Such thoughts that are uplifting, blissful, and are illuminating; which do not give you pain, remorse or guilt; are non-negative, and are positive. In these sutras, Patanjali states in Sanskrit - Vishoka va Jyotishmati. As I had received the knowledge of the yog sutras through my Guru orally, I never had any doubt in my mind about them. But many a times in discussions, that these word have been misinterpreted as non-depressive light - meaning &amp;ldquo;tratak&amp;rdquo; to be done on the light of the ghee lamp. This interpretation is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guruji always insisted that Patanjali yog sutras have to be experienced with closed eyes - not with open eyes. And Patanjali Yog Sutra complete the dimension of the inner mind and the states beyond it - it is not about the physical body. Patanjali wants us to transcend beyond the body and to the further states, and not to be limited to the physical body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the word is studied, it is actually - &amp;lsquo;jyotishmati&amp;rsquo; - jyotish va mati. Mati is opinion and Jyotish meaning illuminating &amp;ndash; the one that illuminates. One that illuminates thoughts, gives light, imparts non-depressive thinking and positive thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times, we read some statements that seem to sort out things within; as if some worries are sorted, or as if the mind is lost and suddenly, it starts seeing solutions in a new light. Even by contemplating on such thoughts, one receives the offerings of the chitt - like peace, stability, and clarity. Many such sayings and proverbs can give you such an experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such statement that inspired me for many years is - God grant me the serenity to accept the things, I cannot change; courage to change the things that I can; and wisdom to know the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another such sentence is - Life is as Such. Recall and select such fundamental statements, that are uplifting and help you illuminate your thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the forthcoming sutras, Patanjali shares all the more easy methods with you. By focussing your energy on those who are above attachment of the senses. For the best result of this method, you can choose to focus your attention on those individuals in your circle who are above the attachments of visual and auditory faculties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus your attention on successful and stable personalities. Such as those of whom you can interact and connect on personal basis. If you do not find such people around you, you may choose to focus your attention on concept of Ishwar. However in this sutra, Patanjali, talks about internalizing those personalities who are above ardor and cravings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many a times, we do so unknowingly. For example, in some situations, we tend to remember an elder while doing some work. This is exactly what Patanjali is asking us to do and internalize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In political circles, I tested this method on joint-secretaries and secretaries (who were associated directly with the cabinet ministers), by asking them to internalize the positive emotions of the Minister while making decisions. The secretaries have to make decisions based on the thought that, if the Minister would be the decision maker, what would be the decision of the Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was astonishing. Not only that these secretaries gave beautiful performances, but they also played the best of roles in making meaningful decisions for the country. They received such wonderful appreciative response from their seniors and they got promoted to influential posts. In other fields too, this method gave very astonishing results. Select a few individuals in your vicinity and experience its practical working and internalize it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next method is for advance level sadhaks. However Patanjali shares it at this point. The test of which should be done after three months of experience of the above mentioned methods. If you do it earlier than that, it will take a long time to succeed in it. However you can be clear in your mind that you can jump directly to this technique. Rest all the methods start showing the result in a few days or in a couple of weeks. In this method, you gain clarity within a month and half. For me, with about three years of meditation experience, I gained clarity of this method in a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The method is based on paying attention on knowledge in sleep and dreaming control. It means that the body is asleep and you are aware that you are dreaming. And you would receive the offerings of the consciousness - solutions, peace, clarity and stability - by consciously paying attention on the knowledge accumulated in the dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it is quite surprising that Patanjali mentions this method at this point. For this, Dhyan, Dharana, Samadhi through Sanyam is required, which Patanjali addresses in the third pad. When I shared my thoughts with Guruji, he smilingly admonished me saying the method of extracting knowledge through dreams, has helped many scientists discover many things in dreams. When you do not find solutions through any other method, you shall find them through this method. However, I stuck to my question, and after three years of working on Patanjali, I had put up my view. When I repeated my question again, I was smilingly told - Ask Patanjali!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question, even after 15 years, suprises me. For me, usage of this method should be included in the third pad. That shall make it easy to act upon. By doing it at this stage, is not a challenge, just that it may take longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By stabilizing the mind on any one of the above mentioned methods, practice stopping the thought whirls for at least 15 days. After that, during the 15 minutes of meditation before bedtime, mentally make a ‘dharana’ that you shall make a note of your dreams in your diary when you wake up. Keep a pen and diary handy. You can experience the benefits of making dharana. For example before sleeping, you can decide to wake up at 6 am and be ready by 7 am to leave. In your routine days, even though you may be waking up at 7:30am, but when when you would have made a dharana - you would naturally wake up at 6:00 without any effort. When you are able to practice this method with ease, you shall be able to wake up at the time of your choice without effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In three to four days, by making a ‘dharana’ that you shall realize that you are vaguely able to remember all four of your dreams (yes, we generally have four dreams in a night). Then by putting a date to it, you shall note down your dreams in detail. Stress your mind to try and recall the details. Within 15 days, you will realise that your are able to recall them with ease. When you shall be able to recall your dreams completely with clarity, then, you will make the dharana such that &amp;ndash; in my dreams, I shall remember that I am dreaming! Keep noting your dreams in your diary. And eventually, add a sentence that - In my dreams, I shall be taking a hanky out of my pocket (or any such object for that matter which is not present in the pocket). Taking the red hanky out is the indicator of the fact that this is a dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall the statement several times before sleep. In a week’s time, you shall be able to have the awareness that this is indeed a dream. Put you hand in your pocket, to remove the red hanky and then smilingly put it back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you will be contemplating in your dreams. Recall place, events and subjects. Remember them. If you are not happy with your dream, then in your dreams, closing your eyes, make a dharana saying that I do not wish to see this dream. I wish to see this (the subject of your choice) in the dream. When you shall be able to dream the subject of your choice. Those that address your problems, or those fulfilling your desires; and it can be any! All dreams are in the domain of your subconscious, And then you go back to sleep in your dreams and wake up as per the set alarm and then describe your dream in your diary. Then you may get busy in your daily life. Keep your diary along with you. And whenever you get a chance, read the description in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The knowledge that you receive as an offering imparts peace for the inner mind, clarity and stability. And you receive solutions for those issues, which you fail to receive in daily life. You gain new perspectives in terms of money, success, investment, prosperity, and growth. The limits of knowledge procured from your sleep is limitless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next sutra, Patanjali says, that wherever you focus, wherever your attention is attracted, if you sustain it with awareness, you receive the above mentioned peace, clarity and stability. For practicing of this method, whatever suits you, you may choose to make it the center of your attention. How? For this, you need to understand two things, Patanjali says that it is important, that you choose only one subject as the focus your attention and not, change it. Second is about time. It is not appropriate that as the subject is of your choice, you get in the flow, and not be aware about the time. For then, it is not meditation, it is a habit. It may not hurt you now, but later you may feel guilty about spending much more time than you should have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, choose a subject of your choice, and delve in it. And when the alarm rings after half an hour or an hour, stop it. Music, sports, beautiful faces, golf, reading-writing, chat, it can be anything. But it has to be done for a specific time period only. After a few days of practice, you shall find yourself more focussed, with better concentration and at peace. Throughout the day, for an hour or half, set the alarm and delve into the subject of your choice. You can make your subject of your choice as the medium of your attention. Do this for minimum three months. If you want to change it, you may change the subject after three months. If you change it every weekly or monthly, the experience of meditation shall be delayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schedule and time-bind these methods of meditation. And if possible, even the place. This will help you expedite the process as well as deepen it. To decide the timeframe means that daily at 7am and at 10am &amp;ndash; this is just an example. You may decide as per your convenience. Through these methods, the inner mind, calms, clears and stabilizes. This will provide you the ability to delve deep into important subjects and also shall widen your perspective in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali discusses the ability to think big - on the macro level, as well as think in detail - at the micro level at the same time. Any individual gains prosperity and success as per his ability to think. When the thought is limited or narrow, the person does not progress much. You would have seen many people around you who have a very limited or narrow thinking. Their way of life and their achievements in life are a direct result of their thinking. Sometimes, we are not able to control and we end up reprimanding them to think broader. But just by saying - it does not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says that it is very much possible do so through these methods. Knowingly or unknowingly, when an individual passes through these methods, then their vision starts getting broader. This is such an aspect of the mind, that starts to develop or can be developed. All those who have attained great heights in their lives - such heights that astonishes you - it is based on this aspect of the mind. Let us understand this with an example and then move ahead. Try observing a product with detail, for example a car, or a phone. Let us take an example of the car that is sold the most in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some set of engineers would have designed it, some set of workers would have made it in the factory, while the marketing would have been done by another team. But who made it possible for it to reach the entire world? The one who would be heading the project! For it is his vision that would have been spread to the entire world. The marketing team’s vision would be limited to one or two countries or maximum to a continent. The thinking of the workers would be limited to the factory, while the thinking of the car designer would be limited to the environment in which it has to be driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the vision of the one who heads the project would include the engineer, the manufacturer, the marketing, government rules and regulations, banking, and the world market: it would include all. He is able to think on all the aspects more skillfully than all the other people involved as he is able to include all of them for an important and a huge task. The thought process of the person who is heading &amp;ndash; is macro as well as micro. Patanjali states that the head has a grasp over his mind, that helps him to take the product from small to big heights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali, in this sutra, refers to the ability to see the details as well as the aerial view, or the ability to see things in totality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the thought whirls get emancipated - the weakening of modifications - the inner mind attains the clarity of a diamond. Being receptive, he receives, all that which is worth receiving. A complete balanced is achieved of these three states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By practicing the methods as explained in the previous sutras, the mind attains clarity of a diamond. It is left without conflict or doubt. Hence it is never in dilemma, fear, confusion or a blocked state. It is free from these and is very receptive. The receptivity of the mind is increased. It just absorbs the relevant and leaves a lot of irrelevant behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali say that the balance of the three gives rise to the state of communion. With the clarity of the mind, it gets possible to know that what is it that you want in life. Close the book, and think for a while, about what is it that you want. What is your purpose or aim? What is your target in the next three to five years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make an effort. Close the book and start writing on paper. Then open the book and start to read ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will realize that you have a lot of clarity about the goals of the next 3-5 years. It is about this clarity and these achievements that Patanjali talks about in this Sutra. The clarity to see with, meditate with, and it will start internalizing in you, and you become receptive to whatever you feel suitable, to what gives you happiness and you start to achieve it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of chapter seven, part two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 7 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 7 Part 1</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170717-dhyan-chapter7-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170717-dhyan-chapter7-part1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.34 to 1.41&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Effective Methods for Dhyan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these sutras, Patanjali imparts the best and the most effective methods to meditate. These methods are extremely simple, and yet, highly effective when practiced. You will find a huge difference with a few days of practice. Along with meditations, we shall also discuss these methods in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first method involves the practice of observing the pause after the exhalation of breath. This method can be comfortably practiced sitting on the chair, sofa, bed or floor. A few things to be kept in mind while observing your breath -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep your phones switched off for a time of 20 minutes. Request the people around you to not disturb you for 20 minutes. Set an alarm for 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sit crossed legged on the floor or on the bed. Ensure that your spine is well-rested on the backrest of the bed or the wall. The lower back and buttocks should be in contact with the backrest or the wall. This shall ensure that your spine is straight or erect. For comfort, you may use a stiff pillow to sit on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting on the sofa, you have to ensure that it’s back should be such that your back and buttocks are chocked on it. Your legs should not dangle and should be rested on the floor. If needed, you may keep a rest under your feet. Close your eyes and relax your body. Rest your hands on your knees. Focus on your breath as it enters and leaves your nostrils. Feel it as it enters and leaves&amp;hellip; It enters, it leaves&amp;hellip;. Keep observing it for a while. Your mouth should be closed and the breathing should be from the nose. If needed, clean your nose to ensure the uninterrupted flow of breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the method of meditation. Gently exhale and observe the pause after exhalation. Let the breath flow in with ease. Then gently exhale. Observe the pause. Let the breath flow in naturally. After doing this for a few times, focus your entire attention on exhalation and the pause after the exhalation. After 10-12 times, stop making the conscious gentle effort. All your attention should be on the pause that occurs after the exhalation of breath. Observe the pause. As your breath shall become subtle and long, the pause shall gradually extend. Now observe this pause one inch below your navel. Keep observing it. Experience the gradual increase of the pause. Whatever thoughts cross your mind, let them come, however, as soon as you realize, bring your attention back to your navel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the alarm rings, rub your hands. Feeling the warmth, keep them on your eyes, and gently open your eyes. Observe your mental state for a while. Recall this feeling several times of the day so that you can remember it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as you wake up, if you don’t have to run to the washroom, do this exercise sitting on the bed. Or else, complete the needed activities, and then sit for meditation. The relaxed state of the body should be made use of, at such times, hence brush and bath too, can be delayed. This can be also done at night if the consumption of alcohol is not done. Within a period of less than a week, you shall observe the stability within you. Meditate naturally, with ease and relaxation. The body has to be let loose. Should not be thinking about anything else. This is the way this method has to be followed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second method is of contemplation meditation. You can do it anytime and anywhere. Even as you read this. Only thing is to be conscious about your thoughts. Do it now and evaluate your thoughts. This contemplative meditation too binds and stabilizes the mind. In this method, Patanjali says that - Vishay Vatti Pravruttirupana - meaning that by observing the tendencies arising by seeing and hearing, the mind gets stable. The tendencies arising by hearing can also be termed as habit. When these habits, start creating a disconnect within you, it terms of yog, it need addressal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which thought whirls got activated through hearing? Just think about it. What do like listening the most? Let&amp;rsquo;s not think about song and music for a while. Kindly close and and address this question for a while. The book and the eyes closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did you see? A very few people will be able to experience that what they and their ears want to hear, is appreciation. Let us understand the essence of this sutra as Patanjali wants us to. It will help us to contemplate on how to settle the mind in this very moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, when someone, appreciated you whether about your memory or beautiful writing, or your beauty, or your facial features or voice, or your ability to comprehend things, or say anything, you would have remembered it until this day. Some people are such that their actions are based solely on the appreciation that they will receive for themselves. What all you do for the pleasure of the hearing faculty! Sometimes, you will give donations, or at times, you will give special emotion to individuals. And at times, you tend to appear and behave special in front of others. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s us think about this for a while. Try to recall and understand. When you do not receive appreciation for all your dramas, you are in pain. Repeatedly, for the longing of appreciation, the dramas that you do, the thought, an activity - and you&amp;rsquo;re addressing of it, and you&amp;rsquo;re doing of it - itself is a thought whirl. Observation of these shall provide you with a lot of solutions for your problems and the mind shall begin to stabilise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are enacting such, you hardly realise that you are doing so. It just happens. However the anticipation of hearing appreciation makes your restless. And when you do not receive the same, you are upset. Then your words gain the tone, “there is no appreciation ; there is no point doing anything for others ; there is no respect etc”. Be slightly thoughtful and try to get away from this mental suffocation. If possible, for forever. Keep your dramatics for the movies, and if you get better at it, you may try your hand in the movies too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural and calm state of your mind, is your eternal beauty. You shall always be able to feel the emotions that arise in the mind of another for it. Words are not needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same way, the visual pleasures give rise to thought whirls - to see and to show. Do you realise this? Try to observe these thought whirls. To look good, you go to a large extent ; you give a lot of pain to your body ; what not do you care in your diet. And then, seeing your photograph, you comment that this photograph is not a good one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this it because the beauty that you are trying to seek in the photograph, is not present in the photograph, as you are always trying to pose as someone else - as some actor, actress or a politician. The beauty of the photograph lies hidden behind these masks. When you start accepting the self, the way you actually are - fat, thin, whatever your facial features are, the way they are - they are naturally beautiful. And do not be hell bent on changing them. Do not be artificial. Accepting the beauty of the self with your inner mind, and you will have the entire world be gazing at you. When you try and be like someone else, the peace of mind, gets disturbed. The effort to look like someone else, takes you away from your own self. Even if you are able to observe this aspect of yourself, you shall be able to establish in your self. Your stability is your beauty - eternal, loving and mesmerising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The activity of all the five senses combine to give rise to thought whirls. Most of these are such that they cause disturbances within you. Due to this, you shall face conflict and challenges as explained in the previous sutras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other senses like touch, feel and smell, too give rise to similar thought whirls. The addiction of taste to a particular brand also generates thought whirls as when you do not get it, you are in pain. Just think about all those industries that are dependent on the sense of smell. Observe it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can free himself from the pain that enates from the activities of the senses, by just being observant about them and you can save your mental energies and can channelize your senses towards making the life better and can enjoy the experiences of senses to the fullest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sense of touch, is connected with the skin, and is the cause of sensuality. The feel of another to gratify the sense of the self, gives rise to the feelings of sensuality. This can become the cause of pain and melancholy for others. By being aware of your emotions and attitude about the sensations of touch, you shall calm down. The awareness set-in, about it’s enjoyment at the right place, in the right context, and at the right time, which shall prevent you from being disturbed within .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contemplative meditation too brings stability in you, and establishes you and frees you from pain and misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of chapter seven, part one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 7 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mahendra: The Energy Field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170611-mahendra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170611-mahendra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The fourth energy field of the eastern direction is MAHENDRA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zone&lt;/strong&gt;: East&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sanskrit meaning of Mahendra&lt;/strong&gt;: God of thunder and rain; the commander of four heavens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mythological significance of Mahendra&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This energy field is one of the most significant Dev in the entire Vastu Purush Mandal, along with Varun and Yam. He is honoured as the King of Gods. His weapon is the Vajra and he rides on the elephant called Airavat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mahendra is the lord of the heavens and, as the name suggests, does not settle for anything less than the best. This energy field relates to those who want nothing but the best and all the benefits that come with it. In the Vastu Purush Mandal, it is associated with people and developing associations. When this energy field is balanced in a home, it bestows powerful connections with abundance of money and comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mythologically, Mahendra is the symbolic representation of the ‘throne’. Mahendra is not an individual. It is the status, given to the one who sits on the throne, for whoever sits on the throne, becomes the king. The value of the throne always remains much higher than the value of the person sitting on it, for the throne is eternal while the kings come and go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astrologically, it is associated with the power of the planet Sun, with administration and government authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entrance Effects: E4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the residents have a door in this energy field, they enjoy a good life with successful associations. This energy field also helps in granting one a high status, respect, and comforts in the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jayant of the East-North-East and Mahendra of the East&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Jayant teaches manipulation at minor levels, Mahendra teaches manipulation on major levels. While providing treatment for clients, if a consultant works on Jayant in a home, then the residents learn how to play smart at small and detailed levels, while if the energy of Mahendra is addressed, then the client shall learn to play bigger games. For a common man, the energy field of Jayant is very important for worldly success than that of Mahendra, while for all politically inclined and ambitious people, for all those who want to gain higher status and luxury in the society, the energy field of Mahendra should be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mahendra in the East and Indra in Southwest&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Vedic periods, only the elemental Gods were revered. Most of the hymns of Rig-veda are dedicated to Indra and Agni. However with changing times of the Puranic periods, the elemental Gods of the Vedic period took a back seat and the importance of the trinity of Brahma, Vishnu and Mahesh came to the forefront. The significance of Indra diminished and his portrayal came across as a headstrong and an arrogant personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while treating this energy field, which attribute of Mahendra should be considered? Should we look at him as the God of thunder and rain that helps to sustain life or should we look at him as the king of Gods, who loves to command and lead? The answer depends on the way a home/space is treated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have looked at the Vastu Purush Mandal in detail, you have noticed that there is another energy field called Indra in the southwest. They both are two sides of the same coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when the Mahendra of the east is treated or enhanced without balancing the Indra in the southwest, the residents start to portray arrogance and a commanding attitude. They develop an ambition for being on the top without being grounded to the base reality. But if the Indra of the southwest is also balanced along with addressing of Mahendra, then this behaviour is not seen! Then the residents show ambition along with being grounded in reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because the Indra of the southwest (belonging to the element of Earth) acts as a counter-balance to the power of Mahendra. When this counter-balance is missing, and only the energy of Mahendra is increased in a space, it leads to behaviour disturbances, which are reflected in the attitude of the residents. Thus, whenever there is a complaint about the excess arrogance in family, especially with the main earning member, it can be easily addressed by also balancing the energy field of Indra in the south-west.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mahendra in the East, Yama in the South and Varun in the West&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mythologically, Varun and Yam are brothers of Mahendra. To get the best result in any space, the energy fields of Varun and Yam should also be addressed while addressing Mahendra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we really need to balance in Mahendra at home, if we do not have any political ambitions or we do not have any high aims?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not important that we all want to be Politicians or CEOs or high-ranking dignitaries to balance the energy of Mahendra. An imbalanced Mahendra brings many challenges in day-today life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In presence of imbalances, the residents, after making a lot of efforts, still may face multiple challenges such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The family shall not get the name and status that it deserves in the society. The family is not considered A-class in the society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sons and daughters of marriageable age may not get good proposals. The proposals that they receive may be from very ordinary families.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The children from such homes do not make friends with the best in the school and fail to get selected as the class-monitors, head boy or head girl or any important role.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In cases of vaastu-consultants and astrologers, they shall fail to get celebrity clients or high-names in their client list.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence it does not matter whether you have political or career ambitions, it is important to keep this energy field balanced in the space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remedies and placements&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the MV remedies that you are already familiar with, like placing the Ashoka pillar in this field, the placement of God Vishnu in his virat-swaroop and the placement of Airavat, the elephant with seven trunks, have shown beneficial results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The placement of living and dining in this field have shown positive results while the placement of bed is termed the most beneficial. Placement of the study-table here helps in securing high ranks in the class and placement of the office-table here, helps in getting the best positions at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Placement of Water in East&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many a times to enhance the energy of this zone, after balancing, it is advisable to place water, especially when the client wants to start a business of his own. However, when flowing water is placed here, the results are much better in comparison to the placement of stagnant water. The moving waters are light and have flow and motion in them - the attribute of Air, while the stored water in large quantity, becomes the attribute of Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Energy of Mahendra&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mahendra [Maha + Indra] is the king of five senses, and helps the residents revel and enjoy the pleasure derived from these senses. A good life has different meanings to different people. For a common man, a life where all the senses are gratified, is an ultimate life! Working on the energy of Mahendra helps you and your clients enjoy such a life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Within infinite myths lies the eternal truth, Who sees it all?&lt;br /&gt;
Varuna has but a thousand eyes, Indra has a hundred,
You and I, only two.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;ndash; Devdutt Pattanaik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(These observations are solely based on my case-studies and case-studies of many Acharyas. It may or may not apply to your case observations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 6 Part 2</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170521-dhyan-chapter6-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170521-dhyan-chapter6-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.30 to 1.33&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to retain the experience of God: the meditative state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali shares the secret of being able to remain in states of awareness in day-to-day life. The way is to maintain friendliness with the ones who are happy, compassion towards the ones who are in pain, joy and enthusiasm with the ones who are doing good deeds and equanimity towards the wrong doers. This shall ensure that the mind shall remain at peace, the thoughts shall remain clear, and a state of stability with awareness shall set in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guruji explained these sutras in detail. However at that time, I understood them in an over-view. But today, after 18 years, after testing these sutras, have understood them minutely. Guruji had explained me that there are five types of minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kshipt - insane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moodh - stupid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vikshipt - scattered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ekagra - focussed and skilled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And Nirodah - stable and at peace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are known as the five states of the subconscious. The mind behaves based on either one of these states. These can be known as the mind states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kshipt mind is disturbed and insane. If this state worsened, a person is termed as mentally ill and needs medical attention. He does not realize the damage that is caused by his actions. In very intense moments, such people may cause physical harm to themselves. Such conditions are brought under control through medication. Such mind states do not help to achieve something concrete, rather gives rise to survival issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second condition - moodh - the dull stupid - or an underdeveloped mind. Such a mind is incapable to analyse subjects or practical situations of day-to-day life. Such a mind refrains from making social contacts. It has a limited understanding and takes offence on little things in life. On the personal front, such minds are filled with fear. They tend to be overly emotional and end up doing stupid things in life. The graph of success and prosperity of such people face downwards in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vikshipt state scatters the mind in fragments. It gets involved in multi-tasks simultaneously. You would have observed that at times, when you have to attend an important meeting, where there is an allocated limited time to it. In such cases, sometimes, the opposite person unnecessary dabbles with the mobile, or engages in petty conversations (instead of saying that I am in a meeting and shall catch up with you later), or when you are in-midst of an important conversation, he is busy sharing jokes over the sms. Or he leaves for some small task and takes pretty long to return. Although the meeting has been planned for mutual benefit, he is involved at ten different places. In terms of Yog, this is termed as the Vikshipt or the scattered mind. Such people may gain success with a lot of hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets us understand these 5 mind states and then we shall understand how to deal with each of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ekagra mind is the mind that is focussed on the target. Such people are organised, focussed and sorted out in their thoughts. These people gain a lot of success in their lives. Highly successful, above the petty show-off, and are precise in their conversations. They hold deep understanding of their subjects and are skilled at social interactions. People of ekagra minds are good listeners, and are able to express their views with clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individuals with nirodah mind are those whose minds are completely still and stable. The way they talk make you feel stable. Their entire personality feels stable and at peace. In life such people are at the highest position. Even by talking to these people, the mind feel satisfied, clear and inspired. By taking everyone along in their journey, they help everyone around them succeed too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all go through these five states and experience these five states frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kshipt - insane,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moodh - stupid, vikshipt - fragmented, ekagra - focussed and skilled, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nirodah - stable and at peace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you observe the people around you, you shall be very easily recognise these five categories of people around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states that by determining our interactions with these, the offering emanating from our sub-conscious such as - peace, clarity, wisdom and stability - can be maintained always. Now how do we deal with them? There shall be a detail discussion on it in which helps you maintain a state of balance, peace and joy, as well as the experience of God stays with you throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of yog and dhyan, one needs to maintain an emotion of friendliness and compassion with the vikshipt, equanimity and compassion with the moodh and the kshipt, friendliness with ekagra and total dedication with the nirodah. By maintaining this practice, the mind shall be at peace, stable and joyful. Or else the mind is disturbed, sad and restless. Why does this happen so? By clarifying this with day to day examples, we shall move ahead. These sutras are given so much to weightage as the forthcoming sutras, which refer to the method of meditation and samadhi are related to these. To understand them better, it is important to for us to understand these five states of mind. By familiarizing with them, it gets easy to address them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to maintain friendliness and compassion with the vikshipt, for it will not take long for the vikshipt to be ekagra. If you ignore the fragmented mind, and get annoyed, then this behaviour would be stupid on your part ( for it would be taking offence without a complete understanding the situation)! By getting annoyed, you are entering the phase of the moodh - and fragmenting it further. This is not the method of integration in YOG. Your yogic behaviour should be such that it helps you remain connected with yourself, be within yourself, and which ever situation that you are addressing, you aid in bringing a positive end to it, and not a disruptive one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vikshipt mind state is the one that remains at the maximun situations. Meditation can help bring the vikshipt state to the state of ekagra. Maintaining of friendliness using one’s ekagra or nirodh state of mind, one should try and bring those with vikshipt states to ekagra states. This is the natural law of humanity. Mostly people around you are in this state of mind. One should not keep anger or criticism towards them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moodh and kshipt should be treated with equanimity. Even with animals, we maintain a distance with a fear of being injured with their horn or kicks. In the same way, we can never judge beforehand which action of theirs may cause us harm. A waste of wealth, energy, peace and time happens while dealing with such people. When you become friendly towards the moodh or kshipt - they do not gain anything, however you do end up becoming like them. They do not appreciate or understand your efforts, help or time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maintain your sanity and peace of mind, it is best that for one to maintain an indifference or equanimity. Or else you shall start feeling vikshipt yourself, start taking offence and shall remain disturbed too. If it is not possible to maintain a total indifference, it is important that you spend limited time and bail yourself out of the situation as soon as possible. Although there is very less chance, but if at all, a moodh shows interest and requests for clarifications, then, you can be compassionate and help them reach a state of ekagra. And in the attempt in doing so, chances of them getting angry on you or taking offence cannot not be negated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with an ekagra mind is alert towards his responsibilities, and is dedicated to complete his tasks with enthusiasm. By deciding his targets, he is aware about what he should be doing and what not. Their skill makes them focussed and confident, and at the same time, makes them committed to give their best and this gives them success in life. Best, professional, and giving maximum delivery in a limited time period. One should not worry about maintaining an attitude of friendliness with such people. By maintaining an indifference towards these, it shall be stupidity on your part, and by maintaining compassion for them, you shall be treated indifferent by them, which shall fragment your mind further. Hence the attitude of friendliness shall help you take the best from such people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attitude of joyful dedication should be maintained towards a nirodah mind. Not compassion, nor friendliness nor indifference. By indifference or compassion, you will bring yourself the moodh state and with friendliness, you shall be scattered. But through dedication, you shall never know which treasures you will explore and if not so, the mind shall be ekagra. That is the reason, that there is a tradition to maintain an attitude of dedication and joy towards, Gurus, Saints, Elders and Yogis. After this discussion, understand that you will not find a bigger saint or a yogi in caves than a person, who is involved in the worldly life and is doing his karmas and is in ekagra or nirodah state. The one who has evaded from his worldly responsibilities does not possess even that much of power that he can remain in the world and carry on with his duties. By addressing responsibilities, through the way of a yogi, is the highest form of austerity. Patanjali describes this in detail in the forthcoming sutras. Now the next sutra is on the method of meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 6 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dear Zindagi - A Medley of 5 Elements</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170514-dear-zindagi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170514-dear-zindagi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just completed the movie - &lt;em&gt;Dear Zindagi&lt;/em&gt;, and while I watched characters of Alia Bhatt and Shahrukh Khan, I could see the five elements of nature come to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the movie, Alia Bhatt is a budding camera person in the movie industry, who faces relationship challenges, and seeks help of a psycho-therapist, played by Shahrukh Khan, to stabilize her life. Towards the end of the movie, with his help, she is able to manage her emotions well and is able to give some direction to her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alia and her group of friends represent the combined elements of water, air and fire, who are emotional, impulsive and ambitious. They are the happening generation, have a go-getter attitude. They are the movers and the shakers of the society. They have everything in their lives, yet they miss something within! They miss the anchoring in their life. They represent the ‘flow’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shahrukh Khan represents that anchor. In the movie, his character represents the element of earth and space. He is stable, settled in his thinking and represents a capacity to hold and channelize the &amp;lsquo;flow&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In homes, where there is a presence of extended zones of water, air or fire, you will find that life is very much happening and eventful. While in all those homes where you shall find earth and space elements extended, you will find that the residents to be very stable and sorted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simple understanding can be used meaningfully to channelise the momentum in any giving home. Whenever there is a need to create momentum, you can work on the water-air-fire zones and whenever you want to create stability, work on the earth-space zones. This simple understanding of elements, will help you make a lot of sense. Mostly families face two major types of challenges; either there is too much happening in their lives, or very less. And in either of the cases, this understanding will help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very happy mother&amp;rsquo;s day to all the beautiful mothers on this forum. We are the earth element to our families. We carry the responsibility to hold and nurture the family through all the beautiful and challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jayant: The Energy Field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170507-jayant/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170507-jayant/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The third energy field of the eastern direction is Jayant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zone&lt;/strong&gt;: ENE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sanskrit meaning of Jayant&lt;/strong&gt;: Victorious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attributes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensures success in all your undertakings.
Imparts the zeal, the enthusiasm and vitality towards life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mythological Associations to Jayant&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dev, Jayant, has appeared in the Sundara-kand in the form of a crow. Mythology has it that while Shri Ram slept with his head on Sita&amp;rsquo;s lap, her feet were pecked by a crow. Seeing her feet bleed, the enraged Shri Ram unleashes a brahmastra on the crow. The crow flees with fear seeking refuge, but ultimately returns to Shri Ram, seeking pardon. As the brahmastra cannot be reversed, it ends up hurting the left-eye of the crow leaving the crow half-blind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jayant also appears in Samudra-manthan. It is said that when the demons seized the pot of amrut, Jayant, in the form of a crow, seizes the pot from them and flies with it for 12 days, continuously, dropping the precious drops from the pot on locations of Prayag, Ujjain, Haridwar and Nasik. Kumbh-Mela is celebrated on these four locations every 12 years, commemorating this incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entrance Effects: E3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per Hindu mythology, Jayant is the son of King Indra and Queen Sachi. Queen Sachi is the daughter of Diti, the mother of Asurs. Jayant has DNA of both, the Devs and the Asurs, in him. Modern science has proved that diverse parental genes lead to smarter children. Hence, whenever an entrance is placed on this energy-field, the occupants are equipped with all kind of smartness and knack (ethical or unethical) that enable them to enjoy success in this materialistic world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-few-observations-on-jayant&#34;&gt;A Few Observations on Jayant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimism and an enthusiasm for life&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this zone is balanced, it brings success in all aspects of life. In today’s day and age of cut throat competition and street smartness, it is the energy of Jayant that in needed for survival. It teaches us the ways of the world. The attribute of Jayant is mythologically associated with the crow, the bird who is famous in our Panchtantra stories for bringing clever and witty solutions to challenges. It is this energy field that gives us the attitude for survival in the day-to-day situations. A living room, bedroom or a door here makes the person very smart and apt to handle life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of Jayant is that it also gives us positivity and enthusiasm for life. People residing in such homes are full of life, and never dull or depressed. They are always doing something or the other that keeps them mentally, emotionally and socially occupied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prolonged usage of the Sword Remedy&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the energy field where the placement of sword is recommended for winning of court cases. The reason for the recommended placement of the sword is that the person gets an edge over the opponent. However, it is very common for clients to continue the usage of the remedy even after the need is over. In such cases of prolonged usage, the residents become bitter and sarcastic in their approach. Their approach towards life and society becomes critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presence of Toilets&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one feels at loss of words in social situation or parties, consider that this energy field needs to be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always find such people in every gathering, who despite of being a part of the group, would be sitting silent, aloof, by themselves, with limited interactions and would not know what to talk or how to hold conversations. In such cases, it is very likely that the energy of Jayant would be disturbed in their homes with a presence of toilet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When there are young children growing up in homes that have the presence of the toilets in this energy field, a negative impact is seen on their personalities. They grow up to be too straight forward for today’s day and age, and are shy and introvert by nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ability to retort or counter reply&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This energy field imparts us with the ability to give sharp retorts or counter replies. Many of us would have faced situations where we find ourselves very angry, and upset, but we are not able to revert back with our words in a very smart manner. To address such cases, the energy of Jayant needs attention. When you see little children giving witty retorts in tv programmes like India’s Got Talent, understand that the energy field of Jayant is quite strong in their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Giving and taking of bribes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents who have a living room or a door placed in this energy field, are usually very comfortable in giving and taking of bribes. They have no hesitation in doing so and they are very likely to get away with it without falling into trouble. This can be understood as the ability of the resident to figure out smarter ways to get their work done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presence of the Color Black&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a very common trend to have huge, heavy black plush sofas in the living rooms. Cases where the clients who have challenges with the astrological planet of Saturn in their horoscopes, may face negative impacts due to this placement. The planetary enmity of Sun and Saturn is well known. The energy field of Jayant falls in the domain of Sun. And thus, when there are challenges of Sun and Saturn in the horoscope of the client, it is likely that there shall be challenges with the presence of objects like black sofas, black carpets and black center tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Placement of Objects&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Vaastu, the objects of the home become the channel of communication with the universe. Whatever is placed in this zone or energy field, it becomes our means to interact with the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: books. Books placed in the east, especially in Jayant, help us interact in the society in a way that we end up socializing, making many friends through the reading club or the library. The same books in south, help us gain a good reputation in reference to our book collection. Books in the North help us create opportunities in context to the subject and the books in the west help us make gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every object, when placed thoughtfully, can become an effective remedy and when placed thoughtlessly, becomes a cause of concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teenagers, social media and Jayant&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In multiple cases, it is found that teenagers sleeping in this energy field are addicted to online browsing, FB or Whatsapp and are so smart that they can very easily fool their parents. They become those super smart kids, who will have ready explanations for every question posed by the parent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Energy of Jayant&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This energy field imparts us the ability to deal with society around us and figure our way out. It imparts us smartness to deal with the day-to-day situations and people in the society with ease. However, does this smartness always help in life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us understand the energy field in our context. Why do most of us, even the smartest of us all, fail to see problems in our own floor plan? Why do our learnings fall short when we try to fix our lives, while it is easy for us to sort out the lives of others? This is because most of us are overflowing with the energy of Jayant. When the energy of Jayant is in excess, we spend more of our time looking at the lives of others and less at our own. Even when we are looking at ourselves, it is in reference to something external. For e.g. how will I please my ‘colleagues’ or how will I influence my ‘clients’. To be able to see our flaws, we need to pause and contemplate on ourselves first, without being obsessive with the other. To be able to see ourselves and figure out our knots. It needs the mindset of an observer and a process of realization needs to take place within. When the flow of the energy of Jayant is in excess, this is just not possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for all the mundane and the ordinary dealings of life, Jayant is our guide to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(These observations are solely based on my case-studies and case-studies of many Acharyas. It may or may not apply to your cases observations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 6 Part 1</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170430-dhyan-chapter6-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170430-dhyan-chapter6-part1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.30 to 1.33&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to retain the experience of God: the meditative state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous sutras, Patanjali discussed the various challenges as - guilt, sadness, doubt, carelessness, laziness, indulgences, illusion, loss of clarity and mental disturbances. These states, disturb and disrupt the subconscious. With faith and dedication towards God, these states can be dissolved. These disturbed states cause mental stress, depression, breathlessness and tremors in the body. Actions conducted in these states do not yield to meaningful results and these results become the cause to depression, breathlessness and disturbances in body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feelings of extreme guilt give rise to disease in the body and mental guilt gives rise to illnesses. The disturbances in the relationships imparts a sense of worthlessness in life, which leads to drinking, and giving rise to liver problems. Lot of self-doubt leads to skin-allergies and lot regret on the actions of the past, leads to itching. Most diseases are caused due to negative emotions in life, different kind of negative emotions give rise to different kinds of problems in different parts of the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadness can be understood as the absence of happiness and fun. The reason behind this is the negative emotion and thought that comes to our minds and settles on it’s surface like a layer of dust. Due to this layer of negativity, the mind is unable to feel the happiness. However, through the experiences of meditations, this layer can be removed and the mind can be restored to its natural state of happiness. An intense state of sadness causes problems of depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fear of losses keeps the mind in doubt and the absence of faith and confidence makes the subconscious doubtful. The ability to make correct decisions and achievements in life is hampered. By keeping trust and faith, it may happen, that you may get cheated once-in-a-while, however it does not happen always. Faith and trust guides your subconscious in those situations, where you are prone to get cheated and in this way, you are saved from losing the prosperity which otherwise you would have lost if you would have heeded to your fears and doubts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carelessness and absence of awareness leads to overconfidence. This too, arises from a disturbed subconscious. Jap (repetition) and Smaran (recall) can help dissolve these challenges. The main cause of laziness is being attached to unorganised thought processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexual indulgence is a natural attribute in a certain age. However for some over-sensitive people, it forms a long lasting inner impression. For such people start living their sexual fantasies anywhere and anytime, which leads to distraction of the mind, and the ability to complete the tasks effectively takes a back seat. The mental energy starts to dissipate and work-effectiveness reduces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation sets in the awareness that the desires of sensual pleasure of touch, based on fantasy, drains away a lot of your mental energies, which could have been utilised to complete a lot of important and pending tasks. With this awareness, an individual can channelize the sexual energy and use it at the right time and at the right place and not at the wrong time and place which leads to mental disturbances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cause for illusion is also the absence of the mature grasping ability of the senses, while the other reason being the mental instability. By being aware of the senses and the activation of the subconscious, these situations are be overcome soon. By only two weeks of meditation, these situations can be overcome and your proficiency in the tasks improves in a way that it is noticeable by others too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali describes the absence of vision as - darshanalabdh. Darshan means vision and Alabdh means the unavailability. Here, vision does not mean the literally seeing through eyes, nor does the unavailability means the incapacity to purchase. Let us understand these two words through example, which shall help us understand the further sutras with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me and my family were visiting universal studios with a few family friends. A discussion started about the benefits of designing or living in a vastu compliant home. Among us, was a business friend who used to follow the rules of vastu and had faith in the system. While among us, was another friend had least interest or exposure of vastu and was not bothered. Both of them lead a successful and prosperous life. Both of them presented their viewpoints. A heated discussion took place with fresh hot snacks as I watched in complete silence. When it got over, I was asked my take on vastu. I opinined that let us have a look at the vastu of the universal studios and then shall continue the discussion in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached the studios and were feeling very good. While have a ride on the train to look at the movie sets, conversations with the studio guide followed. Looking at the capacity of the train and the amount of people on board, a friend commented on the amount in dollars that would be collected by evening, while the other commented on the expenses that would have taken place in making of the place. The third friend was commenting on the beauty of the pictures around, as I wondered on the vastu perspective of the place which made it so successful. One of the friends, who was an engineer was observing the technical aspects of the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same place at the same time was being evaluated by different people from different perspectives, as the kids enjoyed in their own ways. With all this, we ended our day by visiting the Beverly hills and then returned to the hotel in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vastu discussion continued during dinner time with an intention to know my views. I asked my business friend, that today, at the same place, at the same time, why is it that different people talk about different things? He replied that different people belong to different fields and hence they have different thoughts. They have their own perspectives to which I completely agreed. I told him that you run an industry. You also have a driver, and a personal assistant who are mostly with you all the time. Then there is a supplier who supplies you the raw material with which you make your products. However, there is difference between you and them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your awareness - forms your opinions, which forms your perspective. For you, it would be very easy to start another factory business, while for others or rather, even the foreman of your factory, this cannot be thought off - as they lack this perspective. Even if the foreman realizes how to run two machines parallelly, he shall be capable to become a production manager. This can happen with awareness - by having an eye for it. By the practicing vastu, the awareness and perspective, both sharpen, as in it, the five elements of nature are to be synchronized in the space of the building. And hence, such a place has to be decided to reside where the inner wisdom makes decision on your behalf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In absence of this awareness, the individual shall lack perspective - it is this understanding, which Patanjali tries to hint in these sutras. In the past sutras, he explained us how through the medium of meditation, awareness and perspective, can be attained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conscious mind is prone to instability, not the subconscious or the unconscious. The instability gives it the ability to constantly evaluate and analyse. However contrasting thoughts that emanate from the subconscious mind - throw it off balance beyond an extent. This leads to wrong decisions and this lead to direct or indirect losses. Meditations provide depth that imparts stability to the mind. Decisions are not based on logical analysis, but rather on wisdom, and this always leads to beneficial and desired results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conflict and disturbances in the sub-conscious mind gives rise to mental agony and depression. This further causes disturbances in the rhythmic flow of breath, causing breathlessness. This weakens our will power, and at the slightest of stress, the body undergoes tremble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali provides very deep insights in these sutras about the mind-breath connection. The connection between the rhythm of breath and the mental and physical strength. In very stressful situations, the breath becomes heavy and irregular. If you are able to maintain the rhythm of breath, through practice, then you shall be able to overcome very stressful situations and turn them in your favour. The body shall be able to maintain its natural state and you come across as a very influential personality to the opposite person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says that to stop these challenges, one element, one truth, should be meditated upon and practiced regularly. This can be done by understanding the essence of the tatwa, the truth, through the method of meditation, as explained in the forth coming sutras. That one element, or the truth is that which does not hold any doubt or conflict in it. Just like the sound of God, Om or your own breath ; or the light that emanates from fire. That element which has not place of doubt, and only through proper practice it shall be purified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali explains this in depth in the forth coming sutras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be continued&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 6 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise. You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prajanya: The Energy Field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170423-prajanya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170423-prajanya/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is second energy field in the eastern direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sanskrit meaning&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Dev or Gandharva.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rain or thunder cloud.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the 12 Adityas - In the Vedic literature, Adityas are referred to, as the children of Goddess Aditi, while the name Aditya, refers to the Sun. There are 12 Adityas in total, with every month of the hindu calendar being dedicated to each. Each of them is said to be a form of Lord Vishnu.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prajanya is associated with the month of Phalguna of the hindu calendar. The climate during this month is cool and pleasant, and it marks the beginning of spring. It is in this month, when the main events of Ramayana and Mahabharata took place.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attributes&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This golden-yellow energy field is associated with flora and fauna. It is responsible for plants and plantations. The rain clouds fall on the earth and encourage the growth of plants. When we meditate in this energy field, we receive insights and our curiosities are satisfied to the core. Prajanya is the energy field that grants fertility to the cow and women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although, this energy field falls into the zone of ENE, it is also responsible for imparting of insights. However, the difference between the insights received from Prajanya and insights received from Shikhi, is that Prajanya helps us with the implementation ideas of the insights that one receives from Shikhi. We may have thousands of great ideas in our heads, but if we clueless on how to execute those great ideas, then energy of Prajanya needs attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important attribute about Prajanya is that it gives the returns in adequate amounts and is also related to abundance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entrance Effects&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever, there is an entrance placed in this energy field, it leads to more females births in the family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per the ancient indian science of Swaryog, there are three important Nadis that run through our human body: Ida, that lies in the left portion of our spine and is associated with Lunar energy, Sushumna, that runs in the center, and Pingala, that runs through the right portion of our spine, and is associated with Solar energy. Ida is associated with the female energy and Pingala is associated with the male energy. As the body of the Vastu-Purush, is over laid with its head facing the ground, the energy zone of Prajanya encompasses that of Pingala Nadi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, whenever an entrance is placed in Prajanya, the Pingala Nadi (male energy) is disturbed and weakened, resulting into the weakening of the masculine energy force in the house. This leaves the home with increased female energy, and thus raising the chances of more female-births in the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the females of such households are very bold and daring. They take up the all responsibility in the home and are substitutes to sons in the family. One of my initial cases involved a family which had the entry of Prajanya and the home had 8 lovely daughters. All of them were very responsible, highly educated, very well placed in the society and took good care of their old parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;practical-case-observations&#34;&gt;Practical Case Observations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toilets&lt;/strong&gt; - The placement of the toilets here cause a lot of challenges to the residents in-terms of getting results for their efforts. The resident toils relentlessly without getting his or her due. Only and only when the toilets are treated, the resident get his due in terms of the effort made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When there is a toilet in this zone -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The property does not appreciate in the market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The builder may do a lot of effort but the property prices do not rise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The resident does not get a deserved salary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Despite of good work, does not receive the needed appreciation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washing Machine&lt;/strong&gt; - The placement of the washing machine, in this energy field, may become the reasons for infertility in women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the washing machine is placed here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The females suffer from ovarian cyst and challenges related to ovaries and ovarian cysts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In some cases, women faces challenges in conception.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are number of cases which are related to gynac issues in the residents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In most of the cases, to acquire desired results, relocation is needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;../20161007-ashta-laxmi/&#34;&gt;Ashta Laxmi write-up&lt;/a&gt;, Santan Laxmi is attributed to NorthEast. In the broader sense, it is this energy field that is related to childbirth - for what greater wealth than children and what more abundance than a loving family.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kitchen&lt;/strong&gt; - Kitchen here is associated with inadequate returns of one&amp;rsquo;s effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a kitchen in this field,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The person remains restless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develops a depressing and negative attitude for life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does not receive the adequate returns of his efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those zones that deal with abundance, and when there is imbalance placed here, the person does not receive returns in abundance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bedroom&lt;/strong&gt; - Bedroom here, when balanced, gives a very refreshing night sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of my cases, where the resident suffered from Insomnia, and was made to sleep here, enjoyed a beautiful sleep. In her words - &amp;ldquo;At first, I kept awake like an owl. Now I sleep like a baby.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bath&lt;/strong&gt; - Baths here, keeps the residents refreshed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a case, where the home had a numbers of bathrooms, but the bathroom placed in this energy field was rarely used. Only after the regular usage of the bathroom in this zone was made, the residents enjoyed a sense of refreshment in their lives. Having a bathroom here, but it is not being used, does not bring in much benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Placement of objects&lt;/strong&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Objects that signify abundance, like a fruit bowl, or a bouquet of fresh flowers, have given positive results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The statue of a mother and a baby cow, or a photo of a mother and her child, have shown improved relationship between a mother and a child in the home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The placement of healthy plants here is associated with positive results in terms of finances.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Prajanya?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prajanya is that eternal flow of abundance, that flows from the Divine to us and from us to our loved ones, family and the community.Whenever we share something in life, whether in terms of knowledge, thoughts, love or finances, when we share it with an open heart, we get connected with eternal source, and become a channel of the eternal flow. When our mind and hearts are filled with inhibitions and doubts, about sharing, it speaks of our insecurity and fear concerning the reservoir from where we draw our resources from. And in this process of doubt, our reservoir get stale and our offerings no longer remain beautiful or worth sharing. It is the balanced energy of Prajanya that ensures a healthy flow of abundance, from the Divine to us and from us to others further on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(These observations are solely based on my case-studies and case-studies of many Acharyas. It may or may not apply to your cases observations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 5</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170414-dhyan-chapter5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170414-dhyan-chapter5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutra: 1.23 to 1.29&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Experience of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various assumptions about God. However, Patanjali gives us the practical method to experience God in very clear, simple, and few terms. Through this method, the experience of God can occur in a very short time period. What should be the emotion embraced about God and why should one recite &amp;lsquo;OM&amp;rsquo; - these are the few things that Patanjali talks about in these sutras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a state of awareness, the merger with nature and a state of transcending the body is achieved by faith and dedication towards God. God - the Special Purusha - is the one that is beyond and untouched by conflict, karma, and sanskars, and their results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past sutras, Patanjali discussed Purusha-Khayat (Purush Bodh - self realization) and the means by which one can merge with Prakruti through an awareness. The Pure Eternal Purusha is a part of God. However, God is the Special Purusha. In the journey of 5000 years, the word - Param Atma - too become a synonym of it. Dedication and faith towards the specialities of this Purusha also leads to unification with Nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Special Purusha is untouched and unaffected by conflict, karma, and sanskar. Conflict is the condition created by patterns, memories, and impressions in our mind. In addressing this conflict, our actions take the form of Karma. The results gained in addressing them gives rise to new experiences which gives rise to new impressions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speciality of this Purusha - God - is that he is untouched and unaffected by these patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seed of all-knowing is - niratshay - in him. He is the Sanatan Guru of all the Adi Gurus. It is important to understand what it means when we say that the seed of all-knowing is contained within him as this understanding leads to depth in meditation. Niratshay means: beyond which there lies nothing - it is the one that contains everything, within itself - in totality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, there is a building. Then there is the locality whose area includes the building. Then the city, which includes the locality. Then the state and the country which includes the city, and then there is finally the earth and the universal space which includes the country. However there is nothing beyond the universal space that exceeds it. It is in this sense that there is the seed of all-knowing in the Purusha, but in terms of God. It is Niratshay - nothing is beyond it and it is above all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pure consciousness in you contains the seed of all-knowledge and is capable of doing everything. However it has limitations, when compared to God. It is the same as the space inside a home is the part of the space in the universe, and yet has limitations as it is confined to the home. When the home is demolished, this space of the home, shall merge with the infinite space of the universe. In the same way, when the boundary of the body is transcended, one merges with nature and experiences the unlimited joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is the GURU of all the adi-gurus. Kalen Anavechedat means the one which cannot be destroyed with time and cannot perish as it is eternal. He is Adi-Guru of all Gurus. The meaning of Guru can be understood as the one who, with the depth of one’s wisdom, uplifts the wisdom, potential and self-realization in you. As it is the Gravity that holds you to the ground, in the same way, it is the same power that connects you with your own nature. The blessing of the Guru is the one that helps you realize your own pure eternal nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one who, after realizing the self, paves the way for your realization is termed as Guru by Patanjali. The one who is always established in his true nature - pure and eternal. The one who himself is the Vishesh Purusha. The one who is beyond conflict, karma, and impressions. The one who is the Adi Guru to all the other Adi gurus. That is God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Om is the sound of God, by the recitation of which, one can experience God, and it is by this experience of the consciousness, all the obstacles disappear. Patanjali says that Om is his sound reflection. To recite, does not mean verbal recitation. It means mental recitation. Even in the mental recitation, it means mental hearing. Even if you keep on reciting mentally, you may err. Only by hearing the mental recitation of OM, one can experience the eternal God that lies behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try and remember your experience about how much you get receptive while remembering a tune of song. Only after a silent pause, you get the tune clearly. Then its wording, emotion, rhythm, tune and if it is song of a movie, even it’s picture surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In such a deep state, the hearing of the mental recitation of AUM starts to give us the glimpses of the experiences of GOD. At such times, in the pauses of Silence, one needs to turn one’s attention towards the inflow and outflow of breath. Also realise the sound of “A” in the intake, the sound of “U” in the pause and the sound of “M” in the outflow of breath. Very soon, one shall start to experience it very soon. The breath starts becoming deep, long and light. Eventually the awareness of the body and breath is lost and a feeling of oneness with the universe sets in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one mergers with Nature, one experiences the inner consciousness. Then all the obstacles and challenges disappear. These challenges lie in the states of the conscious and the sub-conscious levels. They also exist on the physical and life levels. The inner consciousness starts to fill those empty states due to which all the obstacles and challenges have risen. The inner mind gains peace, clarity, and stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the forthcoming sutras, Patanjali talks about the methods to maintain these states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to Guru Sakha. 🙏&lt;br /&gt;
Gratitude to you, the reader. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the translation of Chapter 4 of the book Dhyan - Kya, Kyo aur Kaise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get a copy of the book here at Amazon:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&#34;&gt;http://www.amazon.in/Dhyan-Kya-Kyo-Aur-Kaise/dp/B0075LRW62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shikhi: The First Energy Field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170409-shikhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170409-shikhi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first energy field of the eastern direction is Shikhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit meaning of Shikhi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &amp;lsquo;pointed flame&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The minute form of Agni is known as Shikha. A ray of light.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shikhi is referred as “Mahadev Shiv” in the ancient text of Samrangan Sutradhar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attributes&lt;/strong&gt;: Ideas and Vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sacred red-energy field helps conceive ideas and and also helps condensing those ideas. All creations in this world begin with an idea, and our ability to conceive ideas is related to this energy field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planetary Association&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ruling planet of the direction of NE is the Jupiter. Jupiter is the planet of insights. We need to examine this energy field when we find ourselves at loss of ideas. This is the energy zone that provides us deep insights and helps us with clarity of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Entrance Effects&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effects of an entrance placed here is associated with fire, accidents, and losses. When we overlay the body Vastu-Purush on the floor plan of our home, the head of the vastu-purush lies in this zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Samrangan Sutradhar, the meaning of Shikhi is mentioned as Mahadev Shiv. Mahadev Shiv has three eyes. The third eye of Shiv always remains closed. Whenever Mahadev opens his third eye, it causes fire and disaster. Hence, whenever there is an entrance placed in this energy field, the energy field is disturbed and this causes fire related accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And perhaps because of this reason, traditional Vastu recommends the placement of water here. Water here helps to keep the the third eye of Mahadev cool. That is also the reason why application of Chandan is done on the third eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us also take a look at an example of this zone in context of an entire country. The entire north east region of Thailand is called Isan. It is extended and disproportionate when compared to the rest of the country. Education is given emphasis, while for job opportunities, people have to travel to Bangkok. This region continuous to remain financially backward. The place is well known for its farming practices and water buffaloes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Few Case Observations on Shikhi&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Kitchen or Red color here causes anger, frustration, and aggression&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presence of the kitchen here makes the residents very irritable and aggressive. The attitude of the resident becomes very intolerant and thus becomes the cause of lots of fight and tension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had come across a case where the couple had filed for a divorce, as the husband suffered from bouts of anger. He suffered from mood swings and remained agitated all the time. When the home was examined, among the other minor imbalances, the major imbalance was the presence of fire in the NE. When the symptom was treated, the man of the house felt better. With time, the divorce was delayed and eventually cancelled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Store&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Presence of Store here acts as the Element of Earth, and causes blockage of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the store is built here, it fill up the space of NE and hence the person loses his capability to think and his clarity of mind takes a beating. The resident complains that he does not know what should be the way ahead in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually in such cases the client would be utterly confused about life. His words would be - “Mera dimag kaam nahi kar raha,” or “Zindagi ruk gayi hai,” or “Kuch samaj mein nahi atta.” Relocation of Store got positive results here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Toilets&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toilets causes challenges in childbirths in the family and several mental defects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many apartments, where the floor plan is the same for the several flats that are placed over each other, and all of them have a toilet placed in this energy field, it has been observed that the children that are conceived and are born in the house may suffer from the challenges of the mind. Either they are born mentally challenged or have restricted mental growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treatment here, with the usage of brass, got some minor positive changes. It is best to demolish toilets. If that is not possible, it’s use should to be kept at minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Imbalances&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imbalances in this energy field causes severe headaches and migraine challenges. In some cases the disease of Dementia (decline of the mental capabilities) and Vertigo (a sensation of feeling off balance), have been observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a sensitive energy field. Dustbins, Mops, and Brooms placed here may cause depression and other challenges too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Sleeping here for a very long time causes disinterest in life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energies of this field are such that spending a lot of time here, causes disinterest in life. Sleeping is usually an 8 to 10 hour activity. Sleeping here causes more damage to adults than to elders (above 60-70 years) or children (under 12). In a case where the teenage kids slept in this energy field, gave a very tough time to their parents. Relocation of the bed is the only effective solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Spending more time here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the resident spends 8 to 10 sitting here, it is equivalent to sleeping. In such cases the result shall be same as the bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of the cases, the resident had a study placed here, and he spent a lot of time doing research based work. Over a period of time, it resulted into disinterest in life. Relocation of the person’s study table in SSE gave positive results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Eye-sight issues&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having fungus and molds on the wall, water seepage, cracked paint, sewage etc can cause stye (lumps around the eyes), mild or severe eye sight issues. In a case, there has been association with blindness and imbalances of this zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removal of the mess from this area, will provide some relief. However the problems will take a very long time to be solved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Door&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doors placed over here, esp in offices will create problems related to electricity board or issues of short-circuits on regular basis. When huge buildings are build with this entrance, few workers die in the construction stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The treatment of the Door can be done based on the colors shown in the shakti chakra. It helps in bringing the effective solution to the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shikhi is a very sensitive energy field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is best to keep this area neat, clean and light.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid usage of red-pink-orange colors or fire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not keep dustbins and other junk articles here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It may not be possible to reverse the problems that are caused by imbalances in this field. So be cautious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This energy field has several implications on your thoughts and psyche. Be mindful while treating or placing objects here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mahavastu.com/…/vastu-…/45-powers-of-alchemy.html&#34;&gt;45 Powers of Alchemey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(These observations are solely based on my case-studies and case-studies of those Acharyas. It may or may not apply to your cases observations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acharya Seema Karecha.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>