<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Swarodaya - the way of the breath</title>
    <link>/website/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Swarodaya - the way of the breath</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/website/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 12 to 16</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra12to16/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra12to16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abhi tak ke sutron me hamne jana ke, chitt ki vritiyan ko rokan se, Yog ghatit hota hai. Vrittiyan woh hoti hai jo maan ko vartamaan mein, jeene nahi deti, aur maan ko, bhoot ya bhavishya ke vicharo mein ulja dati hain. Dukh-dayak, ya na dukhdayak, Vrittiyuan, panch karano se udbahv hoti hai - Pramana, viparya, vikalpa, nindra aur smruti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aaj ke sutroon main hum jaane ge ke chitti ki vrittuyoun ko,
abhyasa aur vairagya se roka sakte hain aur inhe rok dene se, hum kaisi apne man ke mailk ban jata hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;abhyasa vairagyabhyam tat nirodhah,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abhyasa aur vairagya, yog ke do mahatvapurna anga hai. Theek ek chidya me do paankh ki tarah. In do paankho ke dwara hi, ek chidya ki udan, mumkin, hoti hai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;abhyasa use kehta hain jab hum kisi bhi karyako, nirantar lambe samay tak, bar-bar, sadhana aur sharadha bhav se karte se, us karye mien kushalta aur nipurnta prap karte hain. Us karya mein, hamari mastery ban jata hai aur hum, use, kise bhi jagah, koi bhi samay aur koi bhi paristhiti mein, bahatarein-ta se dauhrah saktenain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aur Abhyasa ke sath-sath Patanjali, hame vairagya banaye rakhna ko kahte hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vairagya shabd banata hai Raag se. Raag ayni bhavana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;jab ham kisi anubhav se gujarte hain, hamare bhetar kaiyin acchi-buri bhavanayien udbahav hoti hain. Aur hamara antarmaan, dhere dhere, abhyasa se uthkar, in bhavnaon mein ulaj jata hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in Sutroon mein Patanjali Antarman mein baar baar ane wale vicharo ko, vrittioun ko, Abhyasa aur Vairagya ke dwara inhe rokna ki baat kar rahein hain. Aur In sutra ki sahi samaj, hame, hamara har karya hame, sarvashreshta ban sakta hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;jaisa ke ek bacha, jo cricket seekhna ke liye utsook hain, aur woh criket academy mein dakhala leta hain, Usse, kai varsho tak, nirantar, batting, balling aur fielding ka abhyasa karvaya jata hain. varsho ke nirantar ahbyasa ke tatpaschat hj, woh ek saksham cricketer banta hain aur apne khel mein, nipurnta le ata hain. nirantar Abhyasa se, woh khel ko, bekhobi se khel pata hai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lekin kabhi-kabhi, aise stithi hoti hai ke, khel ke darmiyan uska dhyan, khel se zyada, apna shatak, banane mein, ya apni har-jeet per kendrit hota jata hain. Kabhi-kabhi, khel ki bajay, uska dhyaan, media ya audience per kendrit ho jata hain. Aisi stithi mein, uske khel mein vairagyata nahi bani rehti. Useka dhyan, khel se zyada, khel ke anya pahluoan mein bas jata. aur isi wajah se, jab kabhi, bhi use bahtarein khel pradarshan karne ki avakshakta padeti hain, tab woh shayad hi kar pata hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abhyasa ek khoobsurat antirk prakriya hain aur Vairagya ek bhariya. Agar Abhyasa davai ka kam kareta hein, toh, Vairagya, ka kaam roktham karna hain, Dono, saath-saath chalte hain. Ahbhaya hamien kisi bhi kshetra mein kushalta lane mein, madad karta hain, aur varagya hamain, us kshetra mein, hamara dhyan shat pratishath bana rahein, us baat mein samarthan deta hain. Abhyasa ki prakriya, ek khalI ghade ko bharne jaisi hain, aur Vairagya banaya rakhane ki prakriya, us ghade ke bhetar bade-chote chad ko bandh karne saman hain.Abhyasa aur Vairagya, dono saath, saath chalte hain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aur agle sutra main, Patanjali, hamein kahtein hain,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tatra sthitau yatnah abhyasa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abhyasa aur vairagya, nirantar lambe samay tak, yatnapurva karne se, harama bhether, ek shanthi, ek stitrta stapith kar pata hain. vrittuan rok jane par, hamari urja bekar ke vicharo mein vyartha nain hoti hain aur, aur iske parinaam swarrop, hamara abhyasa gharata hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aur aag ke sutra main,Patanjali, kahetain hain,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sah tu dirgha kala nairantaira satkara asevitah dridha bhumih&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;jub hum abhyasa aur vairagya ka, nairnatar, lambe samay tak, sadhana purak palan karte se, hamere anarmaan mein, yeh shanthi aur stitrta, drudhita se, stapith ho jati hai,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aur agle sutra hain :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;drista anushravika vishaya vitrishnasya vashikara samjna vairagya&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;jab hamara man, dekhe aur sunayo vishayo mei se udbhav hoti vrittiyoun ke taraf bhi,, vairagya ka bhav rakhane me, saksham ho jate hain, tab hamara man, hamare sampoorna vash ho jata hain. Tab hum hamera man ke malik ban jata hain. Jab humara dhyaan, drusya se uthkar, drushta, yani ke jo dekhana vala hai, yani hum -khud, per kendrit hota jata hai, tab humara maan per hamara raaj hota hai.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five houses of Zen namek kitab mein, Lin-chi kehtain hain, ki jab aap, har kshan har waqt, vichar ke picha bhagna bandh kar do ge, tab apki stithi ek Zen Master se alag nahi rahegi..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;jab koi vastu ke bara main dekha ya suna, toh apka man useke vicharon mein ulaj gaya.. Aur Jab tak us vastu, ko app anubhav nahi kar lete, aapka man useke vicharoon mein khoya rehta hai. Aur ek bar aap, woh cheez, prapt kar lete hai, toh app, use, hasil karne ki khushi mein pagal ho jata hain. Jab tak, app ke man ki yeh stitih bani rehti hain, tab tak, apka man, apko bandar ki tarah nachata rehata hain. aaj yeh, toh kal woh. aaj ek naya phone, toh kal ek nayi gadi, aaj ek naya ghadi, toh kal ek kimti poshak. Jab tak hamein yeh samaj nahi aa jata ke sachi khushi aur sacha sukh hamare bhethar hain, baharya cheezon main nahin, tab tak yehi stithi bani rahegi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;yahan, bhavnaien dabane ki baat nahi ki gayi hain, unse upar uthano ko kaha gaya hain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;yeh, theek aisa hi ke, ek vyaktii, jise diabetes ke bimari hain, aur unhe mithai khane par docter ne pabandhi lagyi hai, jab unke samne mithai rakh di jaye, toh unke man mein, do tarah ke bhav aa saktein hain. Pahla, Ya toh mithai dekhkar unke muh main pani aa jayega hain, aur voh badi mushkali ke saath, apne man ko daba denge hain. Aur, aise bhi ho sakta hain ke, mithai dekhkar,unke man mein, muh main pani bhi ne aiye, kisbhi tarah ki bhav utpan nahi hoh, aur koi tarah ka lalach ne jagah. Patanjali hame,hamare man mein, aisi stithi banaye rakhne ke liye kahte hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;jab hamera bhitar se har-jeet ka dar nikal jata hain, jab hume hamare abhyasa ke ilavay, koi anya cheez ka dhyan nahi rahta, jab hame koi aur baat ki parvah ya chinta nahi rahti, tabhi humare maan mein Nirbhayta stith ho jati hain., tabhi hum, hamra khel, bahtarin tarah se khel pate hain. hamara main manavta ka bhav staith hota hain, Hum, hamare nirmayon mei, hamare faisalo mein, adag rah pate hain. hamra bhetar ek pragya ki stithi stapith hoti hain,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iselye Osho kahte hain, ke jitna apka chit shant hoga, utnahi apka samrathya badhega, aur Jitna hi apka man, ulja hua aur jatil hoga, utnehi app parmatma se, apne aap se, dur chale jayenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;aur agle sutra main patanjali kahta hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sankhya kahta hain ki Prakruti tri-gunatmak hain. koi bhi vyakti, koi bhi anubhav, koi bhi stithi ko, teen guna mein vibahjiy kiya jasakta hain. Sattva, Rajas aur Tamas, yeh teen gun, hamere bhitar, hamera har karya main, hamare har vichar mein, hamare jivan ke har ek paristithi main, upastith hote hain. Hamara vyaktiva, yeh teen guno ke mail-jool se banta hain. Aur hum, jeevan ka har ek kshan, in teen guno mein se ek ke beech guzarte hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;jub hum, mata pitta bankar, apne bache ko janam deten hain, pyaar aur dular se, unka lalan-poshan karta hain, tab harare bhetar, satwa gun, stiith hota hain. yahi maa-baap bankar hum, jab, apne bachon, duniya ke sam-dam-dand-bhed sikhata hain, tab hamare bhetar, rajas gun, stith hota hain. Aur jub hum, apne bachoon se niraash aur dukhi ho jate hain, sirf isleyi ke woh samajik maap-dand pur khare ne uttare, aur hamein lagta hain ke hamari samaj mein aan, baan aur shaan kam ho gayi, tab hamare bhitar, tamas gun stith hota hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satva gune hain shanti, sneh, anand aur nirmalta se bhar deta hain, Rajas gune hame moh-maya, len=daan, duniya dari, se bhar detain hain, aur, tamas haimein allochana, ninda, irsha, alas,, bodhhinta aur nishkriyata se bhara data hain,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;hum,apne jivan ka har ek kshan, in teen mein se ek gun ko jeeta hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aur Jab humara maan, in teen guno se paida hone wali vrittiyon ke prati vairagya banaye rakhna meian saksham ho jata hai, tab hame atma-sashatkar hota hain, jise Patanjali, Prusha-khyate kahte hain. Tabhi hamien, khud ka bodh hota hain. Tabhi hamein, khud ki pehchan hoti hain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;yeh theek aisa hi hai ki, pani kita bhi ganda kyun me ho, agar use, kuch samay tak hilaya-dulaya ne jayein, toh thode vakt ke baad, hum uska tal dikhayi dega,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;aaj ke sutroon mein hamene jana ke kaise hum Abhyasa aur vairagya ka mahatva samja, ane vale sutroon mein, hum iska palan bahatarin ta se, kaise kar sakte hain, us baat ko samjange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HumPatanjali ke yeh sutroon, un oos ke bbondon jaise hain, jinme pura sagar samaya hain.Ane wale sutroon main hum, in oss ke boodo ko aur gahrai se samje ge, aur gharaiyi se janege.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tabtak ke liye, dhanyawad.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 01 to 11</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra01to11/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra01to11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Synopsis:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yog Sutras ki rachana 5000 warsh purva, Maharishi Patanjali ke dwara hui hain. In Sutroon ka dhaya, hamre man ka vicharon ko shannth kare ke, inme sthirta laana hai. Ek sthir man hi, hame, zindegi ki har ek paristhiyon mein, sabse bahtarein, sabse badhiya solution lene ke liya hame saksham banata hain. In yogsutroon dwara, Patanjali, hamara man mein, kaise sthirta layi ja sakti hain, use baat ka marg-darshan karte hain,  taki, hamara, har stroke, master stroke ban  jaye, hamara koi bhi vaar, nishana ne chuke, aur, hum zindegi mein, jo bhi karan, hum us karya main, use kshetra main, safalta payain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yog sutroon ko 4 pado mein vibhajit kiya gaya hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pahla, samadhi pad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dusra, sadhana pad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tisara, vibhuti pad aur&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chautha, kaivalya pad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Samdhi-pad ki sharuvat, Patanjali, Atha Yog Anshasanam, kahkar karte hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the journey of Yog. Agle sutra main, Patanjali, Yog ki vyakhay detain huya kahta hain,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;yog chitta vritti nirodah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yog is stopping the mind from being lost in the continuous thought whirls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chitti ki vrittiyon ko rokne se, yog ghatit hota hai. Vrittiyan unhe kheta hai, jo hamein, aaj, is pal mein, is kshan mein, jine nahi dete. Woh maan ko bhoot kal, ya bhavishya mein lakar khadakar deti hain. Vartamaam mein thaharne nahi deti. Maan us bahwar mein ulaj jata hain, jiska koi ant nahi hota. Maan ki, in vrittiyon ko, rokne ko, Yog kaha gaya hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aap kisi anubhav se guzare. Aapka manko koi baat chu gayi. Aur ab, apka man, baar-baar uhhe baaton ke bare main sochta rahta hain, unhe baaton mein kho jata hain. Sote-jagete, uthate-baithate, aapka man, un batoon ko chod nahi pata. Apka man, purntase, un vichar, un vrittiyon, ka bhavar mein, ulaj gaya hai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens if we control our thought whirls? Aur in vrittiyoun ko, roknese, hume kya milega?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tada drushtah swaroopa awasthanam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only when we are able to control the vicious cycle of our thoughts, we are able to establish in ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jab ham, chitta ki vrittiyon ko rokte dete hain, tabhi hum, svayam mein stapith ho pate hain. Tabhi hamere bhitar, ek asi sthiti udbhav hoti hai, jo hamein, apne original aur best form mein leinkar atti hain. Aur is stiti mein, hum, jo bhi kaam karte hain, woh best hota hai, jo bhi nirnay lete hain, woh bilkul theek hote hain. Jab tak hum, vrittyoun ke bhavar mein ulja rehaga hain, tab tak hum, kisi bhi anubhav ya kisi bhi sthith ko, nirpekshata sa, dekh nahi payega. We are unable to perceive situations from a non-biased or non-judgemental perspective, and our perspective shall be colored  and our decisions shall be influenced by our emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens if we are unable to control our thoughts whirls? Aur agar hum aisa ne kar payeen, tab kya hoga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;vritti swaroopa itaratra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are unable to control the thought whirls of the mind, we become similar to them, we become like them. Chitt ki vrittiyon ko ne rokne se, hum wahi vrittiyon ke rang mein, rang jate hein. Aur dheera-dheera, hum apni vrittiyon jaise ban jate hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeh bilkul theek aisa hi hai, ki, app, ek seda, sade, bhoole bhale insaan ho. Its like, you are a straight-,forward and an honest humanbeing, but situations in life force you to deal with cunning, and mean people. Initially, your dealings will be honest, reflecting of your true nature, but  after several bitter experiances, you will under-go a few realizations. And those realization will impact your thoughts. With time, your innocence will be replaced by experiance  and smartness. And may be, at times, to get even with those cunning people, you will be, mean and cunning too! Time and situations and influences will change your perosnality! At such times, only if you sit back and reflect on your thoughts and actions, you will be able to observe the changes that you have undergone and then you may choose to do somthing about it. Until then, you may not even realize the changes that you have undergone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aap appni vrittinyon ke rang mein rang gaye. App apni vritti jaise ho jayange. Agle sutra main, Patanjali kahte hain ki, vrittiyan, dukh-dayak ya, dukhdayak, paanch karanno se, udbhav hoti hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;vritti panchatay klishta aklishta&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pramana, viparya, vikalpa, nidra and smrutih&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pramana: Correct or Proven: Jacha, parkha hua. Jo aapne khud jana, khud samja, aur appka maan, use samaj ne ulaj gaya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viparya: Misinterpreted, Galatfami. Apne kuch dekha, aur apke maan, kuch aurhi hi samjaa baitha. Aur ab, apka maan sahi-galat mein ulaj gaya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vikalpa: Imagined: Kalpanic. Apne kuch dekha, aur apka maan, bohot sari kalpnaye kare ne laga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nindra: Unawareness: Bedhyani, Behoshi. Apka hosh hi nahi hain ke apke, aju baju kya ho raha hain. Apka sharir ek jagah hain, aur apka maan kahu aur!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smriti: Based on past experiences: Yaadein. beetain huva anubhav, apke maan ko, aaj bhi, prabhavit karti hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abhyasa aur Vairagya ke dwara, maan ko, in vicharo ke bhavar main, kho jana se, roka ja sakta hain. Aur jab hum, inhe rok lete hain, tab, hamare bhetar, Yog ghatit hota hain. And then, Patanjali states, that it is possible to stop these continous thought chains through &lt;em&gt;Abhyasar&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Vairagya&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abhyasa aur vairagya se inhe kaise rokna, yeh hum anavale sutroon mein janega.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tab tak ke liye, Dhanyavaad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 16</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra16/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states, that we shall be able to gain vision of the self, our true nature, of what we actually are, the (purusha), when we are able to curb the desires arising from the three gunas, the satwa, the rajas and the tamas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of tri-gunas has originated from Samkhya philosophy, The closest English translation of this word is “quality”. Sankhaya philosophy states that there are three guṇas, in every aspect of life, in every thought, in every action, These three gunas are sattva (good and constructive), rajas (passionate and active), and tamas (dark and destructive,). All of these three gunas are present in everyone of us and everything we do. The interplay of these gunas defines our character, It translates into our personality, innate nature, our behavior, our actions and our reactions. Our mind is always present in any one of the three gunas. We are living our lives in one of these three states all the time. And no personality or event is exclusisvly belongs to just one of the three gunas. However, when the ssattva guna is prominant, there is love and harmony, when the rajas guna is prominant, there is passion and activity, and when the tamas guna is prominant, there is intertia and lethargy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a mother, when I am teaching my children so that they are able to understand a subject well, learn it well and get a grasp over it, I am living in a sattvic state of mind. As the same mother, when I am encouraging them for activities and competion, when I am teaching them how to write the exam papers in the smartest possible way, when I am teaching them the little tricks and tips to get good grades, I am living in a rajasic state of mind. And as the same mother, when I am scolding them as they did not stand first in their class or they did not score as per my expectations, and I am disturbed and depressed, I am living in a tamasic state of mind!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will influence the personality of my kids accordingly to the guna that is the most dominant in me through out the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is more of sattva guna in my nature, my children will grow up secure, balanced, stable, fearless and natural. As a mother, if I live more in the rajasic mode , my children will grow up to become competative, risk takers, adventurous and aggressive. And, as a mother, if I have a lot of tamas guna dominant in me, I will raise me children to be dependent, attention and approval seeking, distressed and having low levels of energy. I am the same mother, who lives in different states of gunas at different times of the day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says only when we are able transcend the desires that arise from the three gunas, we shall be able to know our true self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 15</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra15/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali states, that we shall be able to gain vision of the self, our true nature, of what we actually are, the (purusha), when we are able to curb the desires arising from the three gunas, the satwa, the rajas and the tamas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of tri-gunas has originated from Samkhya philosophy, The closest English translation of this word is “quality”. Sankhaya philosophy states that there are three guṇas, in every aspect of life, in every thought, in every action, These three gunas are sattva (good and constructive), rajas (passionate and active), and tamas (dark and destructive,). All of these three gunas are present in everyone of us and everything we do. The interplay of these gunas defines our character, It translates into our personality, innate nature, our behavior, our actions and our reactions. Our mind is always present in any one of the three gunas. We are living our lives in one of these three states all the time. And no personality or event is exclusisvly belongs to just one of the three gunas. However, when the ssattva guna is prominant, there is love and harmony, when the rajas guna is prominant, there is passion and activity, and when the tamas guna is prominant, there is intertia and lethargy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a mother, when I am teaching my children so that they are able to understand a subject well, learn it well and get a grasp over it, I am living in a sattvic state of mind. As the same mother, when I am encouraging them for activities and competion, when I am teaching them how to write the exam papers in the smartest possible way, when I am teaching them the little tricks and tips to get good grades, I am living in a rajasic state of mind. And as the same mother, when I am scolding them as they did not stand first in their class or they did not score as per my expectations, and I am disturbed and depressed, I am living in a tamasic state of mind!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will influence the personality of my kids accordingly to the guna that is the most dominant in me through out the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is more of sattva guna in my nature, my children will grow up secure, balanced, stable, fearless and natural. As a mother, if I live more in the rajasic mode , my children will grow up to become competative, risk takers, adventurous and aggressive. And, as a mother, if I have a lot of tamas guna dominant in me, I will raise me children to be dependent, attention and approval seeking, distressed and having low levels of energy. I am the same mother, who lives in different states of gunas at different times of the day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says only when we are able transcend the desires that arise from the three gunas, we shall be able to know our true self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 14</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra14/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sah tu dirgha kala nairantaira satkara asevitah dridha bhumih&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persistent and continues practice, with devotion, establishes a firm foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After explaining the importance of unbiased practice, for controlling the fluctuations of the mind, Patanjali states that continuous practice with effort and devotion, is the way to establishes a firm rooted foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his book Outliers, author Malcolm Gladwell, says that it takes roughly ten thousand hours of practice to achieve mastery in a field. After studying the lives of extremely successful people to find out how they achieved succes, the psychologists found a direct relationship between hours of practice and achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that Microsoft was founded by Bill Gates and Paul Allen. But many of us dont know that Gates and Allen had done thousands of hours of programming practice prior to the founding of Microsoft. The Beatles, for years, played eight hours per night, seven nights per week. The Beatles had played over 1,200 concerts together!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In plain words, Patanjali is asking us to fall in love with our interests and living it 24x7! People who are sucessful in any fied, are not always born gifted. But they are in love with what ever they are doing and live their subject all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we start living a subject, we see start seeing patterns in it. We start seeing clues everywhere and it seems that the entire universe comes to help us achieve our goal. We start seeing twists and turns in it that were hiding in plain sight. Those revaltions of the subject come to us, which were otherwise impossible to grasp. All this and much more. Everything else stops to matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so the next time, when we see someone doing something, that we think is amazing, and get a feel that we are not able to it, stop for a moment, and ask, whether is that person doing something that we are not? And if we, too, want to do the same. are we putting enough of hard work? Are we in love with the subject? Are we living it 24x7? Has it become our passion, our obsession?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;apne aap se puchiye, kya apme woh junnon hai?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,
&lt;em&gt;sah tu dirgha kala nairantaira satkara asevitah dridha bhumih&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persistent and continous practice, with devotion, establishes a firm foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 01</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra01/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Before we start, I would want to thank -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The wind beneath my wings,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;For holding me strong as I weathered the storm,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;For helping me soar and ensuring I rise,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;To the wind beneath my winds.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude to you, the reader of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter one: Sutra one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atha Yog Anushasanam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the journey of Yog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word “now” is very important here. it shows that you are starting now, with a kind of preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindu philosophy is be broadly divided into three parts: Sankhya, which tells us why do we need a better world, Yog, which tells us that how can we make it happen, and Vendanta, which tells us, that once we reach a better world, what shall we attain?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with the word ‘now’ here, Patanjali, believes that you are here, after doing a lot of homework. You are here with a lot of preparation. You have studied the philosophy of Sankhaya well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the philosophy of Sankhaya? It is the philosophy of duality. Sankhya darshan regards the universe, of consisting of only two realities. Purush and Prakriti. Purush is the one that is stable, constant, while Prakriti is the variable factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like the nose, which is the stable, while the fragrance, it smells, is the variable factor. The microchips, the processor, the cell phone, the tv – they are the constant, the Purush. While the channels that we see, the programmes that we come across, the data that is stored in them, is the variable element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Patanjali, says, that after knowing about Purush and Prakriti, after knowing about the constant and the variable, let us work on the variable factor of the equation, which would help us become better happier human and successful human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atha, Yog Anushanshanam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets begin the journey of Yog …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 02</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra02/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yog Chitta Vritti Nirodah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yog is stopping the Whirls of repetitive thoughts in subconscious&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After asking us to be prepared, Patanjali directly comes to the point. Though this sutra is just the second sutra, it holds the key, to the entire samadhi pad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It says that Yog, union, is only possible, when one removes all kind of obstacles. all kind of disturbances, all kind of fluctuations from one’s mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind – what are the different states of mind?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vyaasmuni beautifully describes mind beautifully in 5 states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kshipta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mudha&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vikshipta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ekagra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nirodah&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foremost comes the Kshipta mind. The mind which is not developed. It refers to all those, who are mentally incapable to understand and comprehend, leave alone the higher things of mind, but even the basic activities, they are not able to perform by themselves. Their brain is just not developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then comes the Mudha mind. The dull mind, where the understanding and exposure is so limited. It’s like a frog, who thinks that the well he lives in, is the entire universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, comes the third kind of mind, the Vikshipta mind, the distracted mind, who is not able to concentrate and gets distracted easily. A mind like ours, yours and mine, where we are constantly browsing net for hours, looking for something, we don’t even know! Or where we spend hours window shopping and end up buying nothing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then comes the ekagra mind, the focussed mind. A mind which is able to focus – pay attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, in the end, comes the Nirodah mind, a mind which is controlled, regulated, a mind that is self driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So coming back to the understanding of this sutra, what is Yog? Yog is the control, the mastery, the regulation, the stilling, the quietening of the thought patterns of the mind. And this state of Nirodah is the goal of Yog. Yog will only happen, in a Nirodah state of mind, to a mind, where the whirls, the repeatative thought patterns, are in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yog Chitt Vritti Nirodah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jab Chitt ki Vrittian control me hoti hai, Tab Yog ghattit hota hai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 03</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra03/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tada drashta Swaroope Avasthanam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the observer, establishes in his own nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After asking us to be prepared for Yog, and explaining us, how to remove distractions, one is able to attain Yog. Patanjali, in this sutra, tells us, what will happen when one is able to take off distractions from one’s mind. He says that when we remove the distractions of the mind, we shall be able to establish in our own nature, our original form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tada / then&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drushtaa / observer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swaroopam / original form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;awastha / Shall be able to establish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tabhi hum stapit ho sakte hain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the process of Nirodah, the true self stands alone, it is not a process of attaining something, it’s a process of eliminating some thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the Sanskrit concept of Neti-Neti. Not this not that. This is the method of Vedic analysis of negation. The seeker is able to identify the true self, by negating, what is not the true self. You come cLose to your atma, by negating, what in anatma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word can be broken into n + eti. Not this, not that. Guru Granth has a very beautiful shloka (verse) on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Na Shank, na chakram, na gaada, na seeyam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
He doesn’t have any conch shells, nor any chakras, nor gaadas nor is he blue colored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Achraj Roopam, rahit janam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
He has beautiful form and is beyond birth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neti neti kathit ved&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Vedas says that he is not this, not that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Uch-mooch, apar govindam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
He is high and the infinite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Basanti sadh hrudayam, achut bujati, Nanak badbhajya&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to seek him, he resides with you, and all those who are fortunate, says Nanak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when we free our minds from minor and major fluctuations, we are able to rest in our own nature, our atman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tada drashta Swaroope Avasthanam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 04</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra04/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vritti Swaroopam Itratra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At other times, the observer considers himself similar to his thought Whirls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this Sutra, Patanjali indicates how the fluctuations of mind affect you. If you don’t stop them, you will gradually start identifying yourself as you appear, in these fluctuations. Your swaroop will get lost in the forms of these fluctuations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamare Gujratis mein ek kahavat hain, ke ghode ko hum, ghade ke saath bandh dete hain, toh ghoda bhi, thode dino ke baad, ghade jaisa bolne lagta hain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our true self, our consciousness, is like a lump of clay. If clay is moulded as a ball, it starts thinking of itself like a ball. It starts behaving like a ball. People identify it as a ball. What ever shape the clay may take, it does not cease to be the clay. In the same way, we, should not forget, that we are different from our thoughts, that we are different from our influence, we are different from our distractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vritti Swaroopam Itratra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are not conscious of this fact, if we are not aware, we shall, eventually start taking form of our fluctuations. The thought whirls shall become our true nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence this sutra is very relevant as parents. Our children mingle in good and bad company, throughout the day. A reminder of this sutra, to ourselves, and to our children, is very important to discourage mob behavior and mindless cult following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Steve Jobs has very aptly stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your time is limited, so don’t waste it living someone else’s life. Have the courage to follow your heart and your intuition […] Everything else is secondary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vritti Swaroopam Itratra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At other times, the observer considers himself similar to his thought whirls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 05</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra05/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;vrittayah pancatayah klisht aklishtah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether hurting or non hurting, repetitive thoughts are of five types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After talking, what is Yog, and the benefits of establishing in our own nature, Patanjali explains that, what ever, the nature of thought that we witness, hurtful or not, we can divide it into 5 catagories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mind becomes the gate to heaven, the mind become the gate to hell, says Osho. The whole point of Yoga are deeply concerned with the usage of the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words, klishta or aklishta, dukhdayak ya na-dukhdayak, represent the two opposites. And The term, is not just limited to be hurtful or not, It is much beyond that. It refers to those thoughts, that lead to progress or those, that do not, Those thoughts that lead to our good, our freedom, our growth, and those thoughts, that do not. Those thoughts that trouble us, or not. And the five type of repetitive thoughts patterns in the mind, lead you to one of the two states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observing our thoughts, helps us establish our true nature. And for that, we need to overcome those thoughts that are troublesome, painful and lead to ignorance. For if we are able to witness our thoughts, if we are able to look through them, observe them, categorize them, then we are able to detach ourselves from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;vrittayah pancatayah klisht aklishtah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether hurting or non hurting, repetitive thoughts are of five types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 06</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra06/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pramana viparyaya vikalpa nidra smritayah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being right, misinterpretation, illusion, unawareness, and past remembrances. After categorizing the thoughts patterns as hurting or not, Patanjali states the 5 sources from where these thought whirls emanate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pramana / right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Viparyaya / misinterpreted or incorrect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vikalpa / illusion imagined&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nidra / unaware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smriti / based on past memories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says that although we encounter countless types of thoughts, the reasons for these thoughts whirls can be divided into 5 categories. This simplification itself is very relaxing for us, for only if we are able to observe our thoughts well, if we are able to witness them, by knowing the root cause of their emergence, we are able cease the whirls created by them, and we are able to break the unending pattern. And when we are able to cease these thought whirls, we are able to establish in our true nature. And when we do so, our discretionary powers improve, and when our discretionary powers improve, the choices that we make, are correct, and these correct choices, pave the road to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s understand the 5 types of reasons behind our thought whirls, using a simple example of a boy meeting a girl at a wedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;First is Pramana&lt;/em&gt;: Based on direct perception and experience. A boy meets a girl at the wedding. The girl looks at the boy and tells him that she loves him and wants to get married to him. A case of Pramana, where the boy has a direct experience of meeting the girl and hearing her say that she loves him and wants to get married. He is continuously thinking about her words. Why, because he has heard, by himself. And he is sure of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Second is Viparya&lt;/em&gt;: Comes from the word Paryaya, the meaning of Paryaya is Matlab or interpretation.Vi means the contrary to. The one that is opposite of the true meaning, or interpretation, is misinterpretation. A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She smiles and at one of her cousins and he misinterprets that the girl is smiling at him and is interested in him. He goes and asks her whether she loves him. She denies. He is heart broken. And cannot stop thinking about her. In this case, the pain comes from the fact that he misinterpreted her gestures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Third is Vikalpa&lt;/em&gt;: Based on imagination, based on kalpana or bhram and bhram can arise from any of the 5 senses. It is Misperception. A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She just looks at the boy and smiles. Nothing more. However, the boy starts imagining about how the girl loves him and how the girl will get married to him and how they will live happily ever after. All that the girl did is smile. The rest was imagined by the boy’s mind. And when, this does not happen, the boy is hurt. And the reason of this hurt is the imaginary castles that he had build in his head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourth is Nindra&lt;/em&gt;: Based on unawareness. A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She looks at him, smiles. She has a small conversation with him and gives subtle suggestions about her interest in him. This boy however, has never interacted with girls before, and hence, he is totally unaware of the feelings the girl is trying to communicate through her gestures. After the event is over, he realises the situation. And now, he is continuously thinking if what had happened. In future, if he gets a chance to meet the girl and convey his thoughts, he shall be happy. But if he does not get this opportunity he is sad, as he feels that he has lost a golden opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifth is Smriti&lt;/em&gt;: Based on memory. A boy meets a girl. She is wearing a pink dress. She looks at him and smiles. In the past, the boy has fond memories of meeting a girl, in the wedding, wearing a pink dress. In the past, the girl had fallen in love with him and there has an affair. So, this time, again, when he sees a girl, at the wedding, smiling at him, he thinks, he has found his beloved. But then, over a period of time, he realises, that this is not the fact, and he is in pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pramana viparyaya vikalpa nidra smritayah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowledge of the truth becomes the foundation to thoughts whirls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 07</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra07/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pratyaksa anumana agamah pramanani&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasons for being right are based upon seen experiences, interpretations and ancient scriptures. In the previous sutras, Patanjali lists the 5 reasons for the thought whirls. Pramana or right knowledge, being the foremost in the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sutra, Patanjali, states, that Pramana, the knowledge, can be attained from three sources: seen or direct experiences, interpretation and ancient scriptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, base our decisions or opinions on our judgements. And our judgements are based on our experiences, on our understanding and on our reading of ancient books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pramana can be well understood with the example of a boy meets a girl. A boy meets a girl at the wedding. The girl looks at the boy and she tells him that she is in love with him and wants to get married. This event creates a series of thoughts whirls in the mind of the boy. This is case of Pramana, where the boy has a direct experience of meeting the girl and hearing her say that she loves him. She wants to get married to him. In this case, the event or the emotion is directly seen and perceived by the boy. And depending on the boy’s situation, it can be hurtful or not. This thought can be non-hurting, if the boy likes the girl. It would rather make him happy. But, just in case, he does not like her, or is in love with someone else, and he is in a situation that he cannot say no to her, it can be hurtful – however the event has created a situation where he is constantly thinking of what has happened. What he has directly saw and experienced, become the starting point to a continuous chain of thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when one just understands a subject or a thought, has knowledge about it, but has no experiences, or validation? In such cases these individuals who are authorities on a subject, but have no practical experience of the same. It leads to memorization or mere intellectualization. Their understanding is not complete or mature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember my experience with a famous gynecologist in my home town. When she started practicing, she was unmarried, young and did not have kids of her own. Her approach towards her patients was very indifferent and cold. However, later, when she got married and had kids of her own, her attitude changed dramatically. She became warm and compassionate. Our understanding of a subject, our perspective, undergoes a lot of change, when we ourselves live these experiences. When we walk the talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pratyaksa anumana agamah pramanani&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasons for being right are based upon seen experiences, interpretations and ancient scriptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 08</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra08/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;viparyayo mithya jnanam atadrupa pratistham&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misinterpretations are based upon false perceptions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viparya, comes from the word Paryaya, and the meaning of Paryaya is interpretation. Vi means contrary to. So one that is contrary to interpretation, can be understood as misinterpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says incorrect knowledge, lack of information, wrong or distorted perception, form the base to misinterpretations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to our example of the boy meets a girl at the wedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She smiles and at one of her cousins and the boy misinterprets that the girl is smiling at him and he feels that she is interested in him. It is his distorted sense of perception, that leads him to think in this manner. He goes and asks her, whether she loves him. She denies. He is heart broken. He is disturbed. He picks up a fight with her. He uses foul language and makes a scene. And even after doing all this, he cannot stop thinking about her. He is in pain. And the cause of his pain comes from the fact that he misinterpreted her gestures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example of how we often perceive a person or a situation or to be one way, and only to later discover that there was some missing element in our understanding, and this discovery changes our perception completely. And the problem with these misinterpretations are that they become the root cause of stress, ego, negativity and fear in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if we are in a financially difficult position, and we are invited to a social event, we are hesitant to join. Our inner complexes make us feel, that because we are not financially doing well, our relatives may have us invited to show off their affluence. On the other hand, if we are doing financially well, and we are invited for a social event, our perceptions tell us, that because we are doing socially well, we are invited, or else no one would have bothered too call us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why, the Talmud says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not see things the way they are, We see things the way we are!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is our reflection that we seek in the society. And only if we are aware of our misperceptions, we shall be able to correct them, which in turn shall save us from negative, stressful situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;viparyayo mithya jnanam atadrupa pratistham&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misinterpretations are based upon considering false perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 09</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra09/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sabda jnana anupati vastu sunyo vikalpah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illusioned or Imagined situations are based on worded knowledge, devoid of substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sutra, Patanjali states, Vikalpa, as the third reason for hurtful or not hurtful thought whirls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vikalpa can be understood as the one based on imagination. Vikalpa is the one, which is Kalpaniic, illusionary. The environment that we live in, becomes the breeding ground to our imagination. What we perceive through our senses is the truth and nothing beyond that, is the truth - this kind of thinking is vikalpa. And this illusion, becomes the cause to an endless stream of thoughts, hurtful or not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming to our example of a boy meeting a girl at a wedding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A boy meets a girl at the wedding. The girl looks at the boy and smiles. Nothing beyond that! However, the boy starts imagining about how the girl may be in love with him and how the girl may want to get married to him. In this case, all that the girl did, was to smile. And the rest was imagined by the boy. And when, this did not happen in reality, the boy was hurt. He could not stop thinking of the girl. He felt rejected. He felt depressed. And the reason for his pain, his depression, his rejection, was not the girl, but the imaginary castles that boy build in the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vikalpa can be understood as a day dream, fancy, a mirage, a hallucination – a kalpana – where things do not exist in reality. But then, how can we tell, whether our own mental images are accurate or vivid, when we have no direct comparison? How do we judge the contents of our own minds? Researchers in Sweden have found that our imagination can change our perception of reality. Our mind can play tricks on us by changing illusions of what we think, hear and see, into what seems like reality!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to save the mind from such thought whirls, from such situations, Patanjali says that we need observe our thoughts. Only and only, when we observe our thoughts, we get a clear idea of what is truth and what is imaginary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sabda jnana anupati vastu sunyo vikalpah&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illusional or Imagined situations are based on worded knowledge, devoid of substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 10</title>
      <link>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra10/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/website/post/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;abhava pratyaya alambana vritti nidra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repetitive unawareness is based upon lack of exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this sutra, Patanjali states nindra as the fourth reason for hurtful or not hurtful thought whirls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nindra, our unawareness. Patanjali does not refer to it to sleep with closed eyes. He refers to that state of mind, that we live in 24x7, with our open eyes. It refers to a state, where, with open eyes, we are unable to see, observe or perceive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming to our example of a boy meeting a girl:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A boy meets a girl at the wedding. She looks at him, smiles. She starts a conversation with him and gives subtle suggestions about her interest in him. This boy however, is so full of himself, that he is totally unaware of the feelings, the girl is trying to communicate through her gestures. After the wedding is over, he realizes situation.. He realises what he had missed, as he he was unaware at that moment. But now, the moment has passed and it’s too late. Although, now, he is cannot stop thinking about what had happened. His unawareness becomes the foundation to his non-stop thought whirls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story can have two endings. In future, if he gets a chance to meet the girl, and convey his thoughts, he shall be happy. But if he does not get this opportunity, he shall be depressed. In whichever case, he is unable to stop thinking of the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Awareness is the ability to perceive, to feel, or to be conscious of events, objects, thoughts, emotions, or sensory patterns. And the level of awareness is directly linked to our success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Expanded awareness brings success. Awareness isn&amp;rsquo;t a rubber band, but it needs to be stretched&amp;rdquo;, says Deepak Chopra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how do we stretch this band? How do we develop self awareness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patanjali says, only when we are able to stop our thought whirls, we are able to establish in our selves, and when we are able to establish in our selves, we are able to develop self awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;abhava pratyaya alambana vritti nidra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repetitive unawareness is based upon lack of exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>