<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Swarodaya - Maximize Your Potential</title>
    <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Swarodaya - Maximize Your Potential</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 11:41:31 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://swarodaya.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bhrisha: The Creator of Goodwill Zone</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171103-bhrisha/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171103-bhrisha/</guid>
      <description>The seventh energy field from the eastern direction is Bhrisha.
Zone: ESE
Significance of Bhrisha:
Samudra manthan (समुद्रमन्थन) &amp;ndash; churning of the ocean &amp;ndash; is one of the most famous events in the hindu mythology, and is the attribute of this energy field.
Once the Devtas were defeated by the Demons, to figure a way out, the Devtas sought help from the Lord Vishnu who advised them to handle the matter tactfully.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Satya: The Energy field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171022-satya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171022-satya/</guid>
      <description>This is the sixth energy field from the eastern direction.
Sanskrit meaning: the unchangeable truth or reality; the undistorted.
Significance of Satya:
To understand the attributes of this energy field, it is very important to understand the essence of - What is Satya? Satya is the objective truth. Subjective truth is the one that is open to individual interpretation and can be colored in a particular context, while Objective truth is the one that does not change in reference to context.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surya: The Energy field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171012-surya/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20171012-surya/</guid>
      <description>The fifth energy field on the eastern direction is Surya.
Zone: East
Sanskrit meaning: The sun, the controller, the core, one of the 12 Adityas.
Mythological Significance of Surya:
Surya - the Sun God - is considered to be one of the main devtas of Rig-veda. It is the guardian power, the soul, the controller of any system. It is one of the Nine planets (modern science considers Sun a star, not a planet, but astrologically, it is one of the planets) of the solar system, and the most important one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 9</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170917-dhyan-chapter9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170917-dhyan-chapter9/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra 1.48 to 1.51
Seedless, higher-state samadhi.
In these last sutras of the first pad, Patanjali takes us to the deeper realms of the subconscious through the practice of intuition. These states are of the higher, seedless-samadhi; the regular practice of which is very important for us to know and realize the purpose of our life. Just like success, samadhi is not a destination. It is journey - the difference is that instead of travelling on rugged and rough, directionless and maze-like roads, the journey is pre-decided, aware and meaningful, in the right direction, on the correct speed, and on the karma-marga (the path of action), taking life to higher levels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 8</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170909-dhyan-chapter8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170909-dhyan-chapter8/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra: 1.42 to 1.47
Spiritual offertory.
In the previous sutras, Patanjali discusses about the stability of the mind, peace and clarity. In these sutras, Patanjali takes us one step ahead where, for attaining immense prosperity, success and growth, new models of thought can be generated through the wisdom of mind. The mind is your mate and your minister and it guides you to build and flourish your empire. A mind state, where every decision and every choice can turn profitable and it feels as if the energies of the entire universe is conspiring to help you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 7 Part 2</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170724-dhyan-chapter7-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170724-dhyan-chapter7-part2/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra: 1.34 to 1.41
The Effective Methods for Dhyan.
In the next method, Patanjali says, to illuminate your thinking you need to focus on the non-depressive thoughts. Such thoughts that are uplifting, blissful, and are illuminating; which do not give you pain, remorse or guilt; are non-negative, and are positive. In these sutras, Patanjali states in Sanskrit - Vishoka va Jyotishmati. As I had received the knowledge of the yog sutras through my Guru orally, I never had any doubt in my mind about them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 7 Part 1</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170717-dhyan-chapter7-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170717-dhyan-chapter7-part1/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra: 1.34 to 1.41
The Effective Methods for Dhyan.
In these sutras, Patanjali imparts the best and the most effective methods to meditate. These methods are extremely simple, and yet, highly effective when practiced. You will find a huge difference with a few days of practice. Along with meditations, we shall also discuss these methods in detail.
The first method involves the practice of observing the pause after the exhalation of breath.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mahendra: The Energy Field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170611-mahendra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170611-mahendra/</guid>
      <description>The fourth energy field of the eastern direction is MAHENDRA.
Zone: East
Sanskrit meaning of Mahendra: God of thunder and rain; the commander of four heavens.
Mythological significance of Mahendra:
This energy field is one of the most significant Dev in the entire Vastu Purush Mandal, along with Varun and Yam. He is honoured as the King of Gods. His weapon is the Vajra and he rides on the elephant called Airavat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 6 Part 2</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170521-dhyan-chapter6-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170521-dhyan-chapter6-part2/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra: 1.30 to 1.33
How to retain the experience of God: the meditative state.
Patanjali shares the secret of being able to remain in states of awareness in day-to-day life. The way is to maintain friendliness with the ones who are happy, compassion towards the ones who are in pain, joy and enthusiasm with the ones who are doing good deeds and equanimity towards the wrong doers. This shall ensure that the mind shall remain at peace, the thoughts shall remain clear, and a state of stability with awareness shall set in.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dear Zindagi - A Medley of 5 Elements</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170514-dear-zindagi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170514-dear-zindagi/</guid>
      <description>Just completed the movie - Dear Zindagi, and while I watched characters of Alia Bhatt and Shahrukh Khan, I could see the five elements of nature come to life.
In the movie, Alia Bhatt is a budding camera person in the movie industry, who faces relationship challenges, and seeks help of a psycho-therapist, played by Shahrukh Khan, to stabilize her life. Towards the end of the movie, with his help, she is able to manage her emotions well and is able to give some direction to her life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jayant: The Energy Field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170507-jayant/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170507-jayant/</guid>
      <description>The third energy field of the eastern direction is Jayant.
Zone: ENE
Sanskrit meaning of Jayant: Victorious.
Attributes:
Ensures success in all your undertakings. Imparts the zeal, the enthusiasm and vitality towards life.
Mythological Associations to Jayant:
The dev, Jayant, has appeared in the Sundara-kand in the form of a crow. Mythology has it that while Shri Ram slept with his head on Sita&amp;rsquo;s lap, her feet were pecked by a crow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 6 Part 1</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170430-dhyan-chapter6-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170430-dhyan-chapter6-part1/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra: 1.30 to 1.33
How to retain the experience of God: the meditative state.
In the previous sutras, Patanjali discussed the various challenges as - guilt, sadness, doubt, carelessness, laziness, indulgences, illusion, loss of clarity and mental disturbances. These states, disturb and disrupt the subconscious. With faith and dedication towards God, these states can be dissolved. These disturbed states cause mental stress, depression, breathlessness and tremors in the body. Actions conducted in these states do not yield to meaningful results and these results become the cause to depression, breathlessness and disturbances in body.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prajanya: The Energy Field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170423-prajanya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170423-prajanya/</guid>
      <description>This is second energy field in the eastern direction.
Sanskrit meaning:
 A Dev or Gandharva.
 Rain or thunder cloud.
 One of the 12 Adityas - In the Vedic literature, Adityas are referred to, as the children of Goddess Aditi, while the name Aditya, refers to the Sun. There are 12 Adityas in total, with every month of the hindu calendar being dedicated to each. Each of them is said to be a form of Lord Vishnu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 5</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170414-dhyan-chapter5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170414-dhyan-chapter5/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra: 1.23 to 1.29
The Experience of God.
There are various assumptions about God. However, Patanjali gives us the practical method to experience God in very clear, simple, and few terms. Through this method, the experience of God can occur in a very short time period. What should be the emotion embraced about God and why should one recite &amp;lsquo;OM&amp;rsquo; - these are the few things that Patanjali talks about in these sutras.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shikhi: The First Energy Field of the East</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170409-shikhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170409-shikhi/</guid>
      <description>The first energy field of the eastern direction is Shikhi.
Sanskrit meaning of Shikhi:
 A &amp;lsquo;pointed flame&amp;rsquo;. The minute form of Agni is known as Shikha. A ray of light. Shikhi is referred as “Mahadev Shiv” in the ancient text of Samrangan Sutradhar.  Attributes: Ideas and Vision.
This sacred red-energy field helps conceive ideas and and also helps condensing those ideas. All creations in this world begin with an idea, and our ability to conceive ideas is related to this energy field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Element of Fire</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170203-element-of-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170203-element-of-fire/</guid>
      <description>What do you see? The Element of Fire.
There is a very famous incident from Mahabharata where Guru Drona is teaching his young disciples, and he asks the question, &amp;ldquo;What do you see?&amp;rdquo; They all give different answers to the same question. These answers reveal a lot about their own personalities and the ongoing thought process within.
Among the few who were asked this question were the young Duryodhana, Ashwathama, and Arjun.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mahabharat: The Dharmayudha</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170128-dharmayudh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170128-dharmayudh/</guid>
      <description>Mahabharat is often referred to as the Dharmayudha; and
Kurukshetra as the Dharmakshetra.
The conflict symbolized here is not the one between the good and the evil, it is the conflict of the ideas of what we consider good and what we consider evil. And, this eternal conflict is internal. It lasts for ever, and is in our mind.
Nature presents us with three choices in our Breath in the form of three Nadis:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Varun and Indra</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170115-varun-indra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20170115-varun-indra/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Within infinite myths lies the eternal truth
Who sees it all?
Varuna has but a thousand eyes,
Indra has a hundred,
You and I, only two.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ndash; Devdutt Pattanaik
 Varun is the God of Waters. He is the God of oceans and the high seas. In the Vedic period, he was associated with the order and harmony. By the Puranic age, he gets associated with the high seas, oceans, and the direction of West.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Purpose of Life and the Play of Elements</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161230-purpose/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2016 11:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161230-purpose/</guid>
      <description>Does the Vastu of the home play an important role in attainment of this purpose?
Yes, It does. What we understand as Vastu &amp;ndash; the 16 Zones or the 45 Devtas &amp;ndash; is basically the play of the five elements: Space, Air, Fire, Earth, and Water in different permutations and combinations which are present in any given place and time. Let us evaluate each element and observe its role in this context.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 4</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161217-dhyan-chapter4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2016 18:43:37 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161217-dhyan-chapter4/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.17 to 1.22
Wisdom through Self-Realization.
Along with self realisation comes a new thought &amp;ndash; new insight &amp;ndash; imparting a &amp;ldquo;wow&amp;rdquo; feel. It feels as if some knot in the mind has been untangled and the mind is lighter, clearer, and is filled with new thoughts. Patanjali defines this state of mind with a new term &amp;ldquo;Sampragyata&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; insight or inner wisdom. Many a times, people consider this to be a state of Samadhi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Element of AIR</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161215-air/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 09:34:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161215-air/</guid>
      <description>One of the fundamental challenges faced by people is their inability to grasp the root of problems and address the same meaningfully. This can be in terms of Vastu or any other domain of life.
What does it take to grasp and understand a subject?
This happens simply as we fail to pay ‘Attention’. If we were to pay attention, the nuances and details of the subject would emerge to meet our eyes, which otherwise usually missed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 3</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161127-dhyan-chapter3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2016 09:55:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161127-dhyan-chapter3/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.12 to 1.16
Self realisation through Yog.
Recurring thoughts that surface on the subconscious mind can be controlled with Abhyasa (Practice) and Vairagya (Dispassion).
1.12 Patanjali Yog Sutra.
When, for the first time, I heard this from Guruji, an inner voice echoed saying that this is “impossible”; this cannot happen as I always believed that the flow of thoughts is natural! And also at the same time, got a feeling that &amp;ndash; hope my Guruji is not getting senile!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Garuda, Matali and Indra Dev: South-West</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161120-mahabharata/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 09:34:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161120-mahabharata/</guid>
      <description>Moments from Mahabharata: Garuda, Matali and Indra Dev (South-West).
Garuda was the king of birds. Matali was the charioteer to Indra Dev. One day, in a moment of arrogance, Garuda insisted on eating Sumukha &amp;ndash; the serpent, who was to be married to Matali&amp;rsquo;s daughter. Matali begs Garuda not to do so. Yet, Garuda refuses to budge. Finally, Matali requests Indra to intervene. To humble Garuda, Indra gently places his hand on his back.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 2</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161112-dhyan-chapter2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 08:33:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161112-dhyan-chapter2/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.5 to 1.11
There are five reasons that take one beyond the control of the self.
Recurring thoughts can be painful as well as non-painful. An example of painful thought can be, when the behaviour of a friend does not meet one’s expectation, or when one gets recurring thoughts of another’s painful behaviour. Or, when you do not get due recognition for your efforts.
These recurring thoughts become the cause of pain in the mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Chapter 1</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161030-dhyan-chapter1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161030-dhyan-chapter1/</guid>
      <description>Yog Sutra: Chapter 1.1 to 1.4
Yog means &amp;ndash; to stay within yourself.
Some thought patterns recur continuously in one&amp;rsquo;s subconscious. For example, if you had an argument with someone during the day, then just before bedtime the entire sequence of events replays on your mind just like a movie. Even though you do not wish to think about it, these thoughts continuously surface in your mind. For example, thoughts like “he should not have said this”, or “I should have said that”, or “I too tried to explain saying this”, or “why is he saying this?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dhyan: Introduction</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161027-dhyan-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 08:56:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161027-dhyan-intro/</guid>
      <description>Some events change the course of your life in a subtle, yet profound way. For me, one such event of life was being introduced to Patanjali Yog Sutras. During the preparation of the Advance Mahavastu course, KB sir entrusted me with the English translation of Patanjali Yog Sutras. Although it was a mammoth task and took a couple of months to translate, I enjoyed the journey. It helped me understand better the human mind and its workings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ashta Laxmi</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161007-ashta-laxmi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 09:34:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20161007-ashta-laxmi/</guid>
      <description>Traditional Vastu Shastra mentions about Ashta Laxmis or the 8 Laxmis residing in the 8 directions. What more auspicious days than these days of Navratri to pay homage to Ashta Laxmis? These Ashta Laxmis are situated as follows:
 Aishwarya Laxmi in the East Dhanya Laxmi in the South East Adi Laxmi in the South Dhairya Laxmi in the South West Gaj Laxmi in the West Vijaya Laxmi in the NorthWest Dhanlaxmi in the North &amp;amp; Santan Laxmi in the NorthEast  Aishwarya Laxmi of the East: Aishwarya Laxmi resides in the east.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Method of Meditation</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20160909-meditation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 09:34:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20160909-meditation/</guid>
      <description>Today is Ashtami, the eighth day of the month as per the lunar calendar. The transition phase between the Shukla Paksha Nadi (brighter half) and Krishna Paksha Nadi (darker half). This is one of the best days of the month for meditation, because Ashtami is the Day of Space element.
One of the most fundamental challenges faced by anyone who treads a spiritual path is &amp;ldquo;How to Meditate&amp;rdquo; effectively, and hence I want to share the Method of Mediation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 16</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra16/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra16/</guid>
      <description>tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam
The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.
Patanjali states, that we shall be able to gain vision of the self, our true nature, of what we actually are, the (purusha), when we are able to curb the desires arising from the three gunas, the satwa, the rajas and the tamas.
The concept of tri-gunas has originated from Samkhya philosophy, The closest English translation of this word is “quality”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tantra: An Introduction</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20160717-tantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2016 09:34:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20160717-tantra/</guid>
      <description>Tantra is an ancient method practiced in India by Yogis since ages where through the involvement of the mind, breath, body and senses, expansion of abilities and self awareness takes place. It opens many new dimensions which one would not be aware, otherwise.
It&amp;rsquo;s fundamental belief stems from the fact that there is one universal consciousness and we and everything that we see, are a part of it. Everything that we see, is interlinked and interconnected.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 15</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra15/</guid>
      <description>tat param purusha khyateh guna vaitrshnyam
The highest, most excellent supreme perception of pure soul awareness is achieved by trancending the three qualities of nature.
Patanjali states, that we shall be able to gain vision of the self, our true nature, of what we actually are, the (purusha), when we are able to curb the desires arising from the three gunas, the satwa, the rajas and the tamas.
The concept of tri-gunas has originated from Samkhya philosophy, The closest English translation of this word is “quality”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 14</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra14/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra14/</guid>
      <description>Sah tu dirgha kala nairantaira satkara asevitah dridha bhumih
Persistent and continues practice, with devotion, establishes a firm foundation.
After explaining the importance of unbiased practice, for controlling the fluctuations of the mind, Patanjali states that continuous practice with effort and devotion, is the way to establishes a firm rooted foundation.
In his book Outliers, author Malcolm Gladwell, says that it takes roughly ten thousand hours of practice to achieve mastery in a field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 13</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra13/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra13/</guid>
      <description>Tatra sthitau yatnah abhyasa
A practice, which is a deliberate effort to bring stability.
After stating in the previous sutras that continuous unbiased practice, is the way to control the thought whirls, in this sutra, Patanjali explains that deliberate practice of doing so, shall result into a stable mind. Here, Abhyasa refers, not just to mechanical efforts. It is an effort with your complete head and heart are involved. And it is done to such an extent, where it comes to a state where it gets effortless.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 12</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra12/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra12/</guid>
      <description>abhyasa vairagyabhyam tat nirodhah
These can be stopped by unbiased practice.
After explaining the five reasons for thought whirls, Patanjali shares the method to stop them. He suggests unbiased practice. He uses the term abhyasa and vairagya.
Abhyasa is when something is done with persistent effort for a long time. After long term practise, the activity gets effortless and with passing time, the individual is able to perform it with excellence and ease.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 11</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra11/</guid>
      <description>anubhuta vishaya asampramoshah smritih
Past remembrances are based on our inability to let go experiences.
Patanjali states, that our past remembrances or memories, whether painful or not, whether hurtful or not, become the last reason to our non-stop, unending thought whirls. Memories, whether good or bad, become the foundation to our feelings and this foundation, forms our mind-set. Whatever we experiance gets permanently recorded in our minds, and as per the context, this recording starts playing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 10</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra10/</guid>
      <description>abhava pratyaya alambana vritti nidra
Repetitive unawareness is based upon lack of exposure.
In this sutra, Patanjali states nindra as the fourth reason for hurtful or not hurtful thought whirls.
Nindra, our unawareness. Patanjali does not refer to it to sleep with closed eyes. He refers to that state of mind, that we live in 24x7, with our open eyes. It refers to a state, where, with open eyes, we are unable to see, observe or perceive!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 09</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra09/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra09/</guid>
      <description>sabda jnana anupati vastu sunyo vikalpah
Illusioned or Imagined situations are based on worded knowledge, devoid of substance.
In this sutra, Patanjali states, Vikalpa, as the third reason for hurtful or not hurtful thought whirls.
Vikalpa can be understood as the one based on imagination. Vikalpa is the one, which is Kalpaniic, illusionary. The environment that we live in, becomes the breeding ground to our imagination. What we perceive through our senses is the truth and nothing beyond that, is the truth - this kind of thinking is vikalpa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 08</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra08/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra08/</guid>
      <description>viparyayo mithya jnanam atadrupa pratistham
Misinterpretations are based upon false perceptions
Viparya, comes from the word Paryaya, and the meaning of Paryaya is interpretation. Vi means contrary to. So one that is contrary to interpretation, can be understood as misinterpretation.
Patanjali says incorrect knowledge, lack of information, wrong or distorted perception, form the base to misinterpretations.
Coming back to our example of the boy meets a girl at the wedding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pusha: The Strengthener</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20160707-pusha/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 09:34:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20160707-pusha/</guid>
      <description>Zone: SSE
The second energy in the southern direction is known as Pusha.
Sanskrit Meaning: To cause to thrive.
Attributes:
This energy field is associated with nourishing and strengthening. It has the attribute of MatrIguna or the Divine Mother. It is recommended to place to keep ghee, oil, and butter over here to strengthen and nourish the body. This energy field, along with Indra, is evoked to block the path of enemies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 07</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra07/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra07/</guid>
      <description>pratyaksa anumana agamah pramanani
Reasons for being right are based upon seen experiences, interpretations and ancient scriptures. In the previous sutras, Patanjali lists the 5 reasons for the thought whirls. Pramana or right knowledge, being the foremost in the list.
In this sutra, Patanjali, states, that Pramana, the knowledge, can be attained from three sources: seen or direct experiences, interpretation and ancient scriptures.
We, as humans, base our decisions or opinions on our judgements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 06</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra06/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra06/</guid>
      <description>pramana viparyaya vikalpa nidra smritayah
Being right, misinterpretation, illusion, unawareness, and past remembrances. After categorizing the thoughts patterns as hurting or not, Patanjali states the 5 sources from where these thought whirls emanate.
 Pramana / right Viparyaya / misinterpreted or incorrect Vikalpa / illusion imagined Nidra / unaware Smriti / based on past memories  Patanjali says that although we encounter countless types of thoughts, the reasons for these thoughts whirls can be divided into 5 categories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 05</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra05/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra05/</guid>
      <description>vrittayah pancatayah klisht aklishtah
Whether hurting or non hurting, repetitive thoughts are of five types.
After talking, what is Yog, and the benefits of establishing in our own nature, Patanjali explains that, what ever, the nature of thought that we witness, hurtful or not, we can divide it into 5 catagories.
The Mind becomes the gate to heaven, the mind become the gate to hell, says Osho. The whole point of Yoga are deeply concerned with the usage of the mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 04</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra04/</guid>
      <description>Vritti Swaroopam Itratra
At other times, the observer considers himself similar to his thought Whirls.
In this Sutra, Patanjali indicates how the fluctuations of mind affect you. If you don’t stop them, you will gradually start identifying yourself as you appear, in these fluctuations. Your swaroop will get lost in the forms of these fluctuations.
Hamare Gujratis mein ek kahavat hain, ke ghode ko hum, ghade ke saath bandh dete hain, toh ghoda bhi, thode dino ke baad, ghade jaisa bolne lagta hain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 03</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra03/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra03/</guid>
      <description>Tada drashta Swaroope Avasthanam
Then the observer, establishes in his own nature.
After asking us to be prepared for Yog, and explaining us, how to remove distractions, one is able to attain Yog. Patanjali, in this sutra, tells us, what will happen when one is able to take off distractions from one’s mind. He says that when we remove the distractions of the mind, we shall be able to establish in our own nature, our original form.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 02</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra02/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra02/</guid>
      <description>Yog Chitta Vritti Nirodah
Yog is stopping the Whirls of repetitive thoughts in subconscious
After asking us to be prepared, Patanjali directly comes to the point. Though this sutra is just the second sutra, it holds the key, to the entire samadhi pad.
It says that Yog, union, is only possible, when one removes all kind of obstacles. all kind of disturbances, all kind of fluctuations from one’s mind.
Mind – what are the different states of mind?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yogsutra: Chapter 1 Sutra 01</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra01/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/yogsutra_chapter1_sutra01/</guid>
      <description>Before we start, I would want to thank -
The wind beneath my wings,
For holding me strong as I weathered the storm,
For helping me soar and ensuring I rise,
To the wind beneath my winds.
Gratitude to you, the reader of this blog.
Chapter one: Sutra one.
Atha Yog Anushasanam
Now, the journey of Yog.
The word “now” is very important here. it shows that you are starting now, with a kind of preparation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>As Above, So Below: Understanding Vastu Through the Power of Swar</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20160609-above-below/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 21:34:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20160609-above-below/</guid>
      <description>Dennis W. Hauck translates the understanding of this cosmic law as, &amp;ldquo;That which is Below corresponds to that which is Above, and that which is Above corresponds to that which is Below, to accomplish the miracle of the One Thing.&amp;rdquo;
Whatever happens on any one plane, whether physical, emotional, or mental, it also happens on every other plane. Everything in this universe is inter-connected, co-related, is in-synchronicity, in-alignment, and has very powerful influences and connections with us.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yog Sutras of Patanjali: Audio</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20150915-yog-sutra-audio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20150915-yog-sutra-audio/</guid>
      <description>During the journey of Advance Course, I was given an opportunity to translate the Patanjali Yog Sutras, compiled by KB Sir, in English. With time, these sutras became an integral part of my life. Today, I attempt to share my understanding of them.
Yog sutras, formulated about 5000 years ago, are a practical guide to a happy and meaningful life. They guide us, step by step, on how to keep our minds free from fluctuations, so that we can focus on our goals and attain them with ease.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ashta Siddhis</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20150605-ashta-siddhis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2015 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20150605-ashta-siddhis/</guid>
      <description>Although sharing Advance Course contents is strictly prohibited, but after showing my write up on Siddhis and an urge to share the absolute wisdom nuggets, I got permission from KB sir to share it with ME family. It has been an pleasure hearing KB Sir comment on Patanjali during Advance Course. Through his interesting and contemporary analysis of the subject, he has brought life to the age old Yog Sutras and have made them very interesting and relevant for the common man of today&amp;rsquo;s world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bhringraj: The Discriminator</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20150402-bhringraj/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20150402-bhringraj/</guid>
      <description>Zone: SSW.
The gold colored energy field, seventh in the southern direction, is known as Bhringraj.
Attributes:
This energy field imparts residents discretionary powers to retain the best and meaningful, and discard the rest.
Mythologically, Bhringraj is said to be the son of Nairuti, the demon.
The oil extracted from Bhringraj plant is used by Hindus during &amp;lsquo;Shrad&amp;rsquo;, the ceremony for paying respect to a recently deceased person. This plant is one of Hinduism’s “Ten Auspicious Flowers” and it&amp;rsquo;s oil is called “the king of hair oil.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aditi and Diti: The Intriguing and Opposing Energy Fields</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20141212-aditi-and-diti/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2014 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20141212-aditi-and-diti/</guid>
      <description>In Hindu mythology, Aditi and Diti are referred to as the wives of Sage Kshayap and the daughters of legendary King Prajapati Dakhsa, son of Brahma. In vastu shastra, NorthEast encompasses the energy Diti and NNE encompasses the energy field of Aditi. Below, I have tried to summarize my understanding of these two mythical, powerful energy fields that exist right next to each other on the Mahavastu shakti-chakra.
Aditi In Sanskrit, Aditi means limitless, unbound, free, and unfettered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clutter: The Influence of SSW in Rest of the Zones</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20140916-clutter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2014 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20140916-clutter/</guid>
      <description>Rarely does anyone talk about this or hardly does one consider this to be a cause for concern. But a space full of clutter is just incapable of inviting peace and prosperity.
Clutter comes in many forms. It can be emotional (I am unable to dispose, my kids&amp;rsquo; first t-shirts, their baby books, their first toys) or it can be in the form of clothes that I once bought, but no longer fit in!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Energy fields of Rog and Nag</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20141215-rog-and-nag/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2014 08:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20141215-rog-and-nag/</guid>
      <description>Rog: The Weakener The first energy field from the northern direction is called Rog.
Sanskrit Meaning: Sickness or disease or breaking of the strength.
Zone: NW
Attribute:
Roga means Jvara or fever. And the lunar divinity ruling it is Svati ( Nakshatra). The ruling deity of Svati is mentioned to be Vayu. Vayu, here is referred as, the not just as the God of Wind, but also the &amp;lsquo;Prana&amp;rsquo;, the breath of life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The 5 Elements of Effective Thinking</title>
      <link>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20140824-5-elements/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2014 07:17:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swarodaya.com/blog/20140824-5-elements/</guid>
      <description>Title: The 5 Elements of Effective Thinking
Authors: Edward B. Burger and Michael Starbird
This simple and beautifully written book explains how the attributes of 5 elements (Earth, Fire, Air, Water and Space), can be used to form the basis of highly effective thinking. It talks about the principles, based on the characteristics of 5 elements, that help us in understanding the unknown, finding creative insights and transforming our life. These principles can be taught, learned, and applied broadly across various disciplines and professions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>